<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>2016 &#8211; 2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
	<atom:link href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/tag/2016/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/</link>
	<description>Gene and Cell Therapy</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 16:27:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.5.6</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>2016 &#8211; 2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
	<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>2016 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Highlights</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/day-three-highlights/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 16:27:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=2392</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Highlights of the Day Day Three of the World Medical Innovation Forum was short, but was filled with some of the most exciting aspects of the meeting. The first session touched on the needs of cancer patients who require alternative strategies to achieve optimal therapeutic benefit, and the advantages and challenges associated with combination therapy. ... <a title="2016 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Highlights" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/day-three-highlights/" aria-label="More on 2016 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Highlights">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/day-three-highlights/">2016 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Highlights</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><img src="http://image.s6.exacttarget.com/lib/fe8f127274650d797c/m/1/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160427_1732-150-HEADER.jpg" alt="WMIF Header" /></strong></p>
<h2>Highlights of the Day</h2>
<p>Day Three of the World Medical Innovation Forum was short, but was filled with some of the most exciting aspects of the meeting. The first session touched on the needs of cancer patients who require alternative strategies to achieve optimal therapeutic benefit, and the advantages and challenges associated with combination therapy.</p>
<p>The opening session was followed by a fireside chat with Joseph Jimenez, CEO of Novartis, who provided insight into Novartis&#8217; successes and discussed current topics including CRISPR, CAR-T, a second generation of immuno-oncology, and the biggest threats to the future of innovation.</p>
<p>The morning continued with a session in which panelists discussed new cancer diagnostics driven by advances in genetics, genomics and proteomics, and the integration of these technologies into the delivery of care. This panel was followed by a discussion around the evolving role of disease-focused philanthropic foundations in patient care. For more in-depth highlights from Day Three, see below.</p>
<p>The capstone event of the Forum was the announcement of the <a href="http://cl.s6.exct.net/?qs=fc8c9e0c70cd2e56edd5b51f67c06c849eec650f884e68e52cb45eb35ed3fe5b">Disruptive Dozen</a>, the 12 technologies predicted to have the greatest impact on cancer care in the next decade. The main stage was filled with 12 influential leaders in cancer research and clinical care from Massachusetts General Hospital, Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital and Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, who came together for an exciting and insightful discussion around these state-of-the-art medical technologies and what they mean for the future of the field.</p>
<p>The Forum closed with notes from Anne Klibanski, MD, Chief Academic Officer of Partners HealthCare, who noted that one of the greatest accomplishments of the Forum was the facilitation of a new community; a community that can shift paradigms and accelerate cures by having open dialogue, understanding priorities, and incorporating patient needs, expectations, and quality of life issues, and posed a challenge to the audience to maintain this dialogue even after conclusion of the meeting.</p>
<p>Next year, the Forum will focus on cardiovascular disease and will be held from May 1-3, 2017 at the Westin Copley in Boston, Massachusetts.</p>
<p><img src="http://image.s6.exacttarget.com/lib/fe8f127274650d797c/m/1/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160427_1732-150-2.jpg" alt="2016 World Forum" /></p>
<h2>New Philanthropy: Patients Driving Innovation</h2>
<p>As part of continued discussion around patient-driven innovation, the New Philanthropy session provided insight into the efforts of philanthropic leaders and how their community is redefining its role to develop new ways to help patients and drive breakthroughs. As disease foundations become more involved in all aspects of patient care, including the lab, clinic, engagement, and regulatory approval process, their role has evolved.</p>
<p>As gaps in funding for basic and translational research grow, these organizations have provided extensive financial support to the cancer research community, which has led to the development of breakthrough therapies and promising technologies. As Louis DeGennaro, PhD, President and CEO of the Leukemia and Lymphoma Society, pointed out their foundation funded the basic research that eventually led to the development of Gleevec and supported early efforts in the development of CAR-T technology at the University of Pennsylvania. Additionally, Judy Salerno, MD, President and CEO of Susan G. Komen for the Cure, emphasized the importance of funding young investigators and remarked that, as funding has dried up, we are starving a pipeline of next-generation investigators who are needed to advance progress.</p>
<p>To provide this support, fundraising is essential, and the panel discussed the role of athletic events and social media in driving their efforts. As Dr. DeGennaro observed, cancer patients &#8220;want to win,&#8221; and athletic events such as walks, challenges, and races are a practical manifestation of that desire and are successful because &#8220;people give to people.&#8221; Supporting that notion, Billy Starr, Founder and Executive Director of the Pan-Mass Challenge, added that today&#8217;s technology allows people to reach out to their world and create bonds and opportunities that are distinct from the impact of direct mail or celebrity spokespeople. When asked about the influence of the ALS Ice Bucket Challenge and whether they would consider that type of engagement for their audiences, Judy Salerno, MD, President and CEO of Susan G. Komen for the Cure, noted that their focus tends to be more directed toward the recruitment and development of people who are passionate about their mission and can become advocates.</p>
<p>To push for faster cures, panelists noted that their organizations are facilitating ongoing dialogue between patients and the FDA to address issues, concerns, and preferences, and training advocates in science to better disseminate their message. Additionally, as money raised from the Pan-Mass Challenge is donated exclusively to treatment and research at the Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Mr. Starr also noted the patient role in the design of the Yawkey Center for Cancer Care, which was intended to advance clinical care and enhance the patient experience.</p>
<h2>Disruptive Dozen</h2>
<p>After rigorous consideration by cancer faculty from the Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital, Massachusetts General Hospital, and Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, the 12 technologies that are predicted to have the greatest impact on cancer care in the next decade were announced. After a short audio clip describing their disruptive technology, panelists representing each of the 12 areas enlightened the audience as to why their respective fields would have an impact on the future of cancer care in a series of sound bites.</p>
<p>Following a major theme of the Forum, and perhaps unsurprisingly, cellular immunotherapy was announced as the most disruptive technology for the next decade. Marcela Maus, MD, PhD, Director of Cellular Immunotherapy at MGH, highlighted the promise of this technology by stating that it has the potential to become a frontline cancer therapy and noting the unprecedented results seen in some patient populations thus far. However, she also noted that there are obstacles to overcome in the development of this technology for the treatment of solid tumors, which can be addressed by identifying new targets, using different engineering strategies to distinguish tumor from self, and targeting the tumor microenvironment.</p>
<p>The second runner-up for most disruptive technology was liquid biopsy for oncology, and Shyamala Maheswaran, PhD, Associate in Molecular Biology, Surgery at MGH, praised the benefits of more frequent, less invasive sampling methods as compared to tumor biopsy and described the applications of this technology in early detection of cancer, monitoring of therapy, evaluation of mutational status to direct therapeutics, and assessment of heterogeneity between tumor cells for a deeper understanding of tumor evolution.</p>
<p>Coming in at number seven, genome editing was represented by Keith Joung, MD, PhD, Associate Chief of Pathology for Research at MGH. When posed the question, &#8220;how crisp are CRISPRs?&#8221; by Forum Co-Chair Daniel Haber, MD, PhD, Director of the MGH Cancer Center, Dr. Joung explained that, while limiting off-target effects at this time is a challenge, we have a distinct opportunity to develop treatments for diseases in which there are no therapies currently available and should proceed with the understanding that the technology will evolve and improve over time.</p>
<h2>Fireside Chat: Joseph Jimenez, CEO, Novartis</h2>
<p>Rounding out the fireside chat series, Joseph Jimenez, CEO of Novartis, sat down with Gregg Meyer, MD, Chief Clinical Officer at Partners Healthcare System to discuss:</p>
<ul>
<li>Changes that need to take place in the &#8220;healthcare system as a whole to a platform where all patients have access to therapies&#8221;</li>
<li>The company&#8217;s &#8220;IO strategy is to be strong with second generation approaches that target the tumor microenvironment&#8221; and the &#8220;shift away from a transactional approach to outcomes-based approach&#8221;</li>
<li>The four pillars: clinical value, patient value, health system value and societal value</li>
<li>The importance of intellectual property for driving innovation &#8211; &#8220;there are no generics without innovation&#8221;</li>
<li>The relatively low cost and continuing benefits, often extending over decades, of a drug once it comes off patent should be included in discussions of drug pricing</li>
</ul>
<h2>Notable Tweets</h2>
<p>@lisamjarvis<br />
<a href="http://cl.s6.exct.net/?qs=b51a26116e379d1f601459fc4e9e21cc521a5eca4fe7232f151001776ea880ea">$NVS Jimenez: Just launched NVS Access&#8211;bringing 15 molecules to least dev countries, priced at $1/month/treatment #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@EmmaHokie<br />
<a href="http://cl.s6.exct.net/?qs=b51a26116e379d1f1969f9ebe7c3ff5a4d641648fbe4aadb36fba95aa0889f6e">Jimenez @Novartis: Intellectual property is the most important driver of innovation. There are no generics without #innovation. #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@PearlF<br />
<a href="http://cl.s6.exct.net/?qs=b51a26116e379d1f453cc07b3efc65425b8036be7fbfccb1cf7c9fa3bedfa8c6">Foundation Medicine CEO on reimbursement environment for Dx: Reimbursement is abysmal #wmif16</a></p>
<p>@AEDeconinck<br />
<a href="http://cl.s6.exct.net/?qs=b51a26116e379d1f8a50bffddb22509b52fba61f60ab67f60707a34444a38246">Why do FDA approved therapies get reimbursed but approval of test does not guarantee reimbursement? @MichaelPellini @FoundationATCG #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@bnikhil<br />
<a href="http://cl.s6.exct.net/?qs=b51a26116e379d1f0b22d17ab916585ee80b3f904a80a25f85a9fed1c50d84bb">3 challenges in cancer meds: Delivery, delivery, delivery #nanotechnology #WMIF16 Dr Farokhzad @BrighamWomens</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/day-three-highlights/">2016 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Highlights</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2016 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Highlights</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/highlights-day-two-2016/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 16:06:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=2386</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Highlights of the Day Day Two of the World Medical Innovation Forum was brimming with fireside chats and panel discussions. The first session of the day highlighted the growing global cancer burden in which panelists from leading international companies and key government entities discussed the challenges to providing innovative technologies in diverse markets, as well ... <a title="2016 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Highlights" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/highlights-day-two-2016/" aria-label="More on 2016 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Highlights">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/highlights-day-two-2016/">2016 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Highlights</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-HEADER.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-2389 size-full" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-HEADER.jpg" alt="Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-HEADER" width="600" height="100" /></a></p>
<h2>Highlights of the Day</h2>
<p>Day Two of the World Medical Innovation Forum was brimming with fireside chats and panel discussions. The first session of the day highlighted the growing global cancer burden in which panelists from leading international companies and key government entities discussed the challenges to providing innovative technologies in diverse markets, as well as potential strategies to overcome these obstacles.</p>
<p>In the second panel, experts provided an in-depth discussion on the promise of epigenetics for cancer research, describing the complex science behind the regulation of how genetic information is processed and the development of therapies that leverage these alterations to target cancer.</p>
<p>Two panels focused on the promise of immunotherapeutic strategies for the treatment of cancer, highlighting the recent burst in the field of immuno-oncology. A set of fireside chats provided insights into drug pricing, data sharing, collaboration, and patient-driven innovation.</p>
<p>The final plenary session, moderated by CNBC Biotech and Pharma Reporter Meg Tirrell, saw a panel of oncology investors discuss some of the most compelling topics in the industry today, including the most promising technologies, investment trends, comparison to other periods in cancer investing and, naturally, drug pricing.</p>
<p>The day concluded with four concurrent focus sessions, which provided discussion around radiation therapy, oncology devices, study design for personalized cancer medicine, and the unique challenges posed by increased cancer survivorship. For more in-depth highlights from some of the most interesting panels from Day Two, see below.</p>
<p>Notably, panelists demonstrated surprising candor when discussing their personal struggles with cancer, and seemed optimistic about the current trajectory of science, with the word &#8220;cure&#8221; being used more freely in the context of cancer and without reservations of this being a crazy notion, emphasizing the reality of working towards cures.</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2390" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2.jpg" alt="Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2" width="600" height="200" /></a></p>
<h2>Global Cancer Markets</h2>
<p>As the global cancer burden is expected to increase from 14 million to 22 million cases by 2030, panelists from leading international companies and a key governmental entity, namely the famed National Institute for Health and Care Excellence at the UK NHS, discussed the future of cancer in a global market. Moderator Sheila Dharmarajan, Head of Business Development at Zelnick Media Capital, started out by emphasizing the term &#8220;tremendous&#8221; to describe not only the prolificacy of cancer, but also to describe the complexity of the market, breakthrough technology, and the dollars at stake in terms of both pricing and cost of innovation.</p>
<p>When posed with the question of whether pharmaceutical companies should fund diagnostics, panelists acknowledged that, due to the innate differences in business models, each company must decide their own path, but Bruno Strigini, President of Novartis Oncology, also noted the importance of considering the development of targeted therapies with companion diagnostics, which can be critical to providing the right products to the right patients.</p>
<p>Additionally, Newton Crenshaw, Vice President of North America Oncology at Eli Lilly and Company, stressed the importance of symbiosis between diagnostic and therapeutic companies, and indicated that reform is needed for regulatory bodies to accelerate diagnostics and provide access to patients. Following up on this point, Gillian Leng, MD, Deputy Chief Executive and Director of Health and Social Care at NICE, stated that this relationship could be most effective if regulatory bodies were allowed to evaluate the drug and diagnostic together.</p>
<p>As technology advances and we begin to consider cancer to be a chronic rather than terminal condition, Mr. Crenshaw also posed the question of how to best support patients beyond medicine, but noted that the cost burden of long-term treatment must be considered, as well.</p>
<h2>Immunotherapy: Checkpoint Activation, Cancer Vaccines, and Cell Based Therapies</h2>
<p>Day Two featured two panels on the promise of immunotherapy in cancer treatment in which panelists discussed various approaches to leveraging the human immune system to fight cancer, including checkpoint inhibition, anticancer vaccines, and CARTs.</p>
<p>In the first session, panelists were cautiously optimistic about immunotherapy as a tool for cancer treatment and agreed that this wave of enthusiasm is still in its early stages and we must proceed by paying particular attention to the determinants of tumor response and resistance. In this context, a recurring message was the importance of tissue biopsy and biomarker analysis before and during treatment, which will be critical to the understanding of what is happening to patients at a molecular level and, as Scott Rodig, MD, PhD, Associate Professor at Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital, mentioned, will be extremely important in the determination of rational drug combinations going forward.</p>
<p>Similarly, panelists also stressed that we should think carefully about how we are approaching combination therapy; rather than using a shotgun approach in which we try every drug combination, we should be deliberate in understanding the underlying mechanisms to predict optimal patient populations and avoid toxicity. More specifically, Thomas Daniel, MD, Chairman of Celgene Research, stated that we should be considering the patients for which combinations are medically valuable, along with a scientific grounding for why a specific combination makes sense, which is a more tractable and financially feasible option as compared to the shotgun approach.</p>
<p>David Reese, MD, Senior Vice President of Translational Sciences at Amgen, noted that a major challenge in the field at present is a need for the development of new surrogates for traditional response criteria; as patients live longer and overall survival becomes increasingly difficult to measure, some trial designs will essentially become intractable.</p>
<p>The second immunotherapy panel discussed what&#8217;s next for CAR T-cell therapy, with Usman (Oz) Azam, MD, Global Head of Cell and Gene Therapies Unit at Novartis, referring to the current technology to as &#8220;version 1.0.&#8221; Panelists discussed the promise of CART in hematological malignancies, but as Mark Frohlich, MD, Executive Vice President of Portfolio Strategy at Juno Therapeutics, pointed out, we must still determine the right targets for solid tumors.</p>
<p>When quizzed about the future of the technology, Dr. Azam also mentioned that gene therapy could be utilized to take CARTs to the next level, which Chuck Wilson, PhD, CEO of Unum Therapeutics, expanded upon by suggesting that the use of gene editing to target specific genes, create allogeneic T cells, or inhibit signaling pathways, could support the work of CARTs.</p>
<p>Dr. Wilson also reminded the audience that the reality is, as an autologous cell therapy, the logistics of taking cells from the patient, manufacturing cells, and returning them to the patient, will be inherently more costly than other therapies, but that scalability could bring this cost down. Additionally, as Marcela Maus, MD, PhD, Director of Cellular Immunotherapy at MGH, pointed out, the development of point-of-care methods or &#8220;off-the-shelf&#8221; T cells that could treat many patients with one lot are potentially less costly.</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-3.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2391" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-3.jpg" alt="Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-3" width="600" height="200" /></a></p>
<h2>Fireside Chat Roundup</h2>
<p>The first two days of the Forum were filled with fireside chats, which allowed for an intimate perspective on pricing, the importance of data sharing, academic and industry collaborations, current healthcare challenges, and much more.</p>
<p>Kicking off the first fireside chat of the Forum on Monday evening, Richard Gonzalez, CEO of AbbVie, sat down with Nancy Snyderman, MD, Medical Advisor, GE Healthymagination, to discuss:</p>
<ul>
<li>The acquisition of Pharmacyclics and the &#8220;blind dating process&#8221;</li>
<li>&#8220;Doubling down on R&amp;D&#8221; to bring a consistent stream of good medicines</li>
<li>Catering to patients by &#8220;bringing improvements for standard of care&#8221; that the healthcare system would reward</li>
<li>The most important model today of &#8220;partnering with academic and biotech&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>Tuesday&#8217;s lineup of fireside chats started with Amgen&#8217;s CEO Robert Bradway and Bloomberg&#8217;s biotech reporter Caroline Chen on a variety of topics including:</p>
<ul>
<li>The need &#8220;to collaborate outside of your organization, especially with cancer&#8221;</li>
<li>The costly price tag that comes with innovation but &#8220;the need to focus on the benefit that it brings for society&#8221;</li>
<li>Project Data Sphere, an independent and not-for-profit initiative of the CEO Roundtable on Cancer&#8217;s Life Science Consortium (learn more here).</li>
<li>A call to society to invest more in cancer prevention</li>
</ul>
<p>With nine months left on the job, Andy Slavitt, Acting Administrator for the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (CMS), spoke candidly with CNBC&#8217;s biotech and pharma reporter, Meg Tirrell on:</p>
<ul>
<li>The need for new payment models because governments don&#8217;t have &#8220;magic pots of money&#8221; and &#8220;we are still in the 1st and 2nd generation of pricing models&#8221;</li>
<li>Finding new ways to care for the &#8220;most difficult people with the lowest income and are disconnected from the healthcare system&#8221;</li>
<li>Pilot programs for cost containment and spurring innovation focused on &#8220;doubling down on primary care and prevention&#8221;</li>
<li>The qualifications for the next CMS administrator &#8211; &#8220;doesn&#8217;t need the job, doesn&#8217;t see it as a stepping stone, doesn&#8217;t need to make friends, and has struggled to find and provide care&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>Praising the industry for its strides in finding important cures for cancer, Bristol-Myers Squibb CEO, Giovanni Caforio, MD, started off his chat with Meg Tirrell by highlighting three critical points to being a leading company in oncology: keeping the patient at the center, following the science and collaborations with industry and academia. Other topics included:</p>
<ul>
<li>The need for &#8220;different payment models and flexibility in the healthcare system&#8221;</li>
<li>The &#8220;beginning stages of understanding why patients don&#8217;t respond to immunotherapies&#8221;</li>
<li>The need to focus on biomarkers as &#8220;they are really important&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>Rounding out today&#8217;s fireside chats, &#8220;patient scientist&#8221; Kathy Giusti, Founder of the Multiple Myeloma Research Foundation and Multiple Myeloma Research Consortium, spoke with Nancy Snyderman, MD, to discuss her journey:</p>
<ul>
<li>Being a patient advocate, patient and business disruptor who has elevated attention and propelled advancements for multiple myeloma</li>
<li>The need for data sharing for research and cures</li>
<li>The &#8220;tough lifting&#8221; that comes with trying to stay on top of the cancer landscape</li>
<li>Partnership with Harvard Business School to &#8220;put together a business plan by which business and science could start disrupting&#8221; and &#8220;to bring the absolute best-in-class to ask the tough questions and to share and solve the problem&#8221;</li>
<li>How she made the decision to stop her own treatment</li>
</ul>
<h2>Live Coverage on CNBC</h2>
<p><a href="http://video.cnbc.com/gallery/?video=3000512872">View Meg Tirrell&#8217;s interview with Bristol-Myers Squibb CEO Giovanni Caforio</a></p>
<h2>Notable Tweets</h2>
<p>@PartnersWMIF<br />
.@ASlavitt @CMSGov says focusing on affordability won&#8217;t hurt innovation @megtirrell @CNBC #WMIF16</p>
<p>@Novartis<br />
It&#8217;s important to agree on what value-based outcomes means. It&#8217;s not just about cost but value to patients &amp; society -Bruno Strigini #WMIF16</p>
<p>‏@megtirrell<br />
Parachuting into Boston for the day for #WMIF16 &#8211; looking forward to some great panels &amp; our live intvw w $BMY CEO on @PowerLunch. Tune in!</p>
<p>@lisamjarvis<br />
$CELG&#8217;s Daniels: big challenge: anchoring IO combo regimens around testable biological hypotheses #WMIF16</p>
<p>‏@BWHResearch<br />
Dr. Sharpe: As we move forward, we need to understand the impact of dif therapies (targeted, radiation, chemo) on the immune system. #wmif16</p>
<p>@TomLynchMGH<br />
Two Things: Notable items from Tom Lynch, MD 4/26/2016: http://youtu.be/Pe85aTmrAu8?a via @YouTube</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/highlights-day-two-2016/">2016 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Highlights</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2016 World Forum &#8211; Day One Highlights</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/highlights-day-one/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 13:41:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=2368</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>    Day One of the World Medical Innovation Forum began with a wave of young investigators highlighting promising developments in cancer research in a series of rapid-fire presentations. Recurring themes of the First Look session included the use of RNA in-situ hybridization (RNA-ISH) as a diagnostic tool, liquid biopsies for exosome analysis, and precision ... <a title="2016 World Forum &#8211; Day One Highlights" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/highlights-day-one/" aria-label="More on 2016 World Forum &#8211; Day One Highlights">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/highlights-day-one/">2016 World Forum &#8211; Day One Highlights</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8366.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2369" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8366-300x200.jpg" alt="_MG_8366" width="300" height="200" /></a>  <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1393.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2371" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1393-300x200.jpg" alt="_H8A1393" width="300" height="200" /></a>  <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8378.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2370" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8378-300x200.jpg" alt="_MG_8378" width="300" height="200" /></a></p>
<p>Day One of the World Medical Innovation Forum began with a wave of young investigators highlighting promising developments in cancer research in a series of rapid-fire presentations. Recurring themes of the First Look session included the use of RNA in-situ hybridization (RNA-ISH) as a diagnostic tool, liquid biopsies for exosome analysis, and precision medicine approaches to patient care. Multiple presentations also highlighted the capabilities of the AMIGO suite at Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital, which uses intraoperative imaging to guide precise localization and analysis of patient tumors during surgery.</p>
<p>Attendees then had the chance to liaise with established Harvard Medical School faculty over lunch during the Discovery Café session, which paired interested Forum-goers with renowned leaders in their respective fields. Nearly 30 faculty members covered topics such as immunotherapy, diagnostics, therapy resistance, and the potential of CRISPR for research and therapeutics.</p>
<p>The Forum plenary opened with David Torchiana, MD, CEO and Anne Klibanski MD, Chief Academic Officer of Partners HealthCare, who welcomed an audience representing more than two dozen countries and introduced a program filled with high-caliber speakers and hot topics including immunotherapy, epigenetics, and bioinformatics. They emphasized the importance of collaboration to accomplish the goal of providing better care and support to cancer patients and their families and noted that the &#8220;engine of innovation is running better than ever&#8221; as we seek to push the boundaries of the many diseases collectively known as cancer.</p>
<p>After a series of thought-provoking sessions, Astellas Pharma announced the launch of the inaugural C3 Prize<img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.0.0/72x72/2122.png" alt="™" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />. The day culminated with inspiring remarks from Greg Simon, Executive Director, The White House Moonshot Initiative and a fireside chat with Richard Gonzalez, CEO of AbbVie (stay tuned for more about the Forum&#8217;s fireside chats in tomorrow&#8217;s Day Two recap). For more in-depth highlights from some of the most interesting panels from Day One, see below.</p>
<h2>A War or Moonshot: Where Do We Stand?</h2>
<p>In the first panel of the day, Nancy Snyderman, MD, Medical Advisor at GE Healthymagination, sat down with Monica Bertagnolli, MD, Chief of the Division of Surgical Oncology at Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital, and Daniel Haber, MD, PhD, Director of the MGH Cancer Center to discuss what&#8217;s to come in a new era of cancer research and care. The panelists were tasked with advising on whether cancer research and care over the next decade will be a war or a moonshot. Panelists agreed on both perspectives &#8211; a war because, from a patient perspective, it is a personal battle against disease and we must come together as an army to combat the disease and work effectively towards a cure, and a moonshot because progress in cancer happens with huge steps forward and reflects the combined efforts of a large group of people working toward a common goal, much like landing on the moon.</p>
<p>When asked about the funding landscape and future of academic research and development in oncology, Dr. Bertagnolli noted that, when money is tight, teamwork must be utilized, and support from patient organizations such as Stand Up To Cancer is profound. Dr. Haber also noted that we are at a magic time during which so much science is being translated, but that funds are also needed for basic research, with the rationale that, if all money goes to translational research and we do not value basic discovery, then there will be nothing to translate in the coming years.</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1644.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2372" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1644-300x200.jpg" alt="_H8A1644" width="300" height="200" /></a>  <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1752.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2373" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1752-300x200.jpg" alt="_H8A1752" width="300" height="200" /></a>  <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1799.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2374" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1799-300x200.jpg" alt="_H8A1799" width="300" height="200" /></a></p>
<h2>Creating a Disruptive Cancer Pipeline and Winning Portfolio Strategy</h2>
<p>A focus of Day One included cancer pipeline and portfolio development, which began with a panel discussion of how to build and maintain a successful pipeline in a challenging environment. Panelists including Keith Flaherty, MD, Director of Clinical Research at the MGH Cancer Center, and Sean Harper, MD, Executive Vice President of Research and Development at Amgen, commenting on company culture and regulatory oversight of clinical trials.</p>
<p>Jay Bradner, MD, President of the Novartis Institutes for BioMedical Research, noted that we may not be able to visualize what a cure for cancer will look like at this time, as technologies are still emerging, but that we should beware of paradigms, as they can sometimes make you blind to the next breaking wave.</p>
<p>In a discussion of clinical trial participation, panelists stressed the need for improved navigation of study information for patients, which would in turn facilitate the interactions between these patients and their physicians and potentially improve recruitment. It was also noted that these patients should have access to expert opinion on the best trials for their disease; as George Demetri, MD, Director of the Center for Sarcoma and Bone Oncology at Dana-Farber Cancer Institute noted, it should not be so much easier to find the best Chinese restaurants on &#8220;Dr. Google&#8221; than it is to find the best clinical trial.</p>
<p>Panelists discussed the need for improved infrastructure that would hasten the timeline from ideas to clinical trials and noted that the FDA is responsive to novel approaches and is looking to industry and academia for advice. Dr. Demetri also noted that such an idea is on the table, with the proposed creation of an Oncology Center of Excellence at the FDA.</p>
<p>Overall, panelists indicated that the pharmaceutical industry is receptive to insight from academia, and that the field appears to be aligned in the early drug discovery mission. In a discussion of the interactions between small companies and big pharma, panelists noted that the small companies tend to be very innovative, but investments are risky. Sean Harper, MD, noted that pharma tends to be very open to bringing assets in to their pipeline, but would rather engage early on to ensure that it&#8217;s a good product, and that takes engineering.</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A8454.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2377" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A8454-300x200.jpg" alt="_H8A8454" width="300" height="200" /></a>  <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8432.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2375" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8432-300x200.jpg" alt="_MG_8432" width="300" height="200" /></a>  <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8445.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2376" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8445-300x200.jpg" alt="_MG_8445" width="300" height="200" /></a></p>
<h2>Curative Therapies: The Economics of Game-Changing Science</h2>
<p>As novel, potentially curative cancer therapies come to market, drug pricing has emerged as one of the hottest topics of discussion. Speakers shared their insights on the balance between affordability and continued innovation in the healthcare industry, which was emphasized by Betsy Nabel, MD, with the notion that we need to provide the &#8220;right treatment for the right patients at the right time&#8221; while making it affordable.</p>
<p>Speakers included Troy Brennan, MD, Executive Vice President and CMO of CVS Health, Paul Hudson, President of AstraZeneca US, Betsy Nabel, MD, President of Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital, Gary Reedy, CEO of the American Cancer Society, and Peter Slavin, MD, President of Massachusetts General Hospital. The panel was moderated by Sue Siegel, CEO of GE Healthymagination.</p>
<p>In the session, panelists discussed how to measure the effectiveness of a treatment. Dr. Slavin noted that we are facing much more economic pressure in healthcare and that it is critical to eliminate care that doesn&#8217;t help our patients. Panelists suggested that the private sector, including commercial payers, academic medical centers, pharmaceutical industry, biotech, venture, and pharmacy should come together to determine the value framework, rather than leaving it to CMS.</p>
<p>Mr. Hudson noted an inherent risk associated with developing medicines, and that the demand for breakthroughs and targeting of smaller patient populations has never been higher, while Dr. Nabel reminded us that companies must also consider the costs associated with innovation, as well as the hidden cost for future development if innovation is left behind. Panelists suggested that pharmaceutical companies, insurance providers, and pharmacy benefit management companies should come together to share risk, as all parties would be incentivized if the risk is broadly distributed.</p>
<p>When asked about when cancer will become a chronic disease, a majority of the panel agreed that it would be within 10 years, while one panelist noted that, in some patient populations, the time is now.</p>
<h2>Notable Tweets</h2>
<p>@BrighamWomens<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/BrighamWomens/status/724685238237028355">&#8220;We want to ensure that our patients have access to clinical trials &amp; effective therapies.&#8221;- Dr. Betsy Nabel #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@MassGeneralNews<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/MassGeneralNews/status/724603589621108736">Are miniature devices the next tool in diagnosing + tracking #cancer? #MGH&#8217;s Hakho Lee discussing now #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@Novartis<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/Novartis/status/724691948683055104">We can&#8217;t be surprised we haven&#8217;t cured #cancer when we haven&#8217;t figured out how to respond to all its dominant causes -@jaybradner #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@bmsnews<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/bmsnews/status/724675347183230976">This is a historic time in cancer research. The opportunity is unprecedented. #ImmunoOncology research. #WMIF16.</a></p>
<p>@PartnersWMIF<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/PartnersWMIF/status/724656825027682304">.@JayBradner, Pres of @NovartisScience: &#8220;We have to beware of current paradigms&#8230; Can make us blind to next breaking wave.&#8221; #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@CarolineYLChen<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/CarolineYLChen/status/724747692841291776">$ABBV Gonzalez says his perspective as a cancer patient has made him go ahead w testing drugs in small populations that may not have big ROI</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/highlights-day-one/">2016 World Forum &#8211; Day One Highlights</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Kathy Giusti: A Profile in Innovation</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/kathy-giusti-profile-innovation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2016 17:34:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=2342</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>What if choosing the very best treatment for any given cancer were as routine as choosing the right kind of antibiotic to treat a common infection? Kathy Giusti, founder of the Multiple Myeloma Research Foundation (MMRF), and a cancer patient herself, has made it her personal mission. She foresees the day when an individual’s medical ... <a title="Kathy Giusti: A Profile in Innovation" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/kathy-giusti-profile-innovation/" aria-label="More on Kathy Giusti: A Profile in Innovation">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/kathy-giusti-profile-innovation/">Kathy Giusti: A Profile in Innovation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What if choosing the very best treatment for any given cancer were as routine as choosing the right kind of antibiotic to treat a common infection?</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/KG_Headshot.jpg" rel="attachment wp-att-2296"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-2296" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/KG_Headshot.jpg" alt="Kathy Giusti" width="225" height="304" /></a>Kathy Giusti, founder of the Multiple Myeloma Research Foundation (MMRF), and a cancer patient herself, has made it her personal mission. She foresees the day when an individual’s medical care will be tailored in part based on each person’s genetic make-up and other unique characteristics of his or her disease.</p>
<p>“The days of a one-size fits all approach to cancer treatment are over. We can do better than that,” Giusti said.</p>
<p>The kind of precision oncology for which Giusti advocates has already proven lifesaving for some. Patients with many forms of cancer, for instance, undergo molecular testing as a standard part of their care, enabling physicians to select treatments based on this information.</p>
<p>“Armed with focused genetic and molecular information about their patient’s distinct disease, physicians can develop personalized treatment strategies designed for maximum effectiveness,” she said.</p>
<p>But making this routine, Giusti says, requires innovative research models that prize and data-sharing and collaboration to make unprecedented advancements, an approach for which the MMRF has become widely recognized. The MMRF, by working closely with partners in the biotech and pharmaceutical industries, academia, and the cancer community, injects speed and efficiency into the process of discovering and developing new drugs for the treatment of multiple myeloma.  Through this collective approach, myeloma patients now have 10 new treatments – 4 treatments FDA approved in 2015 alone &#8211; that have almost tripled their survival and given thousands of others living with this incurable disease a fighting chance.</p>
<p>Now, Giusti believes this same collaborative approach can be used to usher in a new era of precision medicine and its promise of a cure: the MMRF has pioneered an end-to-end solution specifically focused on precision medicine in oncology.</p>
<p>“We generate the data, we share and aggregate the data, we analyze the data, and draw insights from these data to develop optimal treatment strategies for patients,” she said.</p>
<p>At the core of the model is a robust data ecosystem, including the first multicenter multiple myeloma tissue bank. This endeavor allowed the MMRF, along with its best-in-class partners, to sequence the myeloma genome.  The MMRF also launched the expansive, comprehensive MMRF CoMMpass<img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.0.0/72x72/2122.png" alt="™" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /> (Relating Clinical Outcomes in Multiple Myeloma to Personal Assessment of Genetic Profile) study, which has performed whole genome sequencing on over 1,000 patients and generated the largest longitudinal genomic dataset in myeloma in the public domain. The MMRF then collaborated with partners like the Translational Genomics Research Institute (TGen) and the Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard, to uncover deeper insights into the disease’s biology, such as BRAF, a target previously never linked to myeloma but for which treatments have already been approved for melanoma or are now in clinical trials.</p>
<p>“Studying a large number of people – deeply and over time – allowed us to ask and answer new questions that were never before possible,” Giusti explained.</p>
<p>Today, through CoMMpass study, the MMRF is tracking the progress of these same 1,000+ patients for at least 8 years, analyzing their genetic and clinical data to better understand how certain factors influence response to treatment and disease progression and to generate hypotheses for genomically informed clinical trials. Most importantly, these data are then openly and freely shared through a global learning network, so that brilliant minds from all corners of the scientific community—including experts at the big data analytics company GNS Healthcare—can collaboratively decipher patterns for further exploration. This network was built to democratize data, allowing researchers and clinicians worldwide to share and contribute to a growing knowledge base that can be used to generate hypotheses for clinical trials and rapidly explore new and potentially more effective ways of treating myeloma.</p>
<p>Any findings can be immediately advanced into the MMRF’s worldwide network of research institutions and cancer centers that are working collectively to test an arsenal of new drugs and combination therapies. More than 30 new therapies have been in clinical trials in the network, including genomically-informed treatments – that is, those that target specific alterations in an individual that give rise to cancer or promote its spread – and immunotherapies, like checkpoint inhibitors and immunostimulatory antibodies, which are drugs that make use of a patient’s own immune system to fight cancer.</p>
<p>The MMRF’s model also includes a community of patients, who Giusti says are “every bit a part of curing the disease as scientists”.</p>
<p>These patients are stepping up to share knowledge they have gained on their cancer journeys with fellow patients—including sequencing data, when available—so they can learn which type of myeloma they have and share their data to advance research.</p>
<p>“We consider these patients as partners in our search for better, more targeted treatments,” said Giusti.</p>
<p>“As these patients, eventually, have their genomes sequenced and learn which, if any, mutations they have, can connect with other patients, engage with researchers who specialize in that particular area of genomics, and sign up for clinical trials that might be appropriate for them,” said Giusti.</p>
<p>Giusti will share more details of the MMRF’s innovative end-to-end solution for precision medicine as she sits down on April 26<sup>th</sup> for a fireside chat with Dr. Nancy Snyderman to discuss “Patients Driving Innovation” at the 2016 World Medical Innovation Forum, hosted by Partners Healthcare in Boston.</p>
<p>The World Medical Innovation Forum is a global gathering of more than 1,100 senior health care leaders hosted by Partners HealthCare in the heart of Boston. It was established to respond to the intensifying transformation of health care and its impact on innovation. The Forum is rooted in the belief that no matter the magnitude of that change, the center of health care needs to be a shared, fundamental commitment to collaborative innovation – industry and academia working together and its ability to improve patient lives.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/kathy-giusti-profile-innovation/">Kathy Giusti: A Profile in Innovation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Social Media at WMIF 2016: Engage with Us!</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/social-media-wmif-2016-engage-us/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 18:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=2340</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>World Medical Innovation Forum 2016 is quickly approaching! Would you like to engage with us throughout the Forum and hear about all of the speakers, panels and presentations? If so, connect with us on Twitter and lookout for our blog posts. Our blog will provide daily roundups of the Forum and keep you informed about ... <a title="Social Media at WMIF 2016: Engage with Us!" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/social-media-wmif-2016-engage-us/" aria-label="More on Social Media at WMIF 2016: Engage with Us!">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/social-media-wmif-2016-engage-us/">Social Media at WMIF 2016: Engage with Us!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">World Medical Innovation Forum 2016</a> is quickly approaching! Would you like to engage with us throughout the Forum and hear about all of the speakers, panels and presentations? If so, connect with us on Twitter and lookout for our <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/blog/">blog posts</a>.</p>
<p>Our <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/blog/">blog</a> will provide daily roundups of the Forum and keep you informed about the established leaders in cancer who will be attending and keynoting the event. Members of our team will also be live Tweeting from many of the panels and presentations.</p>
<p>You can use Twitter to not only keep up with the day’s panel discussions but also to engage in conversations with other participants and share insights into the innovations of cancer care that will be explored throughout the three-day event. Simply follow @PartnersWMIF and use #WMIF16 to join in on the conversation.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/social-media-wmif-2016-engage-us/">Social Media at WMIF 2016: Engage with Us!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Second Glimpse at First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs.</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/second-glimpse-first-look-next-wave-cancer-breakthroughs/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2016 18:38:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=2335</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A Second Glimpse at First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs. For our last blog feature, we spoke with Alexander Lin, PhD, Director of the Center for Clinical Spectroscopy at Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Assistant Professor of Radiology at Harvard Medical School, and gave you a preview of his upcoming First Look presentation, ... <a title="A Second Glimpse at First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs." class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/second-glimpse-first-look-next-wave-cancer-breakthroughs/" aria-label="More on A Second Glimpse at First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs.">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/second-glimpse-first-look-next-wave-cancer-breakthroughs/">A Second Glimpse at First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs.</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>A Second Glimpse at First Look: </strong><strong>The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs.</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Mark-Cobbold.jpg" rel="attachment wp-att-2296"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-2296" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Mark-Cobbold.jpg" alt="Dr. Mark Cobbold" width="210" height="294" /></a><strong><em>For </em></strong><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/firstlooknextwave/"><strong><em>our last blog feature</em></strong></a><strong><em>, we spoke with Alexander Lin, PhD, Director of the Center for Clinical Spectroscopy at Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Assistant Professor of Radiology at Harvard Medical School, and gave you a preview of his upcoming First Look presentation, “</em></strong><strong><em>Making the Virtual Biopsy a Reality: Advances in MR Spectroscopy of Cancer.” Our second sneak peek at the exciting discoveries to be featured in the First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs session comes from our conversation with </em></strong><a href="http://www.massgeneral.org/research/researchlab.aspx?id=1645"><strong><em>Mark Cobbold</em></strong></a><strong><em>, MRCP, PhD</em></strong><strong><em>, Associate Professor of Medicine at the Massachusetts General Hospital (MGH) Cancer Center and Harvard Medical School. Dr. Cobbold is a member of the MGH Center for Cancer Immunology and his research focuses on understanding how the healthy human-immune response is able to recognize and target cancerous cells and, when it fails, how it could be strengthened to recognize this threat. </em></strong></p>
<p><strong><em>Dr. Cobbold’s presentation will focus on “Tumor Antigens in Cancer and How to Manipulate Antigens to Stimulate Immunity.” You can catch him and a wide variety of creative minds presenting their most promising commercially related research during First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs, happening at the start of the Forum on Monday, April 25. </em></strong><strong><em>These rapid-fire presentations by early-career Harvard Medical School faculty will highlight compelling new discoveries and insights that will be the cancer care products of the future. </em></strong></p>
<p><strong>Tell us about yourself and why you have an interest in the World Forum:</strong></p>
<p>We moved my lab, the Cobbold Lab, about 9 months ago from Britain to the MGH Cancer Center and we’re currently looking into different immunotherapies for cancer. The research we’re conducting has lead me to conclude that most people have experienced some early form of cancer, but our immune response has protected us from these insults. We believe that in many cases it is when our immune response fails that we develop cancer. The solution we’ve developed is designed to strengthens the immune system to address the cancer in a very different but targeted way, instead of suppressing immunity like treatment with chemotherapy or radiotherapy.</p>
<p>Let me explain this a bit further. We have ionizing radiation going through our bodies every second of every day, and our cells accumulate a small number of genetic errors (mutations) regularly. Life is a process of genetic decay, and I passionately believe that as a long-lived animal living to about 80, which is our genetic life expectancy, we probably all develop cancerous cells thousands of times throughout our lifetime. Thankfully, there are multiple processes that prevent cancer from taking hold, some intrinsic to each cell through DNA repair and damage detection, and some extrinsic. Epidemiological data clearly shows for the first 50 years of our lives the incidence of cancer is very low suggesting that our bodies keep it at bay, and an immunological mechanism may play a dominant role in this. However, once you get past the age of 50, particularly once we get past 70, the incidence of cancer increases very rapidly. This correlates very strongly with the age at which our immunity starts to fail. Until recently, drug companies have been focused on finding ways to suppress immune responses to prevent the body from attacking itself (for patients with autoimmune disease). There is a huge arsenal of drugs available that can be prescribed to suppress immunity. In contrast there are very few drugs available that strengthen our immunity.  What we desperately need are new agents to stimulate and restore immunity and the pharmaceutical industry needs to spend the next 10-20 years developing such therapies.</p>
<p>My research is born out of real curiosity. We all have family members that have died from cancer, but I can’t say that’s what driven me to science. I’m driven really through intellectual curiosity and a desire to do something useful for society. In translating discoveries from the lab into the clinic, the process of innovation is critical for patients’ benefits, and the World Medical Innovation Forum seems to be particularly aligned and targeted towards that particular audience. I do a lot of work that could translate into the clinic, sort of bridging both sides of that pond, so the premise of the Forum is very close to my heart.</p>
<p><strong>Can you tell us a little about the Cobbold Lab and the work you’re currently doing with MGH?</strong></p>
<p>My lab at the moment is just getting off the ground, having been in the US for less than a year. One of the main projects we’re working on is how our immune system is able to identify the difference between healthy cells and cancer cells. In a sense, our immune systems are playing a continuous “Spot the Difference” picture game, where the immune system has got to look at the difference between the upper and lower picture panels, and sometimes the difference is not that easy to distinguish. To an immune cell (T-cell) a cancer cell could be a dividing healthy cell or an enemy, based on the coating around the cell. The question is how does the immune system spot the difference?</p>
<p>So part of my lab’s focus is taking a non-cancerous cell and a cancerous cell and characterizing the peptides on the surface of the cells. The immune system basically interrogates the peptide display on the cell surface and determines the difference between cells. We use a technique called Mass Spectrometry which is able to characterize peptides and spot the differences between cancerous and non-cancerous cells.</p>
<p>All cells are composed of proteins, and our DNA although critical to each cell, can be seen as just the instruction book that makes proteins. It is the proteins that function as the active parts of the cell; however, these parts can be decorated which controls their function. To use a baking analogy, the proteins can be thought of as cakes with the cell as the bakery. Using this analogy, the healthy cell bakery and the cancer cell bakery usually have the same cakes on sale.  However, the decorations on the cakes are very different. In the cancer cell bakery, the cherries (reflecting phosphate groups) haven’t been put on in the correct places, often showing extra cherries. A lot of research groups are looking for the “cake” vaccine. In my lab, we’re not interested in the actual the <em>types</em> of cakes. Instead, we are analyzing their differences by looking at what the cakes are decorated with, i.e. where the cherries lie.</p>
<p>The proteins in a cell are “decorated” with phosphate groups and sugar groups through a process called posttranslational modifications, which is like sprinkling cherries on top to maintain the baking analogy, and the number of cherries present changes multiple times during a cell’s lifetime. The difference between cancer and non-cancer cells is that the cherries, or phosphate groups, are put in different places and it turns out that these groups are retained when the proteins are chopped up and displayed on the surface of the cells. We believe this identifies a cell as either cancerous or not. Ultimately we can either look at the different cakes that exist, or we can examine how they’re decorated to determine a course of action for treatments and therapies.</p>
<p>Despite failing immunity <em>against</em> cancer, people with cancer still have strong immunity to viruses. Thus patients with cancer usually still have strong functioning immunity, it just isn’t focused on cancer. What we’re proposing is to decorate cancer cells to make them look like the viruses that people already have immunity to. In this way we are matching what is displayed on the tumors with what T-cells we have.</p>
<p>Arguably, we’ve got everything wrong right now with cancer therapies. From an immunology point of view, we are essentially strengthening the cancer by giving it new mutations through the use of radiation and chemotherapy, while suppressing the immune response at the same time. We are trying to poison the cancer and in the process end up poisoning everything else as well. Too often these treatments, unfortunately, only give patients a couple of extra months, and seldom curing the patient entirely. Currently, there is huge excitement in potentiating anti-cancer immunity and understanding how the immune system can detect and kill tumors, but also how tumors evade detection and control.</p>
<p><strong>What do you find is the most challenging aspect of your work? </strong></p>
<p>Well that’s a challenging question on its own! I’d have to say getting a hold of the right clinical material and data from patients is a challenge, and getting the right people and funding to continue pursuing one’s research is critical.</p>
<p><strong>Why did you come to the US?</strong></p>
<p>For those challenges really. Funding is a bit of a challenge everywhere. Competition is really high; I think there are too many researchers applying for the same pot of money. This keeps the quality of research high; but the price is huge sector inefficiency. I’m a bit of a paradox here, because I think it’s easier to get funding in Europe than in the U.S., and thus I’ve moved into a more challenging funding environment. But this is more than balanced by the huge opportunities here. Boston/Cambridge is one of the largest life sciences ecosystems in the world and thus a very efficient place to work, and that is a big draw on its own. There’s a lot of good stuff going on here, and from a life sciences’ perspective this place rocks.</p>
<p><strong>Will you be spending some time at the Forum after the First Look session?</strong></p>
<p>I’ll probably be staying around for a fair amount of it. I want these meetings to yield real actions that can produce real results for patients. This seems to be the ideal Forum to connect the right people together to really achieve something that hasn’t been done before. I’m excited to see what happens next!</p>
<p><em>The First Look session is shaping up to be an interesting dive into the most innovative technologies, treatments and therapies that are currently in the early stages of development.</em> <em>These brilliant investigators from Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Massachusetts General Hospital and Dana-Farber Cancer Institute will each describe their work in highly organized 10-minute sessions. Access for this exclusive faculty engagement event is included in the World Forum registration.</em> <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/2016-world-medical-innovation-forum-registration-16705377233">Register Today!</a></p>
<p>The World Medical Innovation Forum is a global gathering of more than 1,100 senior health care leaders hosted by Partners HealthCare in the heart of Boston. It was established to respond to the intensifying transformation of health care and its impact on innovation. The Forum is rooted in the belief that no matter the magnitude of that change, the center of health care needs to be a shared, fundamental commitment to collaborative innovation – industry and academia working together to improve patient lives. The 2016 World Medical Innovation Forum features the newest technologies to diagnose, treat and manage cancer. <a href="http://www.medforum17.wpengine.com/">www.medforum17.wpengine.com</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/second-glimpse-first-look-next-wave-cancer-breakthroughs/">A Second Glimpse at First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs.</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/firstlooknextwave/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2016 15:33:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=2301</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The World Medical Innovation Forum is excited to launch First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs. During this session, which opens the Forum on Monday, April 25, we will hear from a wide variety of creative minds on their most promising commercially related research, and what drives their passions every day. These rapid-fire presentations ... <a title="First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/firstlooknextwave/" aria-label="More on First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/firstlooknextwave/">First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>The World Medical Innovation Forum is excited to launch First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs.</em></strong></p>
<p><strong><em>During this session, which opens the Forum on Monday, April 25, we will hear from a wide variety of creative minds on their most promising commercially related research, and what drives their passions every day.</em></strong></p>
<p><strong><em>These rapid-fire presentations by early-career Harvard Medical School faculty will highlight compelling new discoveries and insights that will be the cancer care products of the future. </em></strong></p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Dr-Alex-Lin.jpg" rel="attachment wp-att-2296"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-2296" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Dr-Alex-Lin.jpg" alt="Dr-Alex-Lin" width="200" height="208" /></a><strong><em>One of the investigators presenting at the First Look session is <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/speakers/alexander-lin-phd/">Alexander Lin, PhD</a>, Director of the Center for Clinical Spectroscopy at Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Assistant Professor of Radiology at Harvard Medical School. Dr. Lin’s presentation will focus on “Making the Virtual Biopsy a Reality: Advances in MR Spectroscopy of Cancer.” His research interests include clinical applications of multinuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy in the brain, breast, and liver, and cardiovascular magnetic resonance imaging. We recently had a chance to talk with Dr. Lin and hear more about the research he’s conducting, his goals moving forward, and what he finds most challenging in his work.</em></strong></p>
<p><strong>Please tell us about yourself and your interests in the World Forum:</strong><br />
I’ve been working in the field of magnetic spectroscopy for about 18 years now. It’s a very powerful research tool that affects many areas in neurological diseases, but it’s never really crossed over into clinical use. That’s one of my big goals, and that’s really why I came to the Brigham to try to translate this really powerful technology into the clinic.</p>
<p>Instead of getting pictures of the brain, or whatever body part that one typically does with an MRI machine, we measure the chemistry. The power of this technique is it allows us to really get a better understanding of what is going on pathophysiologically in the brain and other parts of the body. This technology is available on every MRI scanner and these chemicals that we can measure, the phrase we use is “Virtual Biopsy,” allow us to really get at what’s going within the tissue of the brain itself.</p>
<p>When we looked at ideas that could be commercialized, I really wanted to push something that I felt would be very clinically relevant and important. Take for example, a very specific marker for cancer – 2-hydroxyglutarate, a chemical that is produced only by a mutation that is found in about 70% of all brain tumors. The potential to use magnetic spectroscopy to measure this chemical is something that oncologists are really excited about. They have been ordering these [virtual biopsy] tests on patients, while also being a part of a number of clinical trials developing this technology further.</p>
<p>Connecting with potential collaborators who can help to advance the commercial application of magnetic spectroscopy is a part of my interest in the Forum. We’re already using this technology in clinics today, but one of the big barriers to widespread use and adoption has been that the software that we use to currently use analyze data has always been in the hands of people like myself, researchers. These research tools are not designed to be easy to use. It’s not designed to be friendly. It’s powerful and very accurate but difficult for clinicians to use within their workflow.</p>
<p><strong>Your recent Innovation Grant from BWH Department of Radiology and Innovation Hub focused on magnetic spectroscopy Tell us a little more about BrainSpec and what you’re hoping to accomplish:</strong><br />
I was very lucky to have a wonderful physicist working with me, Ben Rowland, who is also a brilliant programmer, and he, too, felt the ability to analyze data on this level was something that has been missing from the field. Together with Alex Zimmerman, from Harvard Business School, we put together BrainSpec, which is a web-based software platform to provide a brain cancer diagnosis within minutes without any surgical intervention and 100% specificity. This software is designed by radiologists for radiologists, and we have been working in conjunction with the Brigham Radiology Team as well as people even from MassArts and other local universities to really develop a software that would be intuitive and easy to use for people. Much in the way that Apple strives for simplicity in its products, you could almost call it the “Apple of spectroscopy” because it really tends towards being easy to use, therefore making it easier to implement in the clinic and to move this kind of technology forward.</p>
<p><strong>What do you find is the most challenging aspect of developing these kinds of technologies to facilitate early-detection?</strong><br />
For me, as a researcher, I’m not used to the business world. The requirements that are needed to take something from a prototype and turn it into a commercial product, such as FDA approval, are things I’m learning along the way. What’s been really valuable and fortunate is that we have the innovation staff at the Brigham and across Partners that have been incredibly helpful and supportive in trying to get this out there. The Brigham iHub really helped guide us through the process of what things are important and what are not in terms of developing a prototype. As a scientist you often get wrapped up in looking at the bigger picture and they really helped me stay on top of the important things, such as the user interface design. This platform will be fully automated and will allow us to get the results almost instantaneously, we’re talking maybe two or three minutes for it to spit back the information. Time and usability have been driving factors in BrainSpec’s development. As a researcher you just say, “Oh whatever, I’ll just code it” but there’s so much more to it and this has been very different and forced us to approach this platform in a very different way, which is of course new and exciting to me. It’s a newer way of looking at science than I had done before.</p>
<p>For the most part, this kind of technology has not been made available to the more general medical public, but we find it is currently thriving in academic settings. You have to find someone like myself who has experience in magnetic spectroscopy to translate the data as it stands right now. Making this more available on a clinical level is one of the goals of BrainSpec.</p>
<p><strong>Do you have plans to stay for the Forum after the First Look session?</strong><br />
Yes! I definitely want to see what else is happening and take part in this great networking opportunity. I’m entering this world of innovation so much more as of late, and there are interesting challenges I find myself facing as a faculty member in a hospital environment. It will be great to hear others discuss this issue, as well as other areas of development in oncology research.</p>
<hr />
<p>Dr. Lin’s research is just one of the exciting presentations featured in the First Look session. If identifying new high impact cancer technology is your passion—as an investor, company leader, donor, entrepreneur or investigator—this session is for you. These young stars from Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Massachusetts General Hospital and Dana-Farber Cancer Institute will each describe their work in highly organized 10-minute sessions. Access for this exclusive faculty engagement event is included in the World Forum registration. Register Today!</p>
<p>The World Medical Innovation Forum is a global gathering of more than 1,100 senior health care leaders hosted by Partners HealthCare in the heart of Boston. It was established to respond to the intensifying transformation of health care and its impact on innovation. The Forum is rooted in the belief that no matter the magnitude of that change, the center of health care needs to be a shared, fundamental commitment to collaborative innovation – industry and academia working together to improve patient lives. The 2016 World Medical Innovation Forum features the newest technologies to diagnose, treat and manage cancer.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/firstlooknextwave/">First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
