<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
	<atom:link href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/</link>
	<description>Gene and Cell Therapy</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 20:58:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.5.6</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
	<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Realizing the Promise of AI in the Clinic</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/realizing-the-promise-of-ai-in-the-clinic/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nicole Motta]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 20:51:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[healthcare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[STAT]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[World Medical Innovation Forum]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=8287</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Click here to view the full article from STAT By Gregg Meyer, MD, Chief Clinical Officer, Partners HealthCare The gap between development of AI and its use and integration in the clinic is closing, as technology, sophisticated algorithms, data sets, and computational capacity are now directly supporting both clinicians and patient care in clinical settings. ... <a title="Realizing the Promise of AI in the Clinic" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/realizing-the-promise-of-ai-in-the-clinic/" aria-label="More on Realizing the Promise of AI in the Clinic">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/realizing-the-promise-of-ai-in-the-clinic/">Realizing the Promise of AI in the Clinic</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.statnews.com/sponsor/2020/01/16/realizing-the-promise-of-ai-in-the-clinic/">Click here to view the full article from STAT</a></p>
<p><em>By Gregg Meyer, MD, Chief Clinical Officer, Partners HealthCare</em></p>
<p>The gap between development of AI and its use and integration in the clinic is closing, as technology, sophisticated algorithms, data sets, and computational capacity are now directly supporting both clinicians and patient care in clinical settings. Yet, realizing the full impact of AI for patient care and improved diagnostic decision making will depend on a wider community of patients, caregivers, legislators, and data scientists working together to maximize its potential.</p>
<p>AI’s path to implementation in health care began with a strong-hold in back-office functions. Record keeping and coding through natural language processing are two very real examples that are now making their way to office visits, and AI has helped improve the accuracy and speed of these and other operational applications. But what most patients want to know is, when will AI help my doctor make a more accurate diagnosis for my condition?</p>
<p>Patients are asking for AI to deliver meaningful insights on conditions that are specific “to people like me.” AI has the potential to take personalized medicine to an entirely new level, offering tools that create personalized results that apply either to specific populations or individuals.</p>
<p>This next phase of AI development in health care depends on advancements in computing power, the composition and size of data sets, and the comfort level of patients, physicians, and regulators in managing and unleashing this potential.</p>
<h3><strong>Safe patient data repositories</strong></h3>
<p>To realize these advancements, it’s critical to develop safe data repositories without bias. This requires that patients and society at large engage more fully in health data collection and expand the thinking about contributing data to better understand personalized health experience and outcomes. Like our engagement with on-line banking and web-based commerce, which has become customary for most, we must manage the benefits and risks of data sharing while capturing its innumerable benefits, which in this case could be life-saving.</p>
<p>As providers we must also embrace the expanded role of physician data scientists, through development of critical skill sets that will be built, taught, and cultivated throughout medicine. Physicians with the ability to understand and use data in practice will be even better caregivers to patients.</p>
<p>If health care can harness data for improving patient care with the right guidelines and protections, it will continue to advance and realize the promise of truly personalized medical care and treatment. Let’s encourage healthy debate on how to navigate this in health care policy and regulatory considerations, while engaging consumers in understanding the value of data and AI in health care — it’s a massive education opportunity for patients and physicians alike.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Healthcare providers and members of venture and industry are invited to learn more about the future of medicine and clinical deployment of AI at the <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">World Medical Innovation Forum.</a></strong></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/realizing-the-promise-of-ai-in-the-clinic/">Realizing the Promise of AI in the Clinic</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Top 12 Disruptive Health Care AI Technologies Announced</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/top-12-disruptive-health-care-ai-technologies-announced/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Beth Mollineaux]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2019 13:49:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=6537</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Medical Imaging, Mental Health, Suicide Prevention Make the List of Coming Applications Partners HealthCare today announced its selections for the fifth annual “Disruptive Dozen,” the 12 emerging artificial intelligence (AI) technologies with the greatest potential to impact health care in the next year. The technologies were featured as part of the World Medical Innovation Forum ... <a title="Top 12 Disruptive Health Care AI Technologies Announced" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/top-12-disruptive-health-care-ai-technologies-announced/" aria-label="More on Top 12 Disruptive Health Care AI Technologies Announced">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/top-12-disruptive-health-care-ai-technologies-announced/">Top 12 Disruptive Health Care AI Technologies Announced</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 class="subheadline">Medical Imaging, Mental Health, Suicide Prevention Make the List of Coming Applications</h2>
<div id="content-L2">
<p>Partners HealthCare today announced its selections for the fifth annual “Disruptive Dozen,” the 12 emerging artificial intelligence (AI) technologies with the greatest potential to impact health care in the next year. The technologies were featured as part of the World Medical Innovation Forum (wmif21.sitedistrict.com) held in Boston to examine AI in clinical care including a range of diseases and health system opportunities.</p>
<p>“Understanding state-of-the-art medical technologies enables us to anticipate the future of clinical care,” says Gregg Meyer, MD, Chief Clinical Officer, Partners HealthCare and 2019 World Forum Co-Chair.  “The Disruptive Dozen technologies can offer physicians and patients a renewed sense of optimism about Artificial Intelligence and its impact on diagnosis and treatment.”</p>
<p>The 2019 Partners HealthCare Disruptive Dozen are:</p>
<p><b>1 Reimagining Medical Imaging</b> – AI is transforming radiology and imaging, including mammography and ultrasound, to bring improvements in clinical care and diagnoses to patients worldwide. Researchers envision AI transforming mammography from one-size-fits-all to a more targeted tool for assessing breast cancer risk, and further increasing utility for ultrasound for disease detection and rapid acquisition of clinical-grade images.</p>
<p><b>2 Better Prediction of Suicide Risk</b> – Suicide is the 10<sup>th</sup> leading cause of death in the U.S. and the second leading cause of death among young people. AI is proving powerful in helping identify patients at risk of suicide (based on EHR data,) and also examining social media content with the goal of detecting early warning signs of suicide. These efforts toward an early warning system could help alert physicians, mental health professionals and family members when someone in their care needs help. These technologies are under development and not cleared for clinical use.</p>
<p><b>3 Streamlining Diagnosis </b>– The application of AI in clinical workflows such as imaging and pathology is ushering in a new era of AI-enabled disease diagnosis. From identifying abnormal and potentially life-threatening findings in medical imaging, to screening pathology cases according to the presence of urgent findings such as cancer cells, AI is poised to aid the diagnostic, prognostic, and treatment decisions that clinicians make while caring for patients.</p>
<p><b>4 Automated Malaria Detection </b>&#8212; Nearly half a million people succumbed to malaria in 2017, with the majority being children under five. Deep learning technologies are helping automate malaria diagnosis, with software to detect and quantify malaria parasites with 90 percent accuracy and specificity. Such an automated approach to malaria detection and diagnosis could benefit millions of people worldwide by helping to deliver more accurate and timely diagnoses and could enable better monitoring of treatment efficacy.</p>
<p><b>5 Real-time Monitoring and Analysis of Brain Health – a Window on the Brain – </b>A new world of real-time monitoring of the brain promises to dramatically improve patient care. By automating the manual and painstaking analysis of EEGs and other high-frequency wave forms, clinicians can rapidly detect electrical abnormalities that signal trouble.  Deep learning algorithms based on terabytes of EEG data are helping to automatically detect seizures in the critically ill, regardless of the underlying cause of illness.</p>
<p><b>6 “A-Eye”: Artificial Intelligence for Eye Health and Disease </b>– Not only is AI is helping advance new approaches in ophthalmology, it’s demonstrating the ability of AI-enabled technologies to enhance primary care with specialty level diagnostics. In 2018, the Food and Drug Administration approved a new AI-based system for the detection of diabetic retinopathy, marking the first fully automated, AI-based diagnostic tool approved for market in the U.S. that does not require additional expert review. The technology could also play a role in low-resource settings, where access to ophthalmologic care may be limited.</p>
<p><b>7 Lighting a “FHIR” Under Health Information Exchange &#8212; </b>A new data standard, known as the Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources (FHIR) has become the de facto standard for sharing medical and other health-related information. With its modern, web-based approach to health information exchange, FHIR promises to enable a new world of possibilities rooted in patient-centered care. While this new world is just emerging, it promises to give patients unfettered access to their own health information — allowing them to decide what they want to share and with whom and demanding careful consideration of data privacy and security.</p>
<p><b>8 Reducing the Burden of Health Care Administration &#8212; </b>use of AI to automate routine and highly repetitious administrative functions. In the U.S., more than 25% of health care expenditures are due to administrative costs, far surpassing all other developed nations. One important area where AI could have a sizeable impact is medical coding and billing, where AI can develop automated approaches. The goal is to help reduce the complexity of the coding and billing process thereby reducing the number of mistakes and minimize the need for intense regulatory oversight.</p>
<p><b>9 A Revolution in Acute Stroke Care &#8212; </b>Stroke is a major cause of death and disability across the world and a significant source of health care spending. Each year in the U.S., nearly 800,000 people suffer from a stroke, with a cost of roughly $34 billion. AI tools to help automate the diagnostic journey of ischemic stroke can help determine whether there is bleeding within the brain — a crucial early insight that helps doctors select the proper treatment. These algorithms can automatically review a patient’s head CT scan to identify a cerebral hemorrhage as well as help localize its source and determine the volume of brain tissue affected.</p>
<p><b>10 The Hidden Signs of Intimate Partner Violence </b>– Researchers are working to develop AI-enabled tools that can help alert clinicians if a patient’s injuries likely stem from intimate partner violence (IPV). Through an AI-enabled system, they hope to help break the silence that surrounds IPV by empowering clinicians with powerful, data-driven tools. While screening for intimate partner violence (IPV) can help detect and prevent future violence, less than 30% of IPV cases seen in the ER are appropriately flagged as abuse-related. Health care providers are optimistic that AI tools will further complement their role as a trusted source for divulging abuse.</p>
<p><b>11 Voice-first Technology Comes to Health Care &#8212; </b>AI-powered, voice-first technology is coming to the clinic. Using speech recognition and natural language processing, several companies are developing tools designed to help clinicians deliver better care and provide more of what matters: quality time with patients. Voice assistants are being explored for reducing physicians’ data entry burdens. Health care technology companies are developing applications that can run on consumer-grade voice technology platforms while complying with the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act, or HIPAA.</p>
<p><b>12 Narrowing the Gaps in Mental Health Care &#8212; </b>In the U.S., mental illness has reached epidemic proportions; nearly one in five adults grapples with a mental disorder, and opioid addiction and misuse claim the lives of more than 130 adults every day. Promising innovation is being seen in the integration of rigorously validated mental health methods into smartphone apps. One AI app under development is for patients with opioid, alcohol, and other forms of drug addiction with co-occurring mental illness. The app provides patients with a virtual form of integrated group therapy (IGT), a highly effective treatment that teaches behaviors and skills to manage recovery and prevent relapse.</p>
<p><b>Link to Disruptive Dozen 2019 <a title="videos" href="https://www.globenewswire.com/Tracker?data=Dgqhx4fsCb5MQ_uMLOdn-4jAjuHb8HGuFFN8t2sdQ1OhXZimiVl5hSHcVGXYP4EnYsdwK7IDD5ERooXdbabrU99n3wPKMAM5u7WSTTNksEH444-XcmNAeCtfiz5BpO9JI_sj3QAfyeUXsOqP7JcQPw==" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">videos</a></b></p>
<p><strong>Link to <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Partners-FORUM-2019-BROCHURE-D12-AI-190326_0832-F-FOR-WEB-X3-SM.pdf">2019 Disruptive Dozen</a> </strong></p>
<p><b>About the Disruptive Dozen</b></p>
<p>The “Disruptive Dozen” is an annual list of the 12 most disruptive technologies as selected through a rigorous process by Partners HealthCare thought leaders, clinicians and researchers. Interview results from nearly 100 experts are assembled into a field of nominated technologies.  These are considered in a session involving a small committee of experts to the field. The output of the voting is a consensus on the 12 technologies that will have the greatest impact in the next year. The final list is announced in rank order at the World Medical Innovation Forum.</p>
<p><b>About the World Medical Innovation Forum</b></p>
<p>The World Medical Innovation Forum is a global gathering of more than 1,800 senior health care leaders hosted by Partners HealthCare in the heart of Boston. It was established to respond to the intensifying transformation of health care and its impact on innovation. The Forum is rooted in the belief that no matter the magnitude of that change, the center of health care needs to be a shared, fundamental commitment to collaborative innovation and its ability to improve patient lives. For more information: <a title="" href="https://www.globenewswire.com/Tracker?data=OugGt-BRunq1L3O-spNcb7488rmoaMZ04XIqhBuGmjOY7s0P7ZkqRQZvGtR1F1nNBx3AT7y-JC5LVo1ahVFmH67EyBhdZ-XAvTB2ChMIGtkxG5SXyzzmMMrf7__ExfxSLHD6llLTnxtc6WA2F0Wd3vK0wt0PVYNaGg-1aGvwXGbBsp2epZQStpKgKMOBXDwNlw0NNo2IMhI0DdD3K3hOQV5RXDsMujAGouZQi4RCKgHsuYFMP8YrHjUVM5-Y4ssEqEkXcGIQLKwmmvbBI2VhvsQSQIhB5QVG6daLCcYBYOPmUf25UQNSARQNVpcO_BVgX8BG_j0PmWq__sTNdHrEZiLaHWKd6p8REgCzj4a522h3j61u4_0pcZ3_GOGpcrPs" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer"><u>www.wmif21.sitedistrict.com</u></a>.</p>
<p><b>About Partners HealthCare</b></p>
<p>Partners HealthCare is an integrated health system founded by Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Massachusetts General Hospital. In addition to its two academic medical centers, the Partners system includes community and specialty hospitals, a health insurance provider, community health centers, a physician network, home health and long-term care services, and other health-related entities. Partners HealthCare is one of the nation’s leading biomedical research organizations and a principal teaching affiliate of Harvard Medical School. Partners HealthCare is a non-profit organization.</p>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/top-12-disruptive-health-care-ai-technologies-announced/">Top 12 Disruptive Health Care AI Technologies Announced</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Partners HealthCare Embraces the Democratization of AI  to Accelerate Innovation in Medicine</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/partners-healthcare-embraces-the-democratization-of-ai-to-accelerate-innovation-in-medicine/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Beth Mollineaux]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 13:14:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=6520</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The MGH &#38; BWH Center for Clinical Data Science wants to put AI in the toolbox of every researcher and clinician   Boston, MA April 08, 2019 – At the World Medical Innovation Forum 2019, Partners HealthCare today announced a commitment to put artificial intelligence (AI) in the toolbox of all of its researchers and ... <a title="Partners HealthCare Embraces the Democratization of AI  to Accelerate Innovation in Medicine" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/partners-healthcare-embraces-the-democratization-of-ai-to-accelerate-innovation-in-medicine/" aria-label="More on Partners HealthCare Embraces the Democratization of AI  to Accelerate Innovation in Medicine">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/partners-healthcare-embraces-the-democratization-of-ai-to-accelerate-innovation-in-medicine/">Partners HealthCare Embraces the Democratization of AI  to Accelerate Innovation in Medicine</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>The MGH &amp; BWH Center for Clinical Data Science wants to put AI in the toolbox of every researcher and clinician  </em></strong></p>
<p><strong>Boston, MA April 08, 2019</strong> – At the World Medical Innovation Forum 2019, Partners HealthCare today announced a commitment to put artificial intelligence (AI) in the toolbox of all of its researchers and clinicians. These efforts, being spearheaded by the MGH &amp; BWH Center for Clinical Data Science (CCDS), focus on providing researchers and clinicians with access to data, GPU (graphics processing unit) compute capacity and supporting software required to develop their own AI algorithms to be implemented in the clinical environment.</p>
<p>CCDS is planning broad roll-out to the Partners system over the next 12 months and is already offering AI capabilities and support services. This announcement aligns with national and global trends towards democratization of AI capabilities through increasingly collaborative efforts between academic organizations, technology companies and organizations like the American College of Radiology (ACR) that work to establish standards for the field.</p>
<p>“Currently, focused and siloed pockets of domain expertise in AI reside within specific departments or labs at several large academic medical centers, but making AI an enabling technology across the field of healthcare has been a challenge for many facilities” said Keith Dreyer, DO, PhD, FACR, FSIIM, Chief Data Science Officer, Partners HealthCare. “The truth is, you don’t have to be a computer scientist or data scientist to participate in the creation of AI – we are just starting to see increasing availability of tools to enable on-premises development of AI models by clinicians.”</p>
<p>The trend is punctuated by the recent announcement of a free software platform (AI-LAB) being released by the ACR to allow radiologists to develop, validate and implement AI within their own facilities. AI-LAB is a core component of ACR’s vision for the democratization of AI in radiology. The free, vendor-neutral software solution will allow radiologists to work with patient data within their own secure IT environments, while providing opportunities to share AI datasets and algorithms with other institutions. The objective is to facilitate the development of more versatile, generalizable and accurate models – a principle known as transfer learning.</p>
<p>Through collaboration with Nvidia and The Ohio State University (OSU), CCDS has demonstrated the ability for new transfer learning approaches to generate algorithms that are more robust and adaptive to local variation. The specific project involved the transfer of a cardiac Computed Tomography Angiography (CTA) model, which was co-developed with Nvidia, to OSU where it was re-trained using OSU data. The resulting model was more accurate and required less effort to train, validate and test. Ittai Dayan, MD, Executive Director of Operations at CCDS underscores the spirit of collaboration. “The concept of transfer learning means that sites can collaborate in building more highly performant algorithms without having to share sensitive patient data – this collaborative approach will dramatically accelerate the rate at which new algorithms are developed and integrated into the clinical workflow.”</p>
<p>The announcement at the World Medical Innovation Forum in Boston, a global conference focusing on the intersection of AI and clinical care, reflects the vital role of innovation in transforming healthcare. The ability for new technologies, like AI, to have a meaningful impact in the field of medicine is highly dependent on collaboration between stakeholders with a unified goal of improving patient lives. At the conference, clinicians, industry and government leaders, entrepreneurs and venture investors are exploring where AI meets clinical care, including the requisite sensitivity to patient data and standards.</p>
<p>To see more of CCDS’ work at the Forum, visit the CCDS booth onsite on the 3<sup>rd</sup> floor of the Westin Copley.</p>
<p><strong>About Partners HealthCare</strong> <strong><br />
</strong>Partners HealthCare System is an integrated health system founded by Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Massachusetts General Hospital.  In addition to its two academic medical centers, the Partners system includes community and specialty hospitals, a managed care organization, community health centers, a physician network, home health and long-term care services, and other health-related entities. Partners is one of the nation’s leading biomedical research organizations and a principal teaching affiliate of Harvard Medical School.</p>
<p><strong>About the MGH &amp; BWH Center for Clinical Data Science<br />
</strong>Founded in 2016, the MGH &amp; BWH Center for Clinical Data Science is a joint center formed by Massachusetts General Hospital and Brigham and Women’s Hospital to transform healthcare by translating the latest advances in artificial intelligence (AI) into improved health outcomes and greater operational efficiency. With deep academic research expertise, access to significant computational power and data resources, and extensive product development and industry experience, the CCDS is uniquely positioned to improve the detection, diagnosis, treatment, and management of diseases through the application and commercial translation of AI techniques.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/partners-healthcare-embraces-the-democratization-of-ai-to-accelerate-innovation-in-medicine/">Partners HealthCare Embraces the Democratization of AI  to Accelerate Innovation in Medicine</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2019 Partners HealthCare World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/6511-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Beth Mollineaux]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 18:14:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=6511</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The forum is a gathering of more than 2,000 senior health care leaders from around the world and will focus on the advancements and opportunities of Artificial Intelligence (AI). The World Medical Innovation Forum, hosted by Partners HealthCare, will take place April 8-10, 2019 in Boston, Massachusetts. The forum is a gathering of more than 2,000 senior ... <a title="2019 Partners HealthCare World Medical Innovation Forum" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/6511-2/" aria-label="More on 2019 Partners HealthCare World Medical Innovation Forum">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/6511-2/">2019 Partners HealthCare World Medical Innovation Forum</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="article-header">
<h4>The forum is a gathering of more than 2,000 senior health care leaders from around the world and will focus on the advancements and opportunities of Artificial Intelligence (AI).</h4>
</div>
<div class="article-body">
<p>The World Medical Innovation Forum, hosted by Partners HealthCare, will take place April 8-10, 2019 in Boston, Massachusetts. The forum is a gathering of more than 2,000 senior health care leaders from around the world and will focus on the advancements and opportunities of Artificial Intelligence (AI). The World Medical Innovation Forum was established to respond to the intensifying transformation of health care and its impact on innovation.</p>
<p>This year&#8217;s event “Where AI Meets Clinical Care,” will bring together global leaders in the evolving discipline of artificial intelligence and machine learning for in-depth conversations on fast-developing novel technologies. Impact on patients, clinicians and systems will be examined in depth and panels, consisting of industry and investment executives teamed with Harvard clinical and research leaders, will focus on patient interactions across care settings, and the role technology and data can play in advancing knowledge discovery and care delivery.</p>
<p>“For advances in medicine and technology to truly reach their full potential, there needs to be a shared, fundamental commitment to collaborative innovation that can improve patient lives,” said Anne Klibanski, MD, Partners HealthCare Interim President and CEO and Forum co-chair. “We have only just begun to explore how AI and data will revolutionize health care and the Forum is an opportunity for industry and academia to get a first look at the research and developments that will be in the market in the coming months and years.”</p>
<p>Featured speakers include the CEOs of Bayer, Biogen, Bristol-Myers Squibb, GE Healthcare, Nuance, NVIDIA, Philips, Siemens Healthineers, Wolters Kluwer Health as well as Massachusetts Governor Charlie Baker, Secretary of Health and Human Services Alex Azar, Deepak Chopra, MD, former Secretary of Defense Ash Carter and CMS Administrator Seema Verma among many others.</p>
<p>The Forum will also feature <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/first-look/">“First Look”</a> presentations from rising stars at Harvard-affiliated hospitals who will highlight the potential of their research in artificial intelligence, cognitive computing, machine learning, and big data; a look at the <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/disruptive-dozen/">“Disruptive Dozen,”</a> 12 technologies that will reinvent AI in the next 12 months and a fascinating session where clinical and technology visionaries will imagine what medicine will look like in <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/events/imagining-medicine-in-the-year-2054/">2054</a>.</p>
<p>For the full agenda and to register, go to <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">wmif21.sitedistrict.com</a>.</p>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/6511-2/">2019 Partners HealthCare World Medical Innovation Forum</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Next Chapter For Biotech? Many Say &#039;Convergence&#039; With Data Science</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/next-chapter-for-biotech-many-say-convergence-with-data-science/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Jun 2018 13:27:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chris Coburn]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Data Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Partners HealthCare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philips]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[World Medical Innovation Forum]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=4414</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>by WBUR June 8, 2018- So far, the digital revolution has mostly been a disappointment in health care. Doctors stare at their screens instead of us. Specialists and emergency rooms still don’t have all our records. But artificial intelligence, big data analytics and deep learning are converging on health care in a big way, information ... <a title="Next Chapter For Biotech? Many Say &#039;Convergence&#039; With Data Science" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/next-chapter-for-biotech-many-say-convergence-with-data-science/" aria-label="More on Next Chapter For Biotech? Many Say &#039;Convergence&#039; With Data Science">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/next-chapter-for-biotech-many-say-convergence-with-data-science/">Next Chapter For Biotech? Many Say &#039;Convergence&#039; With Data Science</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<section class="article-section--content hang-punctuation article-section--first article-section--centered" data-reactid="280">
<p class="" data-reactid="283">by WBUR</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="283">June 8, 2018- So far, the digital revolution has mostly been a disappointment in health care. Doctors stare at their screens instead of us. Specialists and emergency rooms still don’t have all our records.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="284">But artificial intelligence, big data analytics and deep learning are converging on health care in a big way, information technology experts insist. The changes have already begun. And if and when they really take off, such convergence of biology and technology should bring about a complete transformation of medical care.</p>
<p class="indent-medium" data-reactid="286">“My personal perspective would be in three to five years, the huge majority of patients will be touched one way or [an]other with some AI-related system, whether they know it or not,” says Chris Coburn, chief innovation officer at Partners HealthCare, who recently led a three-day conference on the topic of artificial intelligence, or AI. “The scope of the potential benefit is at times not easily even imagined.”</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="287">Coburn and others cite numerous examples where artificial intelligence is already improving health care:</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="288">&#8212; Digital visual analysis is beginning to replace pathologists at identifying dangerous tumors.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="289">&#8212; Devices are increasingly able to monitor patients at home to catch problems before they become serious.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="290">&#8212; Pharmaceutical companies like Amgen and Novartis are using deep learning and artificial intelligence to shorten their drug development process and improve their odds of successfully bringing a drug to market.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="291">&#8212; Cellphones and watch-like mobile devices are increasingly being used to monitor healthy people for changes that might indicate impending problems.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="292">&#8212; And in hospitals, algorithms can help indicate which patients need immediate attention and which should be left alone to rest.</p>
<p class="indent-medium" data-reactid="293">&#8220;Our patient monitoring and guardian algorithms can actually predictively say how a patient is doing,&#8221; says Frans van Houten, head of Royal Philips, the Dutch conglomerate now focused almost entirely on health care technologies.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="294">Houten, whose company is in the process of consolidating its U.S. research operations in Cambridge, says digital algorithms can predict which patients are vulnerable to life-threatening infections and which to heart attacks.</p>
<p class="indent-medium" data-reactid="295">“And that allows the health system to proactively direct staff to the patients that need [care], versus the patients that don’t,” he says. “So our technology can play a big role for precision care and raising productivity.”</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="296">Similarly, Colin Hill runs a Cambridge company, GNS Healthcare, which analyzes vast amounts of patient data to derive information that can improve care.</p>
<p class="indent-medium" data-reactid="297">“We’re on a path to turning the lights on and revealing what works for whom,&#8221; he says. &#8220;And by getting at the underlying mechanisms of these diseases, we can now stop the guesswork. That&#8217;s what&#8217;s really exciting for me.”</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="298">His company recently used genetic data from a large number of patients with the blood cancer multiple myeloma to identify patterns in those who were helped by a costly, potentially dangerous bone marrow transplant. If the findings are validated, patients whose genetics suggest they wouldn’t benefit could be spared the time, energy, expense and dashed hopes of a fruitless procedure.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="299">Thanks to improvements in artificial intelligence, Hill says, “we’re now able to learn that kind of causality &#8212; those kinds of cause-effect relationships &#8212; straight from real-world data.”</p>
</section>
<section class="article-section--content hang-punctuation article-section--island" data-reactid="300">
<blockquote class="article-pullquote" data-reactid="301">
<p class="article-pullquote-text" data-reactid="302">&#8220;As a society, we are coming to grips with the fact that we have a health care system that costs far too much and delivers far too little&#8230;&#8221;</p>
<p><cite class="article-pullquote-attribution" data-reactid="304">Colin Hill, GNS Healthcare</cite></p></blockquote>
</section>
<section class="article-section--content hang-punctuation article-section--centered" data-reactid="305">
<p class="" data-reactid="306">Hopefully, this will also save money, which is driving the current interest, Hill says.</p>
<p class="indent-medium" data-reactid="307">“What&#8217;s changed is the convergence of both the data and the technology capabilities,” he says. “And I think the environment&#8217;s also changed. As a society, we are coming to grips with the fact that we have a health care system that costs far too much and delivers far too little and it is ultimately not sustainable the way it is.”</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="308">Nobel Laureate and MIT Institute professor Phil Sharp has an even broader vision of this convergence: It’s not just computer science and biology that are converging, but engineering, physics, material science and agriculture too, he says.</p>
<p class="indent-medium" data-reactid="309">“Life science is part of all of those processes and bringing physicists and engineering and information technology together to integrate life science with the translation to solving those problems is what convergence is about,” Sharp says. “It&#8217;ll be decades of exciting science and exciting technology.”</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="310"><strong>&#8216;It Doesn&#8217;t Always Go The Way We Hope&#8217;</strong></p>
<p class="" data-reactid="311">Despite its potential, some people say that artificial intelligence is the future of health care — and always will be. Skepticism remains high because of problems with the electronic health record, which has taken years longer than expected to become functional and constructive.</p>
<p class="indent-medium" data-reactid="312">“We hope that things are going to go well. But specifically in health care it doesn&#8217;t always go the way we hope,” says Andrew Beam, an instructor and junior faculty member in the department of Biomedical Informatics at Harvard Medical School.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="313">GNS Healthcare&#8217;s Hill says he finds it annoying when tech people assume it should be easy to bring change to health care.</p>
<p class="indent-medium" data-reactid="314">&#8220;When folks come from the tech world thinking that they&#8217;re going to come and build the iPhone of human disease and health care, one of the reasons why they stumble with it is because the complexity of these systems is just beyond anything we&#8217;ve dealt with,” Hill says. &#8220;It’s a fundamentally different problem.”</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="315">There is no room for error when someone’s health or life is on the line.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="316">And privacy is an even bigger issue in medicine than on social media. No one wants their medical records on display on the internet.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="317">Beam says that although there is more oversight in medicine, privacy breaches will happen.</p>
<p class="indent-medium" data-reactid="318">&#8220;I think it&#8217;s going to continue to be a problem,” he says. &#8220;The unfortunate fact in cybersecurity is that the bad guys are always just ahead of the good guys and there&#8217;s sort of an ongoing arms race.&#8221;</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="319">Despite the concerns about digital health, there’s clearly a growing interest in the combination of computer technology and medical care.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="320">Abbie Celniker, a partner Third Rock Ventures, says so far, her venture capital firm hasn’t invested directly in artificial intelligence or machine learning companies. But that day may not be far off.</p>
<p class="indent-medium" data-reactid="321">“We are starting to really do our homework and think about the most optimal places to bring together therapeutic development and digital health,” she says.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="322">Others are investing, too. Last month, pharma giant Roche <a href="http://www.modernhealthcare.com/article/20180216/NEWS/180219932">spent $1.9 billion</a> to buy Flatiron Health, a New York startup that tries to advance cancer care by analyzing huge datasets of patient records.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="323">Celniker says that most of the companies Third Rock has helped start already use digital technologies to analyze datasets, crunch numbers or improve efficiency.</p>
<p class="indent-medium" data-reactid="324">“But applying it in a bigger way, bringing together more diverse datasets, and having things learned from those very diverse datasets, that&#8217;s something that we&#8217;re just trying now to figure out where&#8217;s the best place to investigate,&#8221; she says.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="325">Greater Boston has all the necessary ingredients to lead in the area of digital health, a number of local experts say, continuing to keep the so-called BioBoom alive for years to come.</p>
<p class="indent-medium" data-reactid="326">“Digital health is what&#8217;s next. Precision medicine, personalized medicine &#8212; that is what&#8217;s next,” says Bob Coughlin, president and CEO of the nonprofit Massachusetts Biotechnology Council. “Now let&#8217;s ask, where is most of that research in those areas — in digital health and precision medicine? What in gene therapy and immunotherapy and gene modification and exon skipping and CAR-T therapy, CRISPR technology &#8212; where’s most of that happening? Well, folks, you can walk to it right here.”</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="327">Although digital giants like Microsoft and Google are headquartered in Silicon Valley, they now have outposts in Cambridge. They’re the ones driving up the rent in Kendall Square, Coughlin says.</p>
<p class="" data-reactid="328">And there’s a broad range of expertise here, which will be essential for this convergence, Harvard Med&#8217;s Beam says.</p>
<p class="indent-medium" data-reactid="329">&#8220;You can&#8217;t just be a computer scientist working in isolation on artificial intelligence if you want to change biology and medicine,” he says. You have to partner with doctors, engineers and hospital staff. “And no matter what area of biology or medicine would like you to use AI to improve, there is a world expert in that area here Boston.&#8221;</p>
</section>
<p>http://www.wbur.org/commonhealth/2018/06/08/biotech-artificial-intelligence-convergence</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/next-chapter-for-biotech-many-say-convergence-with-data-science/">Next Chapter For Biotech? Many Say &#039;Convergence&#039; With Data Science</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Artificial Intelligence Promises a New Paradigm for Healthcare</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/artificial-intelligence-promises-a-new-paradigm-for-healthcare/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 20:06:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[healthcare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[World Medical Innovation Forum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[XtelligentMedia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=4410</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Click here to view full article from XtelligentMedia The speed with which artificial intelligence has become an inescapable component of every new technology offering is either highly encouraging or deeply troubling, depending on the observer’s zeal or trepidation around the notion of integrating data-rich algorithms into the complex and highly personal practice of caring for ... <a title="Artificial Intelligence Promises a New Paradigm for Healthcare" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/artificial-intelligence-promises-a-new-paradigm-for-healthcare/" aria-label="More on Artificial Intelligence Promises a New Paradigm for Healthcare">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/artificial-intelligence-promises-a-new-paradigm-for-healthcare/">Artificial Intelligence Promises a New Paradigm for Healthcare</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://healthitanalytics.com/features/artificial-intelligence-promises-a-new-paradigm-for-healthcare">Click here to view full article from XtelligentMedia</a></p>
<p>The speed with which artificial intelligence has become an inescapable component of every new technology offering is either highly encouraging or deeply troubling, depending on the observer’s zeal or trepidation around the notion of integrating data-rich algorithms into the complex and highly personal practice of caring for patients.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/artificial-intelligence-promises-a-new-paradigm-for-healthcare/">Artificial Intelligence Promises a New Paradigm for Healthcare</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Should Tech Entrepreneurs Aspire To Fix Clinical Trials Or Reinvent Them?</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/should-tech-entrepreneurs-aspire-to-fix-clinical-trials-or-reinvent-them/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 19:56:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[BWH]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[clinical trials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forbes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[World Medical Innovation Forum]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=4409</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Written by Forbes Contributor David Shaywitz Click here to view full article To fix or to reinvent?  That’s the question many would-be innovators ask as they contemplate potential applications of technology to health. Dr. Stephen Wiviott, a cardiologist and Senior Investigator with the legendary TIMI Study Group at Boston’s Brigham and Women’s (BWH) hospital, nicely represents ... <a title="Should Tech Entrepreneurs Aspire To Fix Clinical Trials Or Reinvent Them?" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/should-tech-entrepreneurs-aspire-to-fix-clinical-trials-or-reinvent-them/" aria-label="More on Should Tech Entrepreneurs Aspire To Fix Clinical Trials Or Reinvent Them?">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/should-tech-entrepreneurs-aspire-to-fix-clinical-trials-or-reinvent-them/">Should Tech Entrepreneurs Aspire To Fix Clinical Trials Or Reinvent Them?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Written by Forbes Contributor <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/davidshaywitz/" data-ga-track="contrib block byline">David Shaywitz </a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/davidshaywitz/2018/05/22/should-tech-entrepreneurs-aspire-to-fix-clinical-trials-or-reinvent-them/#2281428b775c">Click here to view full article</a></p>
<p class="speakable-paragraph">To fix or to reinvent?  That’s the question many would-be innovators ask as they contemplate potential applications of technology to health.</p>
<p>Dr. Stephen Wiviott, a cardiologist and Senior Investigator with the legendary TIMI Study Group at Boston’s Brigham and Women’s (BWH) hospital, nicely represents the views of what might be called the “fix it” folks. At a recent panel discussion at the World Medical Innovation Forum (viewable <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Snd0X0c_qSg" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-ga-track="ExternalLink:https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Snd0X0c_qSg">here</a>), Wiviott noted how expensive traditional randomized clinical trials (RCTs) can be, telling the audience that the cardiovascular (CV) outcome trial he’s now running for an SGLT2 medication involves the recruitment of 17,000 patients, will take seven years to complete, and will cost about half a billion (with a “b”) dollars.  He suspects that it shouldn’t need to cost nearly that much, and that improved regulations in particular, as well as improving efficiencies at each step of the trial (potentially with the help of data and technology) could take 90% of the cost out of the current system.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/should-tech-entrepreneurs-aspire-to-fix-clinical-trials-or-reinvent-them/">Should Tech Entrepreneurs Aspire To Fix Clinical Trials Or Reinvent Them?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Recap</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-three-recap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 13:07:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2018]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=4334</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>&#160; Recap &#124; April 25 World Medical Innovation Forum: Artificial Intelligence 1,700 registrants, 140 executive presenters and key leaders shape the future of artificial intelligence! The third day of the World Medical Innovation Forum featured a series of panel discussions and fireside chats that focused on ways that artificial intelligence (AI) can be used to ... <a title="2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Recap" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-three-recap/" aria-label="More on 2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Recap">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-three-recap/">2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/PartnersFORUM2018EMAILTEMPLATEBoston180425_1932B-AF3150HEADER2.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4335" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/PartnersFORUM2018EMAILTEMPLATEBoston180425_1932B-AF3150HEADER2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="693" /></a></h2>
<h2>Recap | April 25</h2>
<p><strong>World Medical Innovation Forum: Artificial Intelligence</strong><br />
<em>1,700 registrants, 140 executive presenters and key leaders shape the future of artificial intelligence!</em></p>
<p>The third day of the World Medical Innovation Forum featured a series of panel discussions and fireside chats that focused on ways that artificial intelligence (AI) can be used to improve the performance and data-gathering capabilities of medical devices, reduce health care costs, improve operational efficiencies across the healthcare system and mine new insights from clinical and research data.</p>
<p>&#8220;If you think about the magnitude of the information we have available to us in this space, you think about where technology is today and the compute horsepower that is available to all of us, it just makes sense to continue to evaluate technologies like artificial intelligence to be able to streamline not just operational and administrative efficiency, but be able to make more informed and timely decisions,&#8221; said Eric Murphy, CEO of OptumInsight and Enterprise Growth Officer at Optum, during a discussion on how AI technologies could factor into healthcare reimbursement systems.</p>
<p>Another engaging discussion focused on the concerns that AI technologies may eventually replace human pathologists and radiologists in diagnosing patients. The message from the speakers on this panel was that AI tools should be viewed as a friend, not a foe.</p>
<p>Constance Lehman, MD, PhD, Chief of Breast Imaging at Massachusetts General Hospital (MGH), said AI technologies have helped make imaging services at MGH more precise, targeted and personalized while reducing repetitive tasks that lead to burnout.</p>
<p>&#8220;Without a doubt this is on the friend side and a really powerful technology,&#8221; said Andrew Beck, MD, PhD, CEO, of PathAI. &#8220;The types of problems we are interested in solving are really hard and big and we&#8217;re very far from being able to effectively solve them, even with the AI of today. We&#8217;re very lucky that we have the access to these new technologies that will assist the profession.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/PartnersFORUM2018EMAILTEMPLATEBoston180425_1932B-AF3150PHOTO12.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4336" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/PartnersFORUM2018EMAILTEMPLATEBoston180425_1932B-AF3150PHOTO12.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="267" /></a></p>
<h2>Fireside Chats</h2>
<p>Wednesday&#8217;s Fireside Chat sessions provided valuable insights from healthcare leaders in the government, technology and pharmaceutical sectors.</p>
<p>&#8220;I&#8217;ve been in this industry for nearly four decades now. I honestly believe that I have never seen a technology that&#8217;s as transformative as this one,&#8221; said John Kelly, PhD, Senior Vice President for Cognitive Solutions and Research at IBM.</p>
<p>&#8220;The opportunity is enormous to transform this industry for better outcomes, lower costs for the benefit of all,&#8221; Kelly said. &#8220;But it&#8217;s now into the hard work portion of this. It is not easy to build a very intelligent, at scale, precise artificial intelligence system to be injected in the workflow of a clinical physician or a drug researcher. That is a big job. And by the way, you better have heck of a lot of good data to train that system.&#8221;</p>
<h2>The Disruptive Dozen: 12 AI Technologies That Will Reinvent Care</h2>
<p>The forum concluded on Wednesday afternoon with the presentation of the Disruptive Dozen, 12 technologies that faculty members in the Partners HealthCare System (PHS) believe have the potential to significantly advance healthcare in the next decade.</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/Partners-FORUM-2018-BROCHURE-D12-AI-180410_1202-FREV2-FOR-WEB-X3.pdf" target="blank">Follow this link to read all twelve.</a></p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/PartnersFORUM2018EMAILTEMPLATEBoston180425_1932B-AF3150PHOTO2.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4337" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/PartnersFORUM2018EMAILTEMPLATEBoston180425_1932B-AF3150PHOTO2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="133" /></a></p>
<h2>First Look Winners Announced!</h2>
<p>Congratulations to First Look presenters Sabine Wilhelm, PhD, from MGH and Ziad Obermeyer, MD, from Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital (BWH) for winning the Peter K. Ranney Innovation Award!</p>
<p>The award was presented at last night&#8217;s Innovator&#8217;s Dinner to honor the BWH and MGH First Look presenters who embodied the innovative, entrepreneurial and visionary spirit the World Medical Innovation Forum was established to recognize.</p>
<p>Here is some of the feedback the judges provided for the winners:</p>
<h5><em>Mobile Apps: Bridging the Mental Health Treatment Gap</em></h5>
<p><strong>Sabine Wilhelm, PhD</strong><br />
The concept of delivering cognitive behavioral therapy through a mobile app reduces traditional barriers to mental health treatment and tackles cost and access issues head on.<br />
Given the well demonstrated market need for better mental health care paradigms and relative maturity of the technology, the app may benefit from a potentially short commercialization timeline.<br />
The app is well positioned to passively collect substantial data that can inform computational models used to personalize treatment and provide real-time interventions.</p>
<h5><em>A Machine Learning Algorithm to Reduce Costs and Increase Quality</em></h5>
<p><strong>Ziad Obermeyer, MD</strong><br />
The presentation addressed the kind of multi-variate clinical challenges that AI/ML based approaches are well suited to address.<br />
The research has potential for dramatic impact on both cost and quality.<br />
There is real opportunity to expand the approach across clinical domains and disease conditions-a big idea with the potential for broad impact.</p>
<h2>Notable Tweets</h2>
<p>Timothy Howe | @HamiltonHowe<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/HamiltonHowe/status/989138416150503424">Vasant Narasimhan CEO of @Novartis, &#8220;We need to win the race of turtles&#8230;&#8221; commenting on how slow the industry is moving with regard to #AI and data collection. #WMIF18</a></p>
<p>BCBSNC | @BCBSNC<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/BCBSNC/status/989130703609782272">&#8220;We need to remove any remaining friction between insurers and #healthcare providers when it comes to sharing #data. We need a free flow of information.&#8221; &#8211; @PatrickConwayMD #WMIF18</a></p>
<p>Laura Lovett | @lauralovett7<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/lauralovett7/status/989234948241612800">Will robots be creating our meds in the future? Experts say probably not. But there is use for AI in pharma. I got to hang out at the World Medical Innovation Forum yesterday and hear all about it #WMIF18</a></p>
<p>Slalom Boston | @SlalomBoston<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/SlalomBoston/status/989194864427524096">It&#8217;s the final day of #WMIF18 and we&#8217;ve had a blast learning about #AI in #healthcare. Thanks to @PartnersNews for the outstanding event!</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-three-recap/">2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Recap</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-two-recap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 12:47:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2018]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=4329</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>&#160; Recap &#124; April 24 The Role of AI in Health Care Accessibility and Drug Discovery A closer look at how to turn the promise of implementing AI in health care into a reality. Day 2 of the World Medical Innovation Forum was packed with in-depth discussions on the opportunities and challenges of integrating artificial ... <a title="2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Recap" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-two-recap/" aria-label="More on 2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Recap">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-two-recap/">2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4330" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180424_1742B-AF2150HEADER2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="693" /></a></h2>
<h2>Recap | April 24</h2>
<p><strong>The Role of AI in Health Care Accessibility and Drug Discovery</strong><br />
<em>A closer look at how to turn the promise of implementing AI in health care into a reality.</em></p>
<p>Day 2 of the World Medical Innovation Forum was packed with in-depth discussions on the opportunities and challenges of integrating artificial intelligence (AI) into the health care system, with an up-close look at the role AI could play in delivering affordable health care, supporting clinical decision making, processing large amounts of data and speeding up drug development.</p>
<p>The discussion also highlighted some key challenges in AI integration, such as convincing clinicians, patients and payors of the value of AI technology, standardizing data across platforms, and protecting patient privacy in a digitized world.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4332" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180424_1742B-AF2150PHOTO12.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="267" /></a></p>
<h2>The Importance of Data</h2>
<p>Data collection was a key topic in many sessions throughout the day. &#8220;The theme you will hear over and over is very high quality, well-curated data,&#8221; said Mark Murcko, PhD, Chief Science Officer of Relay Therapeutics, during a session on drug development. &#8220;One of the big challenges we have is to better represent the interactions that molecules are having. Just to tease out that little bit of insight that helps the drug discovery team move a little faster.&#8221;</p>
<p>A panel discussion on Data Engineering in Health Care emphasized the importance of engaging patients in discovery process and convincing them that the benefits of sharing their health information with clinicians and researchers outweigh the risks of a potential data breach.</p>
<p>James Mault, MD, Senior Vice President and Chief Medical Officer for Qualcomm Life, noted that 15 years ago many people were hesitant about using their credit cards to make purchases online, but today nearly everyone has their information stored on website such as Amazon because of the convenience it provides.</p>
<p>&#8220;The risk is still there, but we&#8217;re willing to accept that risk because we&#8217;re getting these tremendous benefits,&#8221; he said. &#8220;In health care we&#8217;re seeing a lot of risk, but we&#8217;re not yet seeing a lot of benefit.&#8221;</p>
<h2>Fireside Chats</h2>
<p>Day 2 also featured a series of one-on-one fireside chats. Atul Gawande, MD, a surgeon at Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital (BWH) and bestselling author of Being Mortal and The Checklist Manifesto (among others), told Brigham Health President Elizabeth Nabel, MD, that the key to successfully integrating AI technology into clinical care is to identify clear benefits for both the patient and the clinician-and to ensure that the health care providers are ready and willing to use it.</p>
<p>&#8220;If you give people a great process solution, the perfect innovation tool, and plug it into a ready environment, you make a major impact.&#8221;</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4333" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180424_1742B-AF2150PHOTO2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="133" /></a></p>
<h2>Afternoon Panel Sessions</h2>
<p>In a panel session on AI and Genetic Sequencing, moderator Heidi Rehm, PhD, said that while researchers are now able to collect much more genetic data from patients, their ability to process and take action on that data is still lagging behind.</p>
<p>&#8220;The team in my laboratory still reads articles in the literature to try to figure out what these variants mean,&#8221; Rehm said. &#8220;We will never be able to disseminate these technologies for broad medical use if we can&#8217;t advance what we are doing today in terms of understanding the genetic and genomic variation.&#8221;</p>
<p>Despite the concerns raised and the work that still needs to be done, the tone of the day&#8217;s sessions were overwhelming positive, with nearly all participants saying they believed that AI technology could make significant improvements in the delivery of health care.</p>
<p>In a CEO roundtable discussion hosted by Peter Slavin, MD, President of Massachusetts General Hospital, Terri Bresenham, Chief Executive Officer for GE Healthcare, shared her optimistic outlook.</p>
<p>&#8220;We&#8217;re very bullish,&#8221; Bresenham said. &#8220;I think there&#8217;s no doubt that this will be by far the most transformational technology change that is going to occur, in concert with some other very important changes in genomics and genetics and biotherapies as well as diagnostics and imaging technology.&#8221;</p>
<h2>Notable Tweets</h2>
<p>Samuel Myllykangas | @SamuMyllykangas<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/SamuMyllykangas/status/988861177777344519">CEO panel: #AI will transform healthcare by expanding access to care, improving quality, reducing cost, streamlining information flow and integration, accelerating drug discovery, supporting decision making and supplementing research. #WMIF18</a></p>
<p>Behrooz Hashemian | @behxyz<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/behxyz/status/988862279461560321">Amazing roundtable with CIO and CEO&#8217;s from @Philips, @SiemensHealth, @Vertex, and @GEHealthcare, talking about the AI opportunities in healthcare and how it is transforming the industry. #WMIF18 @MassGeneralNews</a></p>
<p>Cassie Lee | @cassan_druh<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/cassan_druh/status/988780880796831744">Understanding that you in the #innovation world have two customers: you have the patient whose lives you have to make better, and you have the clinicians who you need to make easy tools for that scale &#8211; @Atul_Gawande at #WMIF18 @BrighamWomens</a></p>
<p>Dan Hashimoto | @Laparoscopes<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/Laparoscopes/status/988806822642544640">I want @Nvidia to be an intelligent autonomous machine. I want @NvidiaAI to be an #AI. #AI needs to do 3 things: perception of the environment, reason about what it&#8217;s perceiving, develop a plan to take action. &#8211; CEO Jensen Huang #WMIF18</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-two-recap/">2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2018 World Forum &#8211; Day One Recap</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-one-recap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 13:24:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2018]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=4296</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>&#160; Recap &#124; April 23 A Sell Out Crowd The fourth annual World Medical Innovation Forum (WMIF) sponsored by Partners Innovation, kicked off Monday morning with a record attendance of 1,600 participants representing the top healthcare, biotech and venture capital firms from across the globe. The theme of this year&#8217;s forum is Artificial Intelligence (AI), ... <a title="2018 World Forum &#8211; Day One Recap" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-one-recap/" aria-label="More on 2018 World Forum &#8211; Day One Recap">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-one-recap/">2018 World Forum &#8211; Day One Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180423_1722-B-AF-1-150-HEADER-2.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4297" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180423_1722-B-AF-1-150-HEADER-2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="693" /></a></h2>
<h2>Recap | April 23</h2>
<p><strong>A Sell Out Crowd</strong></p>
<p>The fourth annual World Medical Innovation Forum (WMIF) sponsored by Partners Innovation, kicked off Monday morning with a record attendance of 1,600 participants representing the top healthcare, biotech and venture capital firms from across the globe.</p>
<p>The theme of this year&#8217;s forum is Artificial Intelligence (AI), and much of the discussion on Day One focused on the promise, complexities and limitations of AI in healthcare.</p>
<p>Speakers were optimistic about the potential for AI to drive big improvements in predicting disease, treating patients and managing outcomes, but also cautioned that the technology is still in its early stages and there will likely be some growing pains along the way.</p>
<p>In her opening remarks, Anne Klibanski, MD, Chief Academic Officer of the Partners HealthCare system (PHS), noted that PHS has been investing in the large-scale aggregation and collection of clinical data that can be used to power AI technologies, and is well position to serve as an AI hub with collaborators worldwide.</p>
<p>Massachusetts Governor Charlie Baker was impressed by the speakers and participants at the forum. &#8220;This is what I call rock star city,&#8221; Baker said in his opening remarks. &#8220;I&#8217;ve never seen such a terrific collection of intellectual capital.&#8221;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180423_1722-B-AF-1-150-PHOTO-1-2.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4299" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180423_1722-B-AF-1-150-PHOTO-1-2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="267" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>First Look: Next Wave of AI Breakthroughs</h2>
<p>In what has become a must-see event to kick off the forum, Monday&#8217;s First Look Session provided attendees with a look at 19 new innovations in AI-powered medical applications from investigators in the PHS system.</p>
<p>The depth and breadth of applications was impressive, including innovations in psychiatry, surgery, genetic profiling, in vitro fertilization, predicting C. difficile infection rates and blood group typing, just to name a few.</p>
<p>Ziad Obermeyer, MD, an emergency medicine clinician at Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital (BWH), presented a concept for using machine learning algorithm to improve the decision making process for costly medical tests.</p>
<p>&#8220;We&#8217;re seeing errors on both sides,&#8221; Dr. Obermeyer explained. &#8220;Predictably low risk patients are getting tested and predictability high risk patients are not getting tested.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;One thing clear to me is that anything would be better than what we are doing today.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;It won&#8217;t come as a surprise to anyone that doctors make mistakes, but we can use these algorithms to find out where and with whom those doctors make mistakes. Building on this understanding, you can come to a whole range of possibilities.&#8221;</p>
<p>Daniel Hashimoto, MD, a surgical resident at Massachusetts General Hospital (MGH), presented on a system called &#8220;Surgical Fingerprints&#8221; that is designed to reduce the risk of adverse intra-operative events by collecting data from previous surgeries and using that information to guide real-time decision making in the operating room.</p>
<p>&#8220;It&#8217;s like [the popular direction-finding app] Waze for surgery, but instead of avoiding traffic, it will allow you to avoid surgical complications,&#8221; Hashimoto explained.</p>
<h2>Discovery Café Workshops</h2>
<p>Following the First Look event, the crowd broke out into smaller groups for a series of Discovery Café Sessions taking a closer look at the potential for AI in pathology, anesthesiology, neurosciences, data security and the workforce.</p>
<p>In the neurosciences session, Maurizio Fava, MD, director of the Division of Clinical Research at MGH and the vice chair of the MGH Department of Psychiatry, noted that 20 percent of clinical trial participants never actually take the drug that is being tested,. Fava said he was hopeful that AI technology could help to identify and screen out those participants to improve the accuracy of results.</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180423_1722-B-AF-1-150-PHOTO-2.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4300" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180423_1722-B-AF-1-150-PHOTO-2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="133" /></a></p>
<h2>Panel Sessions</h2>
<p>Monday afternoon&#8217;s panel sessions began with a big picture view of AI in healthcare before digging deeper into specific areas of interest, such as the role of AI in drug development; the interaction of AI with electronic health records and the role of AI in improving clinical trials.</p>
<p>Tom Lynch, MD, Executive Vice President and Chief Scientific Officer of Bristol Myers Squibb, was optimistic that AI could help to streamline the movement of new molecules from discovery to development. The current process &#8220;takes way too long and costs way too much,&#8221; he said.</p>
<h2>Notable Tweets</h2>
<p>Charlie Baker | @MassGovernor<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/MassGovernor/status/988482008635592705" target="blank">Massachusetts is a leader in innovation, technology, and healthcare, and I&#8217;m excited to welcome so many leaders who are experts in these fields to the Commonwealth for the World Medical Innovation Forum here in Boston. #WMIF18</a></p>
<p>Nikhil Bhojwani | @bnikhil<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/bnikhil/status/988446432897257472" target="blank">&#8220;AI will not replace radiologists. Radiologists who embrace Ai will replace radiologists who don&#8217;t.&#8221; Bill Thorwarth, CEO American College of Radiology #WMIF18 @PHSInnovation #ArtificialIntelligence #radiology</a></p>
<p>Deepthi Bathina | @deepthibathina<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/deepthibathina/status/988409483151007744" target="blank">Expecting the impossible from clinicians ..to interpret 100s or 1000s of lab test results for patient diagnosis #AI and #MachineLearning can help #WMIF18 @NuanceHealth</a></p>
<p>Nick Mathisen | @njmathisen<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/njmathisen/status/988433830745968645" target="blank">I&#8217;ve only been at #wmif18 for 2 hours and brain is already melting from 19 amazing presentations on AI breakthroughs. Thanks @PHSInnovation</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-one-recap/">2018 World Forum &#8211; Day One Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
