<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Blog &#8211; 2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
	<atom:link href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/category/blog/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/</link>
	<description>Gene and Cell Therapy</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 19:56:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.5.6</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Blog &#8211; 2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
	<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Should Tech Entrepreneurs Aspire To Fix Clinical Trials Or Reinvent Them?</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/should-tech-entrepreneurs-aspire-to-fix-clinical-trials-or-reinvent-them/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 19:56:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[BWH]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[clinical trials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forbes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[World Medical Innovation Forum]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=4409</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Written by Forbes Contributor David Shaywitz Click here to view full article To fix or to reinvent?  That’s the question many would-be innovators ask as they contemplate potential applications of technology to health. Dr. Stephen Wiviott, a cardiologist and Senior Investigator with the legendary TIMI Study Group at Boston’s Brigham and Women’s (BWH) hospital, nicely represents ... <a title="Should Tech Entrepreneurs Aspire To Fix Clinical Trials Or Reinvent Them?" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/should-tech-entrepreneurs-aspire-to-fix-clinical-trials-or-reinvent-them/" aria-label="More on Should Tech Entrepreneurs Aspire To Fix Clinical Trials Or Reinvent Them?">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/should-tech-entrepreneurs-aspire-to-fix-clinical-trials-or-reinvent-them/">Should Tech Entrepreneurs Aspire To Fix Clinical Trials Or Reinvent Them?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Written by Forbes Contributor <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/davidshaywitz/" data-ga-track="contrib block byline">David Shaywitz </a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/davidshaywitz/2018/05/22/should-tech-entrepreneurs-aspire-to-fix-clinical-trials-or-reinvent-them/#2281428b775c">Click here to view full article</a></p>
<p class="speakable-paragraph">To fix or to reinvent?  That’s the question many would-be innovators ask as they contemplate potential applications of technology to health.</p>
<p>Dr. Stephen Wiviott, a cardiologist and Senior Investigator with the legendary TIMI Study Group at Boston’s Brigham and Women’s (BWH) hospital, nicely represents the views of what might be called the “fix it” folks. At a recent panel discussion at the World Medical Innovation Forum (viewable <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Snd0X0c_qSg" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-ga-track="ExternalLink:https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Snd0X0c_qSg">here</a>), Wiviott noted how expensive traditional randomized clinical trials (RCTs) can be, telling the audience that the cardiovascular (CV) outcome trial he’s now running for an SGLT2 medication involves the recruitment of 17,000 patients, will take seven years to complete, and will cost about half a billion (with a “b”) dollars.  He suspects that it shouldn’t need to cost nearly that much, and that improved regulations in particular, as well as improving efficiencies at each step of the trial (potentially with the help of data and technology) could take 90% of the cost out of the current system.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/should-tech-entrepreneurs-aspire-to-fix-clinical-trials-or-reinvent-them/">Should Tech Entrepreneurs Aspire To Fix Clinical Trials Or Reinvent Them?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Recap</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-three-recap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 13:07:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2018]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=4334</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>&#160; Recap &#124; April 25 World Medical Innovation Forum: Artificial Intelligence 1,700 registrants, 140 executive presenters and key leaders shape the future of artificial intelligence! The third day of the World Medical Innovation Forum featured a series of panel discussions and fireside chats that focused on ways that artificial intelligence (AI) can be used to ... <a title="2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Recap" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-three-recap/" aria-label="More on 2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Recap">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-three-recap/">2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/PartnersFORUM2018EMAILTEMPLATEBoston180425_1932B-AF3150HEADER2.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4335" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/PartnersFORUM2018EMAILTEMPLATEBoston180425_1932B-AF3150HEADER2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="693" /></a></h2>
<h2>Recap | April 25</h2>
<p><strong>World Medical Innovation Forum: Artificial Intelligence</strong><br />
<em>1,700 registrants, 140 executive presenters and key leaders shape the future of artificial intelligence!</em></p>
<p>The third day of the World Medical Innovation Forum featured a series of panel discussions and fireside chats that focused on ways that artificial intelligence (AI) can be used to improve the performance and data-gathering capabilities of medical devices, reduce health care costs, improve operational efficiencies across the healthcare system and mine new insights from clinical and research data.</p>
<p>&#8220;If you think about the magnitude of the information we have available to us in this space, you think about where technology is today and the compute horsepower that is available to all of us, it just makes sense to continue to evaluate technologies like artificial intelligence to be able to streamline not just operational and administrative efficiency, but be able to make more informed and timely decisions,&#8221; said Eric Murphy, CEO of OptumInsight and Enterprise Growth Officer at Optum, during a discussion on how AI technologies could factor into healthcare reimbursement systems.</p>
<p>Another engaging discussion focused on the concerns that AI technologies may eventually replace human pathologists and radiologists in diagnosing patients. The message from the speakers on this panel was that AI tools should be viewed as a friend, not a foe.</p>
<p>Constance Lehman, MD, PhD, Chief of Breast Imaging at Massachusetts General Hospital (MGH), said AI technologies have helped make imaging services at MGH more precise, targeted and personalized while reducing repetitive tasks that lead to burnout.</p>
<p>&#8220;Without a doubt this is on the friend side and a really powerful technology,&#8221; said Andrew Beck, MD, PhD, CEO, of PathAI. &#8220;The types of problems we are interested in solving are really hard and big and we&#8217;re very far from being able to effectively solve them, even with the AI of today. We&#8217;re very lucky that we have the access to these new technologies that will assist the profession.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/PartnersFORUM2018EMAILTEMPLATEBoston180425_1932B-AF3150PHOTO12.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4336" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/PartnersFORUM2018EMAILTEMPLATEBoston180425_1932B-AF3150PHOTO12.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="267" /></a></p>
<h2>Fireside Chats</h2>
<p>Wednesday&#8217;s Fireside Chat sessions provided valuable insights from healthcare leaders in the government, technology and pharmaceutical sectors.</p>
<p>&#8220;I&#8217;ve been in this industry for nearly four decades now. I honestly believe that I have never seen a technology that&#8217;s as transformative as this one,&#8221; said John Kelly, PhD, Senior Vice President for Cognitive Solutions and Research at IBM.</p>
<p>&#8220;The opportunity is enormous to transform this industry for better outcomes, lower costs for the benefit of all,&#8221; Kelly said. &#8220;But it&#8217;s now into the hard work portion of this. It is not easy to build a very intelligent, at scale, precise artificial intelligence system to be injected in the workflow of a clinical physician or a drug researcher. That is a big job. And by the way, you better have heck of a lot of good data to train that system.&#8221;</p>
<h2>The Disruptive Dozen: 12 AI Technologies That Will Reinvent Care</h2>
<p>The forum concluded on Wednesday afternoon with the presentation of the Disruptive Dozen, 12 technologies that faculty members in the Partners HealthCare System (PHS) believe have the potential to significantly advance healthcare in the next decade.</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/Partners-FORUM-2018-BROCHURE-D12-AI-180410_1202-FREV2-FOR-WEB-X3.pdf" target="blank">Follow this link to read all twelve.</a></p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/PartnersFORUM2018EMAILTEMPLATEBoston180425_1932B-AF3150PHOTO2.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4337" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/PartnersFORUM2018EMAILTEMPLATEBoston180425_1932B-AF3150PHOTO2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="133" /></a></p>
<h2>First Look Winners Announced!</h2>
<p>Congratulations to First Look presenters Sabine Wilhelm, PhD, from MGH and Ziad Obermeyer, MD, from Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital (BWH) for winning the Peter K. Ranney Innovation Award!</p>
<p>The award was presented at last night&#8217;s Innovator&#8217;s Dinner to honor the BWH and MGH First Look presenters who embodied the innovative, entrepreneurial and visionary spirit the World Medical Innovation Forum was established to recognize.</p>
<p>Here is some of the feedback the judges provided for the winners:</p>
<h5><em>Mobile Apps: Bridging the Mental Health Treatment Gap</em></h5>
<p><strong>Sabine Wilhelm, PhD</strong><br />
The concept of delivering cognitive behavioral therapy through a mobile app reduces traditional barriers to mental health treatment and tackles cost and access issues head on.<br />
Given the well demonstrated market need for better mental health care paradigms and relative maturity of the technology, the app may benefit from a potentially short commercialization timeline.<br />
The app is well positioned to passively collect substantial data that can inform computational models used to personalize treatment and provide real-time interventions.</p>
<h5><em>A Machine Learning Algorithm to Reduce Costs and Increase Quality</em></h5>
<p><strong>Ziad Obermeyer, MD</strong><br />
The presentation addressed the kind of multi-variate clinical challenges that AI/ML based approaches are well suited to address.<br />
The research has potential for dramatic impact on both cost and quality.<br />
There is real opportunity to expand the approach across clinical domains and disease conditions-a big idea with the potential for broad impact.</p>
<h2>Notable Tweets</h2>
<p>Timothy Howe | @HamiltonHowe<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/HamiltonHowe/status/989138416150503424">Vasant Narasimhan CEO of @Novartis, &#8220;We need to win the race of turtles&#8230;&#8221; commenting on how slow the industry is moving with regard to #AI and data collection. #WMIF18</a></p>
<p>BCBSNC | @BCBSNC<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/BCBSNC/status/989130703609782272">&#8220;We need to remove any remaining friction between insurers and #healthcare providers when it comes to sharing #data. We need a free flow of information.&#8221; &#8211; @PatrickConwayMD #WMIF18</a></p>
<p>Laura Lovett | @lauralovett7<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/lauralovett7/status/989234948241612800">Will robots be creating our meds in the future? Experts say probably not. But there is use for AI in pharma. I got to hang out at the World Medical Innovation Forum yesterday and hear all about it #WMIF18</a></p>
<p>Slalom Boston | @SlalomBoston<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/SlalomBoston/status/989194864427524096">It&#8217;s the final day of #WMIF18 and we&#8217;ve had a blast learning about #AI in #healthcare. Thanks to @PartnersNews for the outstanding event!</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-three-recap/">2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Three Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Recap</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-two-recap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 12:47:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2018]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=4329</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>&#160; Recap &#124; April 24 The Role of AI in Health Care Accessibility and Drug Discovery A closer look at how to turn the promise of implementing AI in health care into a reality. Day 2 of the World Medical Innovation Forum was packed with in-depth discussions on the opportunities and challenges of integrating artificial ... <a title="2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Recap" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-two-recap/" aria-label="More on 2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Recap">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-two-recap/">2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4330" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180424_1742B-AF2150HEADER2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="693" /></a></h2>
<h2>Recap | April 24</h2>
<p><strong>The Role of AI in Health Care Accessibility and Drug Discovery</strong><br />
<em>A closer look at how to turn the promise of implementing AI in health care into a reality.</em></p>
<p>Day 2 of the World Medical Innovation Forum was packed with in-depth discussions on the opportunities and challenges of integrating artificial intelligence (AI) into the health care system, with an up-close look at the role AI could play in delivering affordable health care, supporting clinical decision making, processing large amounts of data and speeding up drug development.</p>
<p>The discussion also highlighted some key challenges in AI integration, such as convincing clinicians, patients and payors of the value of AI technology, standardizing data across platforms, and protecting patient privacy in a digitized world.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4332" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180424_1742B-AF2150PHOTO12.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="267" /></a></p>
<h2>The Importance of Data</h2>
<p>Data collection was a key topic in many sessions throughout the day. &#8220;The theme you will hear over and over is very high quality, well-curated data,&#8221; said Mark Murcko, PhD, Chief Science Officer of Relay Therapeutics, during a session on drug development. &#8220;One of the big challenges we have is to better represent the interactions that molecules are having. Just to tease out that little bit of insight that helps the drug discovery team move a little faster.&#8221;</p>
<p>A panel discussion on Data Engineering in Health Care emphasized the importance of engaging patients in discovery process and convincing them that the benefits of sharing their health information with clinicians and researchers outweigh the risks of a potential data breach.</p>
<p>James Mault, MD, Senior Vice President and Chief Medical Officer for Qualcomm Life, noted that 15 years ago many people were hesitant about using their credit cards to make purchases online, but today nearly everyone has their information stored on website such as Amazon because of the convenience it provides.</p>
<p>&#8220;The risk is still there, but we&#8217;re willing to accept that risk because we&#8217;re getting these tremendous benefits,&#8221; he said. &#8220;In health care we&#8217;re seeing a lot of risk, but we&#8217;re not yet seeing a lot of benefit.&#8221;</p>
<h2>Fireside Chats</h2>
<p>Day 2 also featured a series of one-on-one fireside chats. Atul Gawande, MD, a surgeon at Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital (BWH) and bestselling author of Being Mortal and The Checklist Manifesto (among others), told Brigham Health President Elizabeth Nabel, MD, that the key to successfully integrating AI technology into clinical care is to identify clear benefits for both the patient and the clinician-and to ensure that the health care providers are ready and willing to use it.</p>
<p>&#8220;If you give people a great process solution, the perfect innovation tool, and plug it into a ready environment, you make a major impact.&#8221;</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4333" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180424_1742B-AF2150PHOTO2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="133" /></a></p>
<h2>Afternoon Panel Sessions</h2>
<p>In a panel session on AI and Genetic Sequencing, moderator Heidi Rehm, PhD, said that while researchers are now able to collect much more genetic data from patients, their ability to process and take action on that data is still lagging behind.</p>
<p>&#8220;The team in my laboratory still reads articles in the literature to try to figure out what these variants mean,&#8221; Rehm said. &#8220;We will never be able to disseminate these technologies for broad medical use if we can&#8217;t advance what we are doing today in terms of understanding the genetic and genomic variation.&#8221;</p>
<p>Despite the concerns raised and the work that still needs to be done, the tone of the day&#8217;s sessions were overwhelming positive, with nearly all participants saying they believed that AI technology could make significant improvements in the delivery of health care.</p>
<p>In a CEO roundtable discussion hosted by Peter Slavin, MD, President of Massachusetts General Hospital, Terri Bresenham, Chief Executive Officer for GE Healthcare, shared her optimistic outlook.</p>
<p>&#8220;We&#8217;re very bullish,&#8221; Bresenham said. &#8220;I think there&#8217;s no doubt that this will be by far the most transformational technology change that is going to occur, in concert with some other very important changes in genomics and genetics and biotherapies as well as diagnostics and imaging technology.&#8221;</p>
<h2>Notable Tweets</h2>
<p>Samuel Myllykangas | @SamuMyllykangas<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/SamuMyllykangas/status/988861177777344519">CEO panel: #AI will transform healthcare by expanding access to care, improving quality, reducing cost, streamlining information flow and integration, accelerating drug discovery, supporting decision making and supplementing research. #WMIF18</a></p>
<p>Behrooz Hashemian | @behxyz<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/behxyz/status/988862279461560321">Amazing roundtable with CIO and CEO&#8217;s from @Philips, @SiemensHealth, @Vertex, and @GEHealthcare, talking about the AI opportunities in healthcare and how it is transforming the industry. #WMIF18 @MassGeneralNews</a></p>
<p>Cassie Lee | @cassan_druh<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/cassan_druh/status/988780880796831744">Understanding that you in the #innovation world have two customers: you have the patient whose lives you have to make better, and you have the clinicians who you need to make easy tools for that scale &#8211; @Atul_Gawande at #WMIF18 @BrighamWomens</a></p>
<p>Dan Hashimoto | @Laparoscopes<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/Laparoscopes/status/988806822642544640">I want @Nvidia to be an intelligent autonomous machine. I want @NvidiaAI to be an #AI. #AI needs to do 3 things: perception of the environment, reason about what it&#8217;s perceiving, develop a plan to take action. &#8211; CEO Jensen Huang #WMIF18</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-two-recap/">2018 World Forum &#8211; Day Two Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2018 World Forum &#8211; Day One Recap</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-one-recap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 13:24:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2018]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=4296</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>&#160; Recap &#124; April 23 A Sell Out Crowd The fourth annual World Medical Innovation Forum (WMIF) sponsored by Partners Innovation, kicked off Monday morning with a record attendance of 1,600 participants representing the top healthcare, biotech and venture capital firms from across the globe. The theme of this year&#8217;s forum is Artificial Intelligence (AI), ... <a title="2018 World Forum &#8211; Day One Recap" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-one-recap/" aria-label="More on 2018 World Forum &#8211; Day One Recap">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-one-recap/">2018 World Forum &#8211; Day One Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180423_1722-B-AF-1-150-HEADER-2.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4297" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180423_1722-B-AF-1-150-HEADER-2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="693" /></a></h2>
<h2>Recap | April 23</h2>
<p><strong>A Sell Out Crowd</strong></p>
<p>The fourth annual World Medical Innovation Forum (WMIF) sponsored by Partners Innovation, kicked off Monday morning with a record attendance of 1,600 participants representing the top healthcare, biotech and venture capital firms from across the globe.</p>
<p>The theme of this year&#8217;s forum is Artificial Intelligence (AI), and much of the discussion on Day One focused on the promise, complexities and limitations of AI in healthcare.</p>
<p>Speakers were optimistic about the potential for AI to drive big improvements in predicting disease, treating patients and managing outcomes, but also cautioned that the technology is still in its early stages and there will likely be some growing pains along the way.</p>
<p>In her opening remarks, Anne Klibanski, MD, Chief Academic Officer of the Partners HealthCare system (PHS), noted that PHS has been investing in the large-scale aggregation and collection of clinical data that can be used to power AI technologies, and is well position to serve as an AI hub with collaborators worldwide.</p>
<p>Massachusetts Governor Charlie Baker was impressed by the speakers and participants at the forum. &#8220;This is what I call rock star city,&#8221; Baker said in his opening remarks. &#8220;I&#8217;ve never seen such a terrific collection of intellectual capital.&#8221;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180423_1722-B-AF-1-150-PHOTO-1-2.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4299" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180423_1722-B-AF-1-150-PHOTO-1-2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="267" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>First Look: Next Wave of AI Breakthroughs</h2>
<p>In what has become a must-see event to kick off the forum, Monday&#8217;s First Look Session provided attendees with a look at 19 new innovations in AI-powered medical applications from investigators in the PHS system.</p>
<p>The depth and breadth of applications was impressive, including innovations in psychiatry, surgery, genetic profiling, in vitro fertilization, predicting C. difficile infection rates and blood group typing, just to name a few.</p>
<p>Ziad Obermeyer, MD, an emergency medicine clinician at Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital (BWH), presented a concept for using machine learning algorithm to improve the decision making process for costly medical tests.</p>
<p>&#8220;We&#8217;re seeing errors on both sides,&#8221; Dr. Obermeyer explained. &#8220;Predictably low risk patients are getting tested and predictability high risk patients are not getting tested.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;One thing clear to me is that anything would be better than what we are doing today.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;It won&#8217;t come as a surprise to anyone that doctors make mistakes, but we can use these algorithms to find out where and with whom those doctors make mistakes. Building on this understanding, you can come to a whole range of possibilities.&#8221;</p>
<p>Daniel Hashimoto, MD, a surgical resident at Massachusetts General Hospital (MGH), presented on a system called &#8220;Surgical Fingerprints&#8221; that is designed to reduce the risk of adverse intra-operative events by collecting data from previous surgeries and using that information to guide real-time decision making in the operating room.</p>
<p>&#8220;It&#8217;s like [the popular direction-finding app] Waze for surgery, but instead of avoiding traffic, it will allow you to avoid surgical complications,&#8221; Hashimoto explained.</p>
<h2>Discovery Café Workshops</h2>
<p>Following the First Look event, the crowd broke out into smaller groups for a series of Discovery Café Sessions taking a closer look at the potential for AI in pathology, anesthesiology, neurosciences, data security and the workforce.</p>
<p>In the neurosciences session, Maurizio Fava, MD, director of the Division of Clinical Research at MGH and the vice chair of the MGH Department of Psychiatry, noted that 20 percent of clinical trial participants never actually take the drug that is being tested,. Fava said he was hopeful that AI technology could help to identify and screen out those participants to improve the accuracy of results.</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180423_1722-B-AF-1-150-PHOTO-2.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4300" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/180423_1722-B-AF-1-150-PHOTO-2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="133" /></a></p>
<h2>Panel Sessions</h2>
<p>Monday afternoon&#8217;s panel sessions began with a big picture view of AI in healthcare before digging deeper into specific areas of interest, such as the role of AI in drug development; the interaction of AI with electronic health records and the role of AI in improving clinical trials.</p>
<p>Tom Lynch, MD, Executive Vice President and Chief Scientific Officer of Bristol Myers Squibb, was optimistic that AI could help to streamline the movement of new molecules from discovery to development. The current process &#8220;takes way too long and costs way too much,&#8221; he said.</p>
<h2>Notable Tweets</h2>
<p>Charlie Baker | @MassGovernor<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/MassGovernor/status/988482008635592705" target="blank">Massachusetts is a leader in innovation, technology, and healthcare, and I&#8217;m excited to welcome so many leaders who are experts in these fields to the Commonwealth for the World Medical Innovation Forum here in Boston. #WMIF18</a></p>
<p>Nikhil Bhojwani | @bnikhil<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/bnikhil/status/988446432897257472" target="blank">&#8220;AI will not replace radiologists. Radiologists who embrace Ai will replace radiologists who don&#8217;t.&#8221; Bill Thorwarth, CEO American College of Radiology #WMIF18 @PHSInnovation #ArtificialIntelligence #radiology</a></p>
<p>Deepthi Bathina | @deepthibathina<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/deepthibathina/status/988409483151007744" target="blank">Expecting the impossible from clinicians ..to interpret 100s or 1000s of lab test results for patient diagnosis #AI and #MachineLearning can help #WMIF18 @NuanceHealth</a></p>
<p>Nick Mathisen | @njmathisen<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/njmathisen/status/988433830745968645" target="blank">I&#8217;ve only been at #wmif18 for 2 hours and brain is already melting from 19 amazing presentations on AI breakthroughs. Thanks @PHSInnovation</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2018-day-one-recap/">2018 World Forum &#8211; Day One Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Partners Sets the Tone for Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/partners-sets-the-tone-for-artificial-intelligence-in-healthcare-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2018 18:21:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=4179</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>by Health IT Analytics March 21, 2018 &#8211; Despite the fact that the healthcare industry hit its EHR saturation point some time ago, providers and vendors are still eagerly engaged in dialogue about the utilization and continued optimization of health IT tools. But the topics of debate have shifted away from how to become a digital enterprise ... <a title="Partners Sets the Tone for Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/partners-sets-the-tone-for-artificial-intelligence-in-healthcare-2/" aria-label="More on Partners Sets the Tone for Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/partners-sets-the-tone-for-artificial-intelligence-in-healthcare-2/">Partners Sets the Tone for Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Health IT Analytics</p>
<p><time datetime="2018-3-21">March 21, 2018</time> &#8211; Despite the fact that the healthcare industry hit its EHR saturation point some time ago, providers and vendors are still eagerly engaged in dialogue about the utilization and continued optimization of health IT tools.</p>
<p>But the topics of debate have shifted away from how to become a digital enterprise and towards something bigger and more visionary: <a href="https://healthitanalytics.com/features/how-healthcare-can-prep-for-artificial-intelligence-machine-learning">how to use</a> an organization’s growing data assets to measurably impact cost, patient-provider experiences, and the quality of care.</p>
<p>No discussion of these critical issues would be complete without at least a passing mention of machine learning and artificial intelligence – and for many organizations, including Partners Healthcare, these emerging strategies are at the center of the conversation.</p>
<p>“Artificial intelligence will have succeeded when we no longer talk about it,” said Mark Michalski, MD, Executive Director of the MGH &amp; BWH Center for Clinical Data Science.  “The health system will simply be smarter and better without the need to distinguish it from anything else.”</p>
<p>“But for now, it’s something that we do need to talk about because there’s so much to discover and so many opportunities to refine our thinking and our approaches.”</p>
<p>Partners Healthcare, which includes notable facilities such as Massachusetts General Hospital and Brigham and Women’s Hospital, is taking a leading role as a convener of those conversations by hosting the <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">World Medical Innovation Forum on Artificial Intelligence</a>.</p>
<p>The three-day event, held in Boston on April 23-25, 2018, will bring Partners experts, Harvard Medical School faculty, and numerous luminaries from the developer and vendor community to set the expectations and potential for AI in healthcare.</p>
<p>“We are at this very exciting pivot point in healthcare, and AI is a catalyst accelerating the industry’s transformation,” says Partners Healthcare Chief Information Officer Christopher Coburn. “It isn’t going to take long at all for the effects of AI to spread across all of healthcare.”</p>
<p>Many medical disciplines are already feeling those effects, agreed Michalski.  A radiologist by training, he is keenly aware that artificial intelligence is already becoming a force to be reckoned with in image-based specialties.</p>
<p>“Machine learning has <a href="https://healthitanalytics.com/news/ai-for-imaging-analytics-intrigues-healthcare-orgs-yet-starts-slow">tremendous promise</a> for diagnostics, including in my field of radiology,” he told <em>HealthITAnalytics.com</em>.  “It is very good at processing images, and characterizing the features in those images, to make radiologists more efficient and help them make their reports more quantitative and useful for the patients they serve.”</p>
<p>However, these early success don’t mean that artificial intelligence is going to be taking the place of pathologists, radiologists, and other diagnosticians in the near future.</p>
<p>While it is easy to get caught up in predictions of autonomous AI clinicians, Michalski suggests a bit of <a href="https://healthitanalytics.com/features/navigating-the-hype-of-healthcare-artificial-intelligence-companies">healthy skepticism</a> about the notion that highly-trained individuals will be supplanted by machines any time soon.</p>
<p>“We’re hearing a lot in the popular press about the power of this technology, and there are articles coming out from some very smart people that say artificial intelligence will replace certain job functions or categories, which can be a little bit intimidating or even a little frightening,” he acknowledged.</p>
<p>“That comes from not yet fully understanding the boundaries of this technology and what it is really capable of doing.”</p>
<p>Artificial intelligence may be starting to get very good at classification, but human intelligence is still required to supervise AI efforts and cast a critical eye over its results.</p>
<p>“AI is very accomplished at some things, but it’s still not very good at performing other tasks,” Michalski noted.  “At the Center for Clinical Data Science, part of our mission is to define those boundaries and understand how these tools fail so we can improve them.  If AI was perfect, we wouldn’t have so much work to do every day.”</p>
<p>Instead of replacing clinicians entirely, both Michalski and Coburn believe AI will take an important supporting role.</p>
<p>“There’s a great quote that’s along the lines of ‘not all radiologists will be replaced by AI, but the radiologists who are not expert in AI will be replaced by the ones who are,’” said Coburn.</p>
<p>“AI is going to help clinicians of all types improve the things they’re doing right now.  And it will also enable some things that have never been done before. Clinicians are curious about what that is going to look like and how AI can help them become more effective and efficient.”</p>
<p>Using artificial intelligence to improve operational efficiencies and <a href="https://healthitanalytics.com/news/can-artificial-intelligence-relieve-electronic-health-record-burnout">the EHR workflow</a> are very attractive use cases, he added.</p>
<p>“A lot of folks feel like the rise of electronic health records is coming between physicians and their patients,” he said.  “AI has the potential to reinforce the human aspect of healthcare and pull back a lot of the clumsiness of the technology interfaces we have today.  There’s a lot of hopefulness around that.”</p>
<p>Top executives and developers from a number of organizations, including Epic Systems, Change Healthcare, Optum, Nuance, Microsoft, and Health Catalyst will share their views on how to create more intuitive EHRs and more intelligent decision-making opportunities in both the clinical and operational environments.</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/agenda/">Other sessions</a> will focus on the role of AI in drug development and precision medicine, as well as the challenges of regulating technologies that leverage brand new approaches to collecting, analyzing, and sharing big data.</p>
<p>“You’re going to see luminaries who are leading their segments of the field right now as well as folks who will be the absolute stars of their disciplines in five or ten years,” said Coburn.</p>
<p>“And there are no PowerPoints,” he added.  “We have worked hard to create opportunities for shared insights in a very rich, discussion-based format.  It’s all about communicating actionable ideas through conversations, which I think is the best way to learn.”</p>
<p>To close out the event, Partners will be putting its money where its mouth is, Coburn continued, by awarding grant funding to a series of new machine learning and AI tools developed within the Partners community.</p>
<p>“We’re going to announce the ten internal technologies that we’re going to put $50,000 against,” he said.  “That’s $50,000 each.  We’ll also be sharing our faculty’s selections of the twelve AI technologies they think will be most disruptive over the next decade.”</p>
<p>The event is designed to provide a comprehensive look at how artificial intelligence is currently used – and how it will evolve over the next few years – to significantly <a href="https://healthitanalytics.com/news/artificial-intelligence-in-healthcare-gets-cheaper-and-quicker">disrupt the health IT status quo</a>, said Coburn.</p>
<p>Clinicians, developers, data scientists, health IT leaders, investors, and provider executives are all encouraged to attend the crash-course in machine learning and its impacts on the industry, he urged.</p>
<p>“If you only had three days in all of 2018 to devote to AI, these would be the three days you’d want to spend doing it,” said Coburn.  “You’ll come out of there having learned what technologies are going to make the biggest impact and what areas of healthcare will be most affected by them.”</p>
<p>“It’ll be excellent preparation for making the right moves in your own organization, and we could all use as much preparation as we can get when it comes to making important decisions.”</p>
<p><a href="https://healthitanalytics.com/news/partners-sets-the-tone-for-artificial-intelligence-in-healthcare">https://healthitanalytics.com/news/partners-sets-the-tone-for-artificial-intelligence-in-healthcare</a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/partners-sets-the-tone-for-artificial-intelligence-in-healthcare-2/">Partners Sets the Tone for Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Partners Sets the Tone for Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/partners-sets-the-tone-for-artificial-intelligence-in-healthcare/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2018 18:17:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=4178</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Partners Healthcare, which includes notable facilities such as Massachusetts General Hospital and Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital, is taking a leading role as a convener of those conversations by hosting the World Medical Innovation Forum on Artificial Intelligence. The three-day event, held in Boston &#8230;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/partners-sets-the-tone-for-artificial-intelligence-in-healthcare/">Partners Sets the Tone for Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>Partners Healthcare</strong>, which includes notable facilities such as Massachusetts General Hospital and Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital, is taking a leading role as a convener of those conversations by hosting the <strong>World Medical Innovation</strong> <strong>Forum</strong> on Artificial Intelligence. The three-day event, held in Boston &#8230;</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/partners-sets-the-tone-for-artificial-intelligence-in-healthcare/">Partners Sets the Tone for Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reinventing Cardiovascular and Cardiometabolic Care Focus of Global Gathering</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/reinventing-cardiovascular-cardiometabolic-care-focus-global-gathering/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 12:10:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=3449</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>BOSTON&#8211;(BUSINESS WIRE)&#8211;Partners HealthCare, the nation’s largest academic research enterprise, today announced the third annual World Medical Innovation Forum, which will bring together nearly 1,000 international cardiovascular innovation decision-makers from industry, investment, clinical and research communities from May 1 to May 3, 2017 in Boston.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/reinventing-cardiovascular-cardiometabolic-care-focus-global-gathering/">Reinventing Cardiovascular and Cardiometabolic Care Focus of Global Gathering</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>BOSTON&#8211;(<a href="http://www.businesswire.com/" rel="nofollow">BUSINESS WIRE</a>)&#8211;Partners HealthCare, the nation’s largest academic research enterprise, today announced the third annual World Medical Innovation Forum, which will bring together nearly 1,000 international cardiovascular innovation decision-makers from industry, investment, clinical and research communities from May 1 to May 3, 2017 in Boston.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/reinventing-cardiovascular-cardiometabolic-care-focus-global-gathering/">Reinventing Cardiovascular and Cardiometabolic Care Focus of Global Gathering</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2017 World Medical Innovation Forum Sets Sights on Cardiovascular Innovation</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2017-world-medical-innovation-forum-sets-sights-cardiovascular-innovation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 12:08:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=3448</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>At the conclusion of the 2017 World Medical Innovation Forum: Cardiovascular, attendees left with a renewed sense of understanding about how the medical and scientific communities will work together to combat one of the largest health-related killers around the globe.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2017-world-medical-innovation-forum-sets-sights-cardiovascular-innovation/">2017 World Medical Innovation Forum Sets Sights on Cardiovascular Innovation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At the conclusion of the 2017 <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">World Medical Innovation Forum: Cardiovascular</a>, attendees left with a renewed sense of understanding about how the medical and scientific communities will work together to combat one of the largest health-related killers around the globe.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/2017-world-medical-innovation-forum-sets-sights-cardiovascular-innovation/">2017 World Medical Innovation Forum Sets Sights on Cardiovascular Innovation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Medical Innovation Forum 2017: The Future of Cardiovascular Care</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-medical-innovation-forum-2017-future-cardiovascular-care/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2017 19:34:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=3141</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Anthony Rosenzweig, MD, chief of cardiology and co-director of the Corrigan Minehan Heart Center at MGH, describes a paradox at the center of heart disease. On the one hand, the last half-century has seen a dramatic drop in death rates among patients hospitalized for a heart attack. On the other hand, survivors often go on ... <a title="World Medical Innovation Forum 2017: The Future of Cardiovascular Care" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-medical-innovation-forum-2017-future-cardiovascular-care/" aria-label="More on World Medical Innovation Forum 2017: The Future of Cardiovascular Care">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-medical-innovation-forum-2017-future-cardiovascular-care/">World Medical Innovation Forum 2017: The Future of Cardiovascular Care</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<header class="fl-post-header">
<p class="fl-post-title">Anthony Rosenzweig, MD, chief of cardiology and co-director of the Corrigan Minehan Heart Center at MGH, describes a paradox at the center of heart disease. On the one hand, the last half-century has seen a dramatic drop in death rates among patients hospitalized for a heart attack. On the other hand, survivors often go on to develop chronic conditions that are expensive and ultimately deadly. Add the aging of the world’s population and the epidemic of metabolic diseases, and heart disease remains the number one killer in the United States and most of the world, with its burden expected to increase over the coming decades.</p>
</header>
<div class="fl-post-content clearfix">
<p>The changing spectrum of heart disease has produced new clinical needs, and marshaling an effective response will require cooperation among a diverse array of stakeholders. Technology, patent insights and clinical management have combined to propel diagnosis, treatment and long term care into a new threshold. To accelerate this process, Rosenzweig and Calum MacRae, MD, PhD are co-chairing the World Medical Innovation Forum on May 1–3, 2017 to be held in Boston at the Westin Copley hotel.</p>
<p>Many top leaders from throughout the industry, government and investment communities will speak including the CEOs of a large number of leading organizations including Abiomed, AHA, Amgen, Bard, Boehringer Ingelheim, Boston Scientific, Cardinal Health, Edwards, GE Healthcare, LivaNova, Lilly, Medtronic, Mirna, Myokardia, Philips, Siemens, Yumanity, Zafgen and Zoll Medical. They will be joined by top investors, the heads of the FDA, NHLBI and key executives from CMS and other entities.</p>
<p>This year’s agenda captures the excitement of the newly emerging chapter of cardiovascular and cardiometabolic care. It will highlight the newest approaches to treating heart failure and atherosclerosis, personal monitoring tools, breakthrough devices, metabolic syndrome, changes in pricing and policy, flexible trial design and much more. Cardiology is at the leading edge of the ongoing revolution across biomedicine and the Forum will seek to understand how this will affect every part of the translational cycle.</p>
<p>The Forum will open with twenty rising BWH and MGH stars, Harvard Medical School faculty, describing the clinical potential of their work in cardiovascular and cardiometabolic care. Discovery Café workshops will follow, led by senior Harvard faculty addressing cutting-edge cardiovascular challenges. On the final day, a panel of clinical experts from BWH and MGH will announce their selections for the “Disruptive Dozen,” the technologies likely that will have the greatest impact on cardiovascular and cardiometabolic care in the next decade.</p>
<p>MacRae describes the goal of this year’s forum as “to bring all our expertise together around the problems that our current and potential industrial partners recognize as the barriers in the future, and really think through together with these partners how we can best overcome the challenges.”</p>
<p>“Too often,” says Rosenzweig, “we are in our isolated environments and not really reaching out and interacting with our counterparts on the other side.” But, he adds, “there is no more exciting time to be in cardiovascular medicine than now. The tools we have for attacking these problems are so much more robust than they have ever been before, and the ability to merge science and clinical medicine is unparalleled. We have a large unmet need, and the hope is that industry-academic partnerships will grow out of this to move that forward.”</p>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-medical-innovation-forum-2017-future-cardiovascular-care/">World Medical Innovation Forum 2017: The Future of Cardiovascular Care</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Calum MacRae, MD, PhD: One Brave Heart</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/calum-macrae-md-phd-one-brave-heart/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2017 19:32:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/?p=3140</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Musing over the proposal that netted him a $75 million “One Brave Idea” prize from the American Heart Association, Calum MacRae, MD, PhD, recognizing the many applicants for the grant, credits good luck and strong collaborations over ingenuity. “I think the funders were brave to give us the money.” Nevertheless, MacRae, chief of cardiovascular medicine ... <a title="Calum MacRae, MD, PhD: One Brave Heart" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/calum-macrae-md-phd-one-brave-heart/" aria-label="More on Calum MacRae, MD, PhD: One Brave Heart">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/calum-macrae-md-phd-one-brave-heart/">Calum MacRae, MD, PhD: One Brave Heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<header class="fl-post-header">
<p class="fl-post-title">Musing over the proposal that netted him a $75 million “One Brave Idea” prize from the American Heart Association, Calum MacRae, MD, PhD, recognizing the many applicants for the grant, credits good luck and strong collaborations over ingenuity. “I think the funders were brave to give us the money.”</p>
</header>
<div class="fl-post-content clearfix">
<p>Nevertheless, MacRae, chief of cardiovascular medicine at Brigham and Women’s Hospital, possesses a breadth of expertise and a big-picture outlook that seem ideally suited to the purpose of the award—to support a groundbreaking idea aimed at preventing or reversing coronary heart disease. The prize is jointly funded by the American Heart Association, Google’s Verily, and AstraZenica.</p>
<p>MacRae’s aim is to develop a more complete understanding of the phenotype of cardiac disease through a combination of technological innovation and a holistic approach that views nearly every aspect of an individual’s biology as potentially relevant to the disease process. To MacRae, who runs both clinical and basic research programs studying the genetics of heart disease, “at the end of the day, genetics is the easy part; there is a single way of understanding the genomes of bacteria, conifers, humans, and everything in between.”</p>
<p>The phenotype—the various forms in which a condition expresses itself during a person’s life, starting long before there is any outward sign of illness—has received too little attention. With new dynamic phenotypes, it will be possible to improve the utility of patients’ genotypes and, in many cases, to identify the biological pathways involved in disease. With better measurement of phenotypes and the environment, and new understanding of how these enormously complex interactions lead to disease, according to MacRae, will address the rate-limiting step in modern medicine.</p>
<p>If MacRae’s proposal challenges the current cardiovascular research paradigm, that’s because the creators of the One Brave Idea prize chose to break with traditional methods of funding. Attendees were informed of the prize and given a scant four weeks to respond. Fortunately, the first-round application consisted of only four questions, each of which had to be answered in 250 words or less.</p>
<p>MacRae’s winning idea—his one brave idea, if you will—was that for the first time it might be possible to describe the phenotype of cardiac disease in a way that is precise enough, and early enough, to allow for interventions that stop it before it causes serious damage. But to do so required looking at individuals much earlier in life, and in far greater depth, than had been done previously.</p>
<p>MacRae seeks a holistic understanding of cardiac disease. In addition to studying patients’ genomes, epigenomes, transcriptomes, and proteomes, the team will collect information on a broad range of characteristics, including features of skin, bone, behavior, and more. Though most may turn out not to be relevant to heart disease, chances are that some will, and the only way to find them is to look.</p>
<p>To illustrate where such an approach might lead, MacRae offers the example of obesity. Maybe the reason for obesity is the genetic variants that cause the disease also change the way you think about food. Or maybe they change the bacteria in your gut. We’re trying to be agnostic in the way we think about coronary heart disease. We need to think about it as a heart disease or a cholesterol disease but as a problem that we need to solve. Unless you understand the whole patient and the whole disease, it’s very difficult to understand how any individual piece of it might work.”</p>
<p>This approach would not be possible without a grant on the scale of the One Brave Idea prize. MacRae compares it to funding a startup company with its “fail-quickly” approach that supports risk-taking – “do fifty experiments, then pick the two that really work and take them across the finish line. I’m under no illusions as to how easy it will be.”<br />
After decades of medicine dominated by specialists, MacRae sees a resurgence in the role of the generalist – “but a different type of generalist, one interested in learning the fundamental rules of how everything fits together, which is made possible by new technologies and new methods of analysis.</p>
<p>The end result won’t simply be a better understanding of heart disease or even better treatment and prevention. For one thing, MacRae sees this project as overturning the way science is done. For another, it has the potential to change the doctor-patient relationship. Patient visits are shorter than they used to be, and most of the time is spent collecting data. Technology should improve collection and analysis before, during and after the appointment, freeing up time for the doctor to get to know patients on a deeper level.</p>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/calum-macrae-md-phd-one-brave-heart/">Calum MacRae, MD, PhD: One Brave Heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
