<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>2015 &#8211; 2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
	<atom:link href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/tag/2015/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/</link>
	<description>Gene and Cell Therapy</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 May 2015 22:21:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.5.6</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>2015 &#8211; 2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
	<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>World Medical Innovation Forum Day 3 Recap</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-medical-innovation-forum-day-3-recap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2015 22:21:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1514</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The final day of the inaugural Partners HealthCare World Medical Innovation Forum was a fittingly profound end to a thought-provoking meeting that featured leaders from business, research, and clinical practice discussing the most important and relevant topics of the day related to healthcare and brain disease. Reshaping Innovation Through Electronic Health The day began with ... <a title="World Medical Innovation Forum Day 3 Recap" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-medical-innovation-forum-day-3-recap/" aria-label="More on World Medical Innovation Forum Day 3 Recap">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-medical-innovation-forum-day-3-recap/">World Medical Innovation Forum Day 3 Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The final day of the inaugural Partners HealthCare World Medical Innovation Forum was a fittingly profound end to a thought-provoking meeting that featured leaders from business, research, and clinical practice discussing the most important and relevant topics of the day related to healthcare and brain disease.</p>
<p><em><strong>Reshaping Innovation Through Electronic Health</strong></em></p>
<p>The day began with a conversation on the history and current implementation of electronic health records between Partners’ Chief Clinical Officer, Gregg Meyer, MD and Judy Faulkner, the founder and CEO of leading electronic medical records company, EPIC Systems. Faulkner shared the story behind and the philosophy with which grew the company 100% organically (without mergers or acquisitions) from a 2-employee shop in a basement in Madison, Wisconsin, to a healthcare software powerhouse with approximately $2 billion in annual revenues and over 6,000 employees. She explained that EPIC Systems designed the software from the very beginning with the patients and their records as the central focus and organizing principle.</p>
<p>EPIC systems supports all functions related to patient care, including registration, scheduling; clinical systems for doctors, nurses, lab technologists, pharmacists, radiologist and billing systems for insurers. With the comprehensive implementation of EPIC at Partners currently underway, Faulkner offered some suggestions about the implementation based on the experience of EPIC’s other major clients. She suggested that providers and administrators should take advantage of EPIC’s customization options, training offerings, user groups, and especially “MyChart,” the patient engagement platform, which is unusual among its peers because it has 10 times the number of patient users as it does provider users—illustrating that the patients are very engaged. Patients see it has a form of freedom, being able to fill out their own information in some cases, providing better care through self service. The applications vary from engagement through scheduling and payment, to video doctors’ “visits.”</p>
<p><em><strong>Gene Editing, Gene Therapy, and the Eye as a Gateway</strong> </em></p>
<p>During this panel discussion, leaders from industry and research discussed the progress and promises of developing effective gene therapies. Eric Pierce, MD, PhD, of Mass. Eye and Ear and Harvard Medical School, stated his sense that the community is truly “on the threshold of using all these technologies.” The panelists recalled some of the challenges and failures of the past 20 years, but highlighted some extraordinary advances, compelling drug candidates, and continued confidence in gene therapies becoming a more and more integral therapy for providers for both rare and eventually more common diseases (including HIV, sickle cell anemia, and thalassemia). Another panelist noted the great success of the CRISPR gene-editing platform, stating that scientists were overheard making statements rarely heard in genomics, such as “I tried it and it worked”. CRISPR is empowering scientists to make quick and inexpensive edits to stretch of DNA with a level of ease and efficiency not previously possible.</p>
<p><em><strong>MS Transformed: Harnessing Biology and Inflammation</strong></em></p>
<p>“MS Transformed: Harnessing Biology and Inflammation” brought together an expert panel across disciplines: Tim Coetzee, PhD, Chief Advocacy, Services, and Research Officer at the National Multiple Sclerosis Society, Alfred Sandrock, MD, PhD, Group Senior Vice President and Chief Medical Officer at Biogen, Howard Weiner, MD, Founder and Director of the Partners Multiple Sclerosis Center, and Michael Panzara, MD, Group Vice President and Therapeutic Area Head of Multiple Sclerosis and Neurology at Genzyme.</p>
<p>The panelists began the conversation by providing context into the multiple sclerosis (MS) landscape since the condition’s initial description 150 years ago. At the beginning of Weiner’s career in the 1970s, there was very little understanding of MS and no treatments or MRI scans available for diagnosis, treatment, and assessment of the disease. Today, MS is thought to be a success story within neurologic disease discovery as there are 12 FDA approved drugs on the market. The rapid rate of drug discovery and available MS therapies is largely due to a greater understanding of the mechanisms behind MS, the identification of testable targets, and measurable outcomes thanks to advances in biomarkers and MRI imaging.</p>
<p>These 12 drugs currently on the market are utilized as treatments of the relapsing-remitting type of MS and there are no known therapies specifically for secondary-progressive MS. This leaves behind a large population of MS patients in terms of therapeutic development and makes the current treatment choices far from perfect. Clinically, MS patients often go through a trial and error process to see which medications work best for them. Some patients can switch therapies for years before finding the right fit for them while brain damage continues to occur.</p>
<p>The emphasis on increased treatment options for individuals with MS leads into the question of what a cure will inevitably look like. Dr. Weiner mentions his three prong approach to a “cure”, which consists of: 1) rebuilding a damaged nervous system, possibly via stem cells and myelin repair, 2) controlling attacks through individualized therapies to stabilize the condition, and 3) eradicating MS through a preventative vaccine. Under this notion, the pioneering drug discovery process of the last two decades has led many MS patients to a “cure” as their disease remains stable without attacks.</p>
<p>Looking ahead, the panel enthusiastically agreed about the possibilities precision or individualized medicine will have for patients with MS and their physicians. The ability to prescribe the right drug to the right patient at the right time in the disease course will treat MS with greater efficacy and lead to an increased quality of life beyond the current trial and error system. Individualized therapies will undoubtedly involve continuous follow-up with patients that monitoring devices and big data will likely play a role in. It is not uncommon for current patients with MS to schedule clinical visits every 6 to 12 months, and a great deal can change in their symptoms and care during that time. Sandrock, MD describes a future that will utilize technology similar to a Google Watch for patients to measure their daily symptoms and regimens and scan for lesions and brain shrinkage without full-blown MRI imaging — all while contributing to pivotal clinical trials. Lastly, the panel mentioned an emphasis on drug discovery to help prevent and treat the secondary-progressive disease course. Upcoming therapies may also rely on the microbiome or human gut for answers addressing the role of the immune system in MS.<br />
As Panzara concluded, the questions that we will ask and developments we will make in MS research and care over the next 5 years are unpredictable and will surprise us.</p>
<p><strong><em>The Century of the Molecule Becomes the Century of the System </em></strong></p>
<p>Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital surgeon, bestselling author, and healthcare thought leader Atul Gawande, MD gave a moving and thought-provoking talk on healthcare quality and healthcare costs from the 19th century until today. He discussed the great reduction in inpatient mortality at MGH from the 1950s to the 1990s. Then, Gawande noted that the relative lack of improvement from approximately 1990 coincided with a dramatic increase in the cost per patient. He used this trend to frame a conversation about increasing cost and complexity without improvements in quality. He subsequently discussed the extraordinary reductions in patient mortality in surgery that had been achieved around the world at very little cost with the introduction of a coordinated systems approach and simple checklists used before and after surgery.</p>
<p>Using personal anecdotes and experiences, he discussed his more recent work around death and dying. He explained that since the 1980s, the trend has been that most Americans are dying in institutions and often while undergoing dramatic interventions. He explained that this flies in the face of many people&#8217;s preference &#8212; when asked &#8211; -to die at home and/or without such dramatic and often painful curative or “life-saving” measures. He closed by discussing the systems, planning, and checklist efforts he was helping to develop and implement to improve the experience of death for people and their families &#8212; often simply by making sure that providers, patients, and family members simply take time to discuss the patients&#8217; preferences and priorities around death and dying.</p>
<p><strong><em>The Builder’s Roundtable: Perspectives of Public/Private Payer Architects</em></strong></p>
<p>In this session, Partners SVP Tim Ferris, MD moderated a lively and insightful discussion about healthcare costs, payers, and economics with Aetna CEO Mark Bertolini and Affordable Care Act architect Peter Orszag, PhD, who is a Citigroup senior executive and former Director of the United States Office of Management and Budget (OMB) and Director of the United States Congressional Budget Office (CBO).</p>
<p>During this conversation, Bertolini shared his own dramatic personal and family healthcare history, as well as his perspective that healthcare in the United States was on a &#8220;burning platform&#8221; and that the Affordable Care Act created the impetus for conversations that needed to happen. Both agreed that the fee-for-service models are unsustainable and do not incentivize quality or cost control. They also agreed that the Affordable Care Act and related reforms were helping to move the country toward a new model that would be predicated on outcomes and include some mechanism to align incentives to encourage providers, consumers, and other market actors to contain escalating healthcare costs.</p>
<p>While emphasizing that extraordinary challenges remained, both shared some concrete reasons for hope. Bertolini shared that a targeted pilot program that Aetna had run to prevent hospitalizations among heart failure patients had reduced hospital visits by approximately 49%. Orszag shared his perspective that the recently announced 2.8% unadjusted Medicare cost increase was a positive sign that it is indeed possible to control healthcare costs and also that the Affordable Care Act may be having its intended effect.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-medical-innovation-forum-day-3-recap/">World Medical Innovation Forum Day 3 Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Day 3 Disruptive Dozen Overview</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/day-3-disruptive-dozen-overview/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 14:58:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1510</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A powerful summary of many of the innovations discussed at the Forum the past 3 days, the “Disruptive Dozen” is more than just a registry of buzz words; this list represents the optimistic current state of neuroscience and one to look back on in years to come to see the progress made. 12. DIAGNOSING AND ... <a title="Day 3 Disruptive Dozen Overview" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/day-3-disruptive-dozen-overview/" aria-label="More on Day 3 Disruptive Dozen Overview">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/day-3-disruptive-dozen-overview/">Day 3 Disruptive Dozen Overview</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A powerful summary of many of the innovations discussed at the Forum the past 3 days, the “Disruptive Dozen” is more than just a registry of buzz words; this list represents the optimistic current state of neuroscience and one to look back on in years to come to see the progress made.</p>
<p><strong>12. DIAGNOSING AND TREATING NEURODEGENERATIVE DISEASES THROUGH THE MICROBIOME</strong><br />
For the first time, the gut microbiome is now being examined as a therapeutic target. The body’s largest immune system holds many clues to neurological health. For example, a high-fat diet increases the risk for depression and other psychiatric disorders. Changes in the microbiome in the imbalance of certain bacteria could affect microglial cells in the brain.</p>
<p><strong>11. NEUROIMAGING FOR NEURODEGENERATIVE AND PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS</strong><br />
With more advanced, high-gradient 7 tesla MRI, the possibilities for imaging are plentiful. In Alzheimer’s disease (AD), comparisons are being made between the brains of symptomatic patients and non-symptomatic. Depression and anxiety – both neurocircuitry disorders – are being mapped with higher resolution and understanding.</p>
<p><strong>10. IMMUNE CHECKPOINT INHIBITORS FOR BRAIN CANCER</strong><br />
Checkpoint inhibitors could potentially stop the progression of brain cancer in certain subsets of patients. In advanced metastatic melanoma, where cancer reaches the brain, inhibitors produce better responses. Induced immunity is gearing the body for a stronger attack against the tumor.</p>
<p><strong>9. HEALING THE BRAIN WITH NEUROMODULATION</strong><br />
“Electricity for healing” is proving to be a viable treatment for improving working memory, making people more alert, and positively affecting people with neurocircuitry disorders such as tremors, addiction, PTSD, etc. There are 350,000 people in the United States with these “brain pacemakers.”</p>
<p><strong>8. MOLECULAR INTERVENTION WITH MINIMALLY INVASIVE TECHNOLOGY</strong><br />
The heterogeneity of tumors is affecting our approaches of targeting them. Because not every tumor is the same and not even the cells of one act the same all of the time, delivery devices with the capability of turning on or off different tumor expressions are key.</p>
<p><strong>7. NEW ASPECTS OF GENE THERAPY</strong><br />
More than 10,000 diseases are caused by a single gene defect. The explosion in gene therapy will be in editing techniques and “resilience” genes that can make diseases milder.</p>
<p><strong>6. THE PROMISE OF BRAIN BIOMARKERS</strong><br />
Finding biomarkers is the key to advancing drug development. For example, in AD, biomarkers found in cerebral spinal fluid (CSF) and on images of the brain appear years before symptoms present.</p>
<p><strong>5. THE PROMISE OF FOCUSED ULTRASOUND</strong><br />
The brain hides behind the skull and the blood-brain barrier. To be able to target deep tissue without radiation or incision means less time spent in the operating room and a quicker recovery for patients than current procedures allow. Less energy would be needed for the procedure, and reversible entry into the blood-brain barrier could mean safer, repeat procedures if necessary.</p>
<p><strong>4. RAPID INTERVENTION FOR PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS</strong><br />
In acute settings, suicidal ideation is an emergency. Symptoms of psychiatric disorders need faster intervention to keep patients and the people around them safe. Anti-depressants can take up to weeks to have an effect and may not produce an effect in some people. Techniques such as anesthetics, inhalants, and electrotherapy could soon be more widely deployed in emergency rooms.</p>
<p><strong>3. SMART BRAIN PROSTHETICS</strong><br />
Imagine what a “closed-loop thermostat” in the brain could do for many neurological diseases. They could restore quality of life to the physically impaired by stroke. These small devices would be implanted into the brain to stave off disease as it arises with no side effects.</p>
<p><strong>2. STEM CELL THERAPY TO REPAIR AND REPLENISH THE BRAIN</strong><br />
Regenerative medicine is recreating cells that are deficient, diseased, or missing. The use of stem cells and cell-based therapies is still controversial and presents moral and ethical issues as well as regulatory hurdles. However, it is undeniable that the brain is incredibly “plastic” and boasts an elegant biofeedback system. To use cells to correct a dysfunction requires great specificity.</p>
<p><strong>1. EARLY DIAGNOSIS AND TREATMENT FOR ALZHEIMER’S DISEASE</strong><br />
Fourty-four million people worldwide suffer from clinical AD, and many more go undiagnosed. It is a global health concern at the forefront of neuroscience. Speeding up drug discovery, tau protein immunotherapy, a-beta reduction, and robust imaging are just four of many tactics being used in the journey to a cure.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/day-3-disruptive-dozen-overview/">Day 3 Disruptive Dozen Overview</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Day Two &#8211; Focus Group Wrap Ups</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/day-two-focus-group-wrap-ups/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 17:20:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1498</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>National Security Through Neurodevelopment: County Initiatives to Meet CNS Challenges Neurodegenerative and neuropsychiatric diseases threaten the United States and wide swaths of the globe. Alzheimer’s disease (AD), alone &#8212; where 120 million across the world may be affected by mid-century &#8212; may cost trillions of dollars. The economic burden on families and governments will be ... <a title="Day Two &#8211; Focus Group Wrap Ups" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/day-two-focus-group-wrap-ups/" aria-label="More on Day Two &#8211; Focus Group Wrap Ups">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/day-two-focus-group-wrap-ups/">Day Two &#8211; Focus Group Wrap Ups</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>National Security Through Neurodevelopment: County Initiatives to Meet CNS Challenges</strong><br />
Neurodegenerative and neuropsychiatric diseases threaten the United States and wide swaths of the globe. Alzheimer’s disease (AD), alone &#8212; where 120 million across the world may be affected by mid-century &#8212; may cost trillions of dollars. The economic burden on families and governments will be tremendous and could lead to a global economic crisis over the next generation.</p>
<p>The demographic trends are clear: In western society, we have added a third to our lifespan and have low birthrates. As a result, we face a tsunami as the populations across the globe age. Until recently, AD, was a fairly rare disease, with the risk being 1 in 8 at age 65, but rising sharply to 1 in 2 at age 85. AD will be a common occurrence more and more in the future, as it correlates well with age.</p>
<p>But governments across the world have been slow to recognize this. NIH funding for AD was approximately $600 million last year. By comparison, HIV/AIDS spending was over $3 billion. To invest now in basic research will save the estimated $1.2 trillion Americans will be spending per year to care for AD in only 20 years. David Cameron’s call for a global fight on AD during the 2013 meeting of the G8 is a start. The UK’s $100 million Dementia Discovery Fund is another effort to develop collaborations between the public, private and non-profit sectors.</p>
<p>To heighten the alarm and call to action, we ought to stop looking at this just as a disease process, but rather as an economic crisis. WHO has issued a report on the coming pandemic. But where are reports from the World Bank or IMF? We should re-think spending on health and medical research not as a cost but as an investment &#8212; just as we did on a global scale with HIV/AIDS.</p>
<p>Due to stigma, there’s no public voice for mental illness as there is for other diseases. And for mental illness, the funding situation is even more critical. NIH spends far less on mental illness than other neurological conditions. Pharma is still investing in neuro, but it is getting out of R&amp;D and drug discovery for psychiatry. This will obviously reduce the number of therapies in clinical trials and will drastically reduce the pipeline of young scientists entering the field.</p>
<p>Perhaps a paradigm shift in our thinking will help: AD is not as a disease of 80-year olds; it is a disease in its early stages of people in their 40s and 50s. Collaboration and leadership are needed from the political, corporate and NGO sectors to capitalize on this realization. After all, our collective cognitive health will equal our economic wealth.</p>
<p><strong>Technology, Pathology, Radiology: Changing the Game through Neurodiagnostics </strong><br />
The promise in imaging lies in being able to detect disease through multiple modalities and thus, diagnose sooner and more accurately. In the past, neurological diseases were studied post-mortem, and we depended on lesions to show function and structural correlation. The shift has moved from first a gross level, then a cellular level, and now a molecular level – finding out which genes and proteins are altered to cause inflammation and tissue damage. Becoming more “micro” and using data analytics will be continuing trends. Today’s imagers and pathologists are excited about possibilities in wearable MR, and radioomics. The recent changes in WHO classification of brain tumors to add molecular properties shows the global shift of diagnostics towards a more personalized approach. Our techniques are getting smaller and data is getting bigger – a promising combination.</p>
<p><strong>Autism and Neurodevelopment: Are Therapies Possible Today?</strong><br />
This session, moderated by Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist and author, and Director of the Project on Public Narrative at Harvard University, Ron Suskind, explained that, 20 years ago, his own son was diagnosed with autism, at a time when not much was known of this “Rainman” affliction. The diagnosis of autism has exponentially increased and is now largely a public health issue.</p>
<p>The panel focused on the hurdles the speakers collectively face studying autism. The majority, about 25% of severe autism disorders, does not have an obvious genetic defect. In fact, there may not be a relationship between what is seen clinically and genetically in autism. It was said that in autism, there are no treatments; therefore small improvements can be revolutionary. Measurements of outcomes in drug developments in autism research are also quite complex. Parent warriors are often scientists who were touched by autism in a personal way, as is directly seen on this panel. Social media has made broad-reaching clinical trials possible, connecting with other parent warriors from far and afield. Crowd source funding is also utilized.</p>
<p>A collective goal amongst the panelists is to better understand the molecular defect(s) of autism, and to determine a way to objectively measure outcomes of experimental treatment. One panelist offers the possibility to discover treatable idiopathic subtypes of autism. Perhaps inflammation plays a causal role in some subtypes of autism that can be targeted with effective therapies. Collectively grappling with the impressive and challenging future of autism research, it does not seem that any of these panelists are capable of limiting themselves in their pursuit to define, treat and end this disease. In the end, the moderator, Ron Suskind, Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist and author and Director of the Project on Public Narrative at Harvard University, also rallied for the societal inclusion of those already autism-afflicted, highlighting the strengths or passions of differently-abled people, while seeking creative adaptations and treatments to enhance their quality of life.</p>
<p><strong>Pyschiatric Targets: Finally New Mechanisms</strong><br />
Today, most of us know – either as family members, friends or work associates – people who suffer from some form of psychiatric disease. Yet, the delivery of care and the corresponding investment in research, infrastructure, and medical support suffer from a disproportionate lack of resources, compared to other targeted health programs such as cancer. As was noted in the earlier session on neurostimulation, venture capital investment for psychiatric diseases is less than 10% of the cancer investment. Maurizio Fava, M.D., Executive Vice Chair, MGH Psychiatry and Slater Family Professor of Psychiatry at Harvard Medical School, added that the drug therapies available today (mostly monoamines) have been available for years, and very few new drugs have made it to Phase 3 trials. Other participants contributed their analyses about why the industry has not championed new therapies.</p>
<p>Deborah Dunsire, M.D., as CEO of FORUM Pharmaceuticals, stated “Show me the target.” Her assessment of the industry is that the therapies and outcomes lack the tools to successfully predict the risk of the investment. Fava commented that the placebo effect resulted in a number of Phase 3 trials being abandoned.<br />
One theme was the need for better biological markers that can be used in providing more accurate and actionable diagnoses. David Silbersweig, Chairman, Psychiatry at BWH and Stanley Cobb Professor of Psychiatry at Harvard Medical School, in his opening comments, referred to the difficulty of working with patients where many of the symptoms are self-reported. He also pointed out how recent research has identified the high level of interaction between the executive functions and the limbic system – which makes some of the traditional categories less useful. Instead, he emphasized that new methods have explored the role of the environment along with current therapies. Part of this discussion was also the need for better metrics for outcomes.</p>
<p>Another theme was the emerging use of CBT (cognitive behavioral therapies). Corey McCann, M.D., Ph.D., Founder and CEO, Pear Therapeutics, discussed the approach his company has taken in merging software-based CBT technology with various drug therapies. The panel discussed the application of CBT to post traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) and the underlying mechanisms that deal with fear circuitry. CBT – using contemporary game technology – allows the patient to work through his or her fear experience so that the narrative can be selectively disassociated from the emotional response. PTSD has gained a lot of recent attention in the industry, partly because of the need to treat the veteran population. McCann stated that studies have shown that CBT plus an antidepressant have treated depression better than either one alone. It also has the benefit of working with several existing drugs, and it can be deployed for new indications without some of the overhead currently associated with FDA approval of new drugs.<br />
Other topics covered included addiction, active and passive monitoring using cell phone technology, and imaging. The panel was generally upbeat about the future.</p>
<p><strong>Sleep and Consciousness: Clinical Need Versus Safety</strong><br />
Sleep serves as the bedrock of good health. And poor sleep, either in duration, quality or continuity, may have significant negative implications for overall health.</p>
<p>While we sleep, parts of our brain are quite active. Deep, slow-wave sleep at the beginning of a sleep cycle helps to consolidate memory, while REM stage sleep that occurs much later in the sleep cycle helps us integrate what we have learned. REM sleep assists with the development of insight and understanding. And when we are asleep, the brain’s own drainage system removes harmful metabolites like amyloid beta.</p>
<p>A number of factors get in the way of sleep. Many of us are over-caffeinated and spend too much time in front of TV and other device screens. The light emitted by these devices interferes with the normal role of melatonin and delays the onset of sleep. Millions of others, many unaware, suffer from interrupted breathing during sleep – sleep apnea. Still others face chronic disorders of insomnia and narcolepsy. Chronic pain and psychiatric illnesses can also disrupt sleep.</p>
<p>Research is needed to identify biomarkers so that personalized therapies can be developed. Intensive effort and significant resources will be needed to see if it is possible to come up with a blood test to indicate who among us is at greater risk for a given sleep disorder. It was once thought that all sleep apnea, for example, was the same. Research has shown there to be a number of subtypes. Continued work to indentify subtypes will help develop more effective therapies.</p>
<p>Many of the wearable computing devices like Fitbit and sleep monitors are generating great interest. As more and more individuals are collecting data, including on sleep habits, patterns are emerging. This data may also be used for diagnostic and treatment purposes. However, these devices are early prototypes and as such, can produce erroneous data or even be “tricked” into producing false results. As they become more sophisticated, they may be able to offer more insight into sleep and other health indicators.</p>
<p>Exciting new areas to be explored include the genetics of sleep pathology. This coincides with the groundswell of interest in personalized medicine.</p>
<p><strong>Parkinson’s: Finally Crossing the Therapeutic Threshold</strong><br />
The first part of this panel focused on the need for better biological markers which would result in enhanced diagnostic capability, and the second part dived into current therapies for Parkinson’s disease. Michael Schwarzchild, M.D. Ph.D., Chair, Parkinson Study Group Executive Committee at MassGeneral Institute for Neurodegenerative Disease, and Professor Neurology, Harvard Medical School, opened the session by providing an overview of what Parkinson’s is and its prevalence in the population (second most common disease behind Alzheimer’s). He also reviewed some of the recent findings, particularly in the emergence of some of the genetic clues and their complex interactions with environmental factors. New insights have been gained on the progress of the disease and early diagnosis. He stressed that the most typical symptom of Parkinson’s – tremors and other motor disorders – is not necessarily the first manifestation of the disease (for example, sleep disorders, depression, etc.) As he remarked later in the session, there is still no unifying hypothesis for Parkinson’s.<br />
The difficulty in identifying biomarkers was complicated by the effect of patients already in treatment. Some studies have taken 10 years and have been very costly. Clemens Scherzer, M.D., Director, Neurogenomics Lab and Parkinson Personalized Medicine Program, Brigham and Women’s Hospital/Massachusetts General Hospital, and Associate Professor of Neurology, Harvard Medical School, described the collaborative approach his team has taken at Harvard and the positive results they have achieved. Results are now measured in weeks rather than years. Todd Sherer, CEO of the Michael J. Fox Foundation, also championed collaborative research and described some successful programs they have run. So far, the strongest markers have been genetic.</p>
<p>Current therapies seem to be centered on the continued use of dopamine-based strategies. Scherzer noted that of 35 recent trials, only a handful include disease-modifying drugs. The improvements are more focused on better delivery mechanisms, so that a patient can gain relief in a matter of minutes rather than in 30 to 40 minutes (based on inhalationm versus oral intake). More work is also being done on integrating non-motor symptoms into the treatment portfolio.</p>
<p><strong>New Leaders at the Table: Filling the Gap Through Philanthropy</strong><br />
Henry McCance, dynamic speaker and Co-Founder of Cure Alzheimer’s Fund eloquently defined this nonprofit organization, founded in 2004, by several families who were frustrated by the slow pace of research. This fund is a new venture-based entity created to speed research and exclusively focus on finding a cure, leveraging successful returns that de-risk research and thus become more attractive to public funding sources.<br />
Meryl Comer, President of the Geoffrey Beene Foundation’s Alzheimer’s Initiative, spoke of her role as long-term caregiver of her afflicted husband and her realization that she needed to turn the suffering into purpose. Comer spoke of actively changing the direction and pace of medical research, by mining public databases, or “big data,” and not focusing on reinventing the wheel, as well as utilizing collaborative technologies to help foster data collection and analysis. The Initiative has generated more than $4.8 million so far, in support of awareness programs and early diagnostic and treatment research.</p>
<p>Nancy Frates, mother of Pete Frates, described how their family enveloped themselves in philanthropic relationships that banded together to amplify funding for ALS research. A fellow ALS sufferer came across the Ice Bucket Challenge and brought it to Pete’s attention, and the Frates family quickly and efficiently used social media to use the Challenge to spread the word, as well as to raise the funds to be proactive and accelerate ALS research.<br />
CEO of Forma Therapeutics, Steven Tregay, spoke of how Forma is helping to transform the drug discovery process through collaborations in pharma.</p>
<p>Jeff Walker, Vice Chair, United Nations Envoy Office of Health and Finance and Malaria, shared that he just lost his father t Alzheimer’s last Friday. He spoke of pointing out to investors that their investment “return” is invaluable.<br />
Bill Sahlman, Senior Associate Dean of Harvard Business School, brilliantly defines the biggest “data dumps: on everyone’s hips, the cell phone. The importance of gathering information on a big scale is very important, and cell phones are ideally placed for this purpose. He does not feel that privacy concerns should get in the way of utilizing these ubiquitous tools for research purposes.</p>
<p>The takeaway message of this panel was that in an age where we are living longer lives, it may be that it’s not if you get Alzheimer’s, it’s when, and we should all be active investors in its prevention, treatment and cure.</p>
<p>Posted by Jim Coburn, Christine Dyer-Ward, John Hannigan and Fares Nigim</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/day-two-focus-group-wrap-ups/">Day Two &#8211; Focus Group Wrap Ups</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Forum – Day 2 Recap</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-forum-day-2-recap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 14:39:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1497</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The second day of the World Medical Innovation Forum continued to build momentum on the Forum’s mission — providing a venue for imperative conversation among academic, private, government and patient/consumer communities. The agenda set forth today brought together stakeholders across disciplines — patients living with neurologic conditions and leaders in academic medical research, private biotechnology, ... <a title="World Forum – Day 2 Recap" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-forum-day-2-recap/" aria-label="More on World Forum – Day 2 Recap">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-forum-day-2-recap/">World Forum – Day 2 Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The second day of the World Medical Innovation Forum continued to build momentum on the Forum’s mission — providing a venue for imperative conversation among academic, private, government and patient/consumer communities. The agenda set forth today brought together stakeholders across disciplines — patients living with neurologic conditions and leaders in academic medical research, private biotechnology, and government. The one-on-one panel format paved the way for candid insight into where the field of neurosciences has been for the past 30 years and where it is heading, at an accelerated pace, via collaboration and conversation.</p>
<p><strong><em>Clinical Demonstrations </em></strong><br />
The first session started early and strong with demonstrations from two of neuroscience medicine’s most promising tools, the AMIGO Suite and NeuroSwitch. The AMIGO Suite is a $20 million multi-modality operating room pioneered at the Brigham and Women’s Hospital (BWH). This robust theater is intraoperative imaging at its best, the concept first conceived at BWH in the 1990s. It is equipped with CT, MR, fluoroscopy, among others, and the world’s only intraoperative PET/CT scan. Suites featuring intraoperative imaging are now adopted widely across the United States and the world.</p>
<p>The goal of these suites is to make surgery safer by assisting surgeons in distinguishing normal versus cancerous tissue. This guidance, along with superior imaging technique, allows neurosurgeons to contour a mass with unprecedented approximation and aids in real-time clinical decision-making. Suites like AMIGO are multi-specialty and can be applied to systems other than the brain and therefore, engage a wide array of the clinical community. Transforming a maximally invasive procedure into a minimally invasive one and being able to operate on a formerly inoperable patient are the underlying incentives for using such suites.</p>
<p>What are brain surgeons currently excited about? More precision for better outcomes. Metabolite-guided surgery through mass spectroscopy, delivery of drugs into the central nervous system (CNS), and laser hyperthermia to destroy tumors. The AMIGO Suite is able to use any type of instrument, metallic or not. A versatile OR is a vehicle of the future, and the world’s eyes are on BWH and the AMIGO suite.</p>
<p>NeuroSwitch is unlike the typical communication aids available on the market. It gets past the physical interface (buttons, keyboards, clickers) and uses movements and EEG data to control a computer device. Patients with locked-in syndrome (LIS), most commonly found in ALS, are able to use NeuroSwitch to regain control of their self-expression. The market size is growing – 35,000 patients suffer from ALS in the United States, with 5,000 new diagnoses annually. The ability for patients to communicate with not only their loved ones, but also with the world online is paramount for them. Patients who use NeuroSwitch gave live demonstrations, raving about NeuroSwitch and how it allows them to keep their passions, like book blogging or 3D printing, alive. When motor control diminishes, sophisticated, hands-free communication aids are mandatory. With features like the ones NeuroSwitch boasts, patients are able to stay connected with their families and communities.</p>
<p><strong><em>Patient One-on-One</em></strong></p>
<p><strong><em><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6858-SM.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1499" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6858-SM-300x200.jpg" alt="Ann Romney" width="300" height="200" /></a><br />
</em></strong>Serving as the official launch of the Ann Romney Center for Neurological Diseases at BWH, Ann Romney spoke to Forum attendees about her personal journey with multiple sclerosis (MS). She was diagnosed in 1998 and expressed how fortunate she was to have received early and aggressive treatment at BWH. She is now currently in remission and on no medication, a state of health not realized by many other patients who suffer from neurologic disease worldwide. She maintains her stellar health by rigorous fitness regimens and diets, as well as a spiritual and mental wellbeing that is fostered by her passion for horseback riding. She credits both physicians at BWH and her dedicated supporters who were there for her on the campaign trail during her husband’s past presidential bid.</p>
<p>The Ann Romney Center for Neurological Diseases will support research and innovation in MS, Alzheimer’s disease (AD), Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS), Parkinson’s Disease, and brain tumors. She hopes that this horizontal model will instigate interdisciplinary collaboration. The overlap in many neurological illnesses calls for a different approach and to break down the silos of disease cures and therapy research and development efforts. There is power in numbers, and she encourages all who are affected by neurological disease to join her new social media campaign by using the hash tag, #50MillionFaces, on Twitter.</p>
<p><strong><em>The Alzheimer’s Phoenix: New Technologies, New Economics<br />
</em></strong>This panel of esteemed and diverse AD experts shed light on the current theories of disease causes and what to expect on the journey to a cure. All were very optimistic and agreed that we are close to disease-modifying therapies that could be marketable as soon as five years from now. It has taken decades to validate the two-tiered pathology of AD in amyloid-beta (a-beta) and tau protein aggregation. The future lies in combining these theories into parallel therapies to enhance clinical effect. Base inhibitors have been found to be very promising and are currently the most competitive targets in the industry. When given to compliant patients for a year, a-beta was eliminated almost entirely. This is the epitome of reverse translational medicine – aiding the immune system in recognizing these destructive protein aggregates.</p>
<p>As the underlying causes of AD become clearer, early and personalized treatment for patients has become more realistic. In the autopsies of people who died of suspected AD, almost 1/3 of their brains were seen to be damaged. According to the speakers, clinicians must realize that AD is malicious organ failure that starts decades before being symptomatic, if at all. The heterogeneity of the population with AD in years to come will help evolve treatment. It will not be long before we are treating AD patients based on their own specific symptoms and biology. Today’s speakers advised that clinicians need to start utilizing a risk-assessment profile to plan beyond the long prodromal period and optimistically provide a risk “score” as early as age 40.</p>
<p>Where are there room for improvements in AD care? There has to be greater coordination among payers to coordinate cost-effectiveness. The late-stage AD patient requires 24-hour care, multiple caregivers, and an extensive clinical team. The advances to come will hopefully allow patients to maintain more independence and a greater quality of life and have care at an as-needed basis. Investigators need to focus their efforts on finding the right genes and biomarkers for drug development. Non-pharmacological interventions should be integrated into care and be viewed just as importantly as drugs. Poor diet and scarce exercise cannot be compensated for by better drugs. The stratification of AD patients as at-risk, non-symptomatic, early-stage, or late-stage, require individualized care and treatment.</p>
<p><strong><em>Regeneration, Cell Therapy, and Neurocare: Products? Delivery?<br />
</em></strong>Regenerative medicine is recreating cells that are deficient, diseased, or missing. The use of stem cells and cell-based therapies is still controversial and presents moral and ethical issues as well as regulatory hurdles. However, it is undeniable that the brain is incredibly “plastic” and boasts an elegant biofeedback system. To use cells to correct a dysfunction requires great specificity. Cell-based therapies have the potential to be applied across disciplines in spinal cord injury, diabetes, and blood dyscrasias. In spinal cord injury, “cross-correction” can produce enough of a missing enzyme in defective neurons for them to remain viable. Diabetics can be unleashed from a life support of administered insulin with the replacement of defunct beta cells in the pancreas. In inherited disorders like sickle cell anemia and thalassemia, gene editing can reprogram cells to be embryonic, enabling patients to essentially “get their cells back.” The targeted diseases for stem cell research are typically ones that have no treatments; any work in this field, therefore, will address a large unmet need.</p>
<p>There are two types of cells used in regenerative therapies: embryonic, or immature cells derived from embryos, and “adult” cells that come from a formed organ. Embryonic cells can potentially produce any cell type in the body – providing a wealth of possibility yet also result in the chance of tumorgenecity, or the primitive cell developing into a tumor. There are ways to address this by pre-determining cells or turning on “suicide genes” to kill the cell once it starts to express tumorgenecity. This controversial technique has the potential to save tens of thousands of lives but will not be adapted into practice if headway cannot be made by industry and academia, together, in addressing the treatment risks.</p>
<p><strong><em>CEO One-on-One Sessions</em></strong></p>
<p><strong><em><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7115.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1500" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7115-300x200.jpg" alt="Robert Bradway" width="300" height="200" /></a><br />
</em></strong>The personal one-on-one accounts continued throughout the day with candid conversations between leaders in the private biotechnology industry and government. Robert Bradway, CEO of Amgen, and George Scangos, Ph.D., CEO of Biogen, reflected on the challenges and successes to date in identifying and producing novel therapies for devastating neurologic diseases.</p>
<p>Bradway said that Amgen is a leader in drug development across various diseases like chronic kidney disease, cardiovascular disease, inflammation, and the company is increasingly interested in getting more involved in the neurosciences. Some drugs in their current pipeline are early-stage treatments for schizophrenia, AD, and chronic pain. Amgen is currently active in genetics, and Bradway sees a sustaining trend in favoring genetics for informing drug development.</p>
<p>Bradway discussed Amgen’s acquisition of Decode Genetics at length, emphasizing the imperative role collaboration plays in translational research—an interdisciplinary research style that is currently guiding the industry. Bradway noted there has been recent feverish collaboration as government withdraws more funding for basic research. We are seeing this withdrawal because of a decades-long steady monetary decline. More investment in genetics can reverse this by quickening the drug development process and making it more efficacious. Per Bradway’s account, Amgen is looking ahead to identify and develop therapies based on the genetic and molecular understanding of a disease and its pathway. As industry at large is seen further reducing its commitment to discovery research, Amgen proclaims it is not shrinking back.</p>
<p>Scangos’ account provided insider details into Biogen’s past and current Phase 2 and 3 trials for ALS, MS and AD therapies. Scangos praised the role academic collaborations have had in driving the talent, direction, and mission of successful biotechnology research and development. Scangos also shed light on Biogen’s biggest concern for the next half decade—the current environmental context that medical research operates in. Thoughtful public policy will be necessary to fulfill the potential of this pivotal time in medical history—with aligned talent, resources, and a greater understanding of neurologic diseases than ever before.</p>
<p><strong><em>Secretary One-on-One</em></strong></p>
<p><em><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7296.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1501" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7296-300x200.jpg" alt="Sylvia Mathews Burwell" width="300" height="200" /></a><br />
</em>The one-on-one conversation with Honorable Sylvia Matthews Burwell, Secretary of the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, echoed Scangos’ glimpse into the importance of public policy. Secretary Burwell emphasized the similar priorities all entities hold—affordable, accessible, life-changing therapies for patients. By changing health care pay systems, implementing integrated care systems, and moving forward with data collection, analytics, and protection, the Department of Health and Human Services is optimistic about the next phases of neuroscience care and beyond.</p>
<p><em><strong>Neurostimulation: First Line Therapy?</strong></em><br />
What is neuromodulation and why does it work? Neuromodulation is the use of various kinds of electric signals to restore the brain to a more normal state. It is a broad and emerging field; we are on the verge of a revolution with treating diseases such a Parkinson&#8217;s, epilepsy and OCD. This type of treatment has been around for decades but has recently re-emerged through new findings in neuroscience research.</p>
<p>Speakers said that in the past, neuromodulation treatments worked, but nobody knew why. Although the field is much more developed now, patients are still hesitant to embrace this technology due to its highly invasive nature. Panelists mentioned that up to 15 percent of Parkinson’s patients receive these implants, but there still needs to be additional education and a shift in mindset in order for this type of treatment to be more widely adopted – a challenge that may be overcome with time. ​</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-forum-day-2-recap/">World Forum – Day 2 Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Forum &#8211; Day 1 Recap</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-forum-day-1-recap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2015 13:50:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1484</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Partners HealthCare kicked off its inaugural World Medical Innovation Forum in Boston on April 27 with a truly international presence, bringing together over 1,000 attendees from 18 countries to discuss and advance the state of neuroscience research, patient care, and delivery. The first day of this three-day event also highlighted the role of collaboration and ... <a title="World Forum &#8211; Day 1 Recap" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-forum-day-1-recap/" aria-label="More on World Forum &#8211; Day 1 Recap">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-forum-day-1-recap/">World Forum &#8211; Day 1 Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Partners HealthCare kicked off its inaugural World Medical Innovation Forum in Boston on April 27 with a truly international presence, bringing together over 1,000 attendees from 18 countries to discuss and advance the state of neuroscience research, patient care, and delivery. The first day of this three-day event also highlighted the role of collaboration and partnering across stakeholders in venture capital, academia, life sciences, and health care to ensure financial sustainability amidst increasing cost pressures and constraints in funding.</p>
<p>Neurological diseases are particularly prominent and represent a huge, unaddressed disease burden across global societies, and today’s panels provided a multifaceted view of the current state of care for neurological diseases, accompanied by bold proposals for what the future setting of neurocare will entail.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Discovery Cafe, Welcome</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6249.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1487" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6249-300x200.jpg" alt="Discovery Cafe - 1" width="300" height="200" /></a></p>
<p>The day kicked off on when attendees gathered over lunch for a roundtable discussion on a specific topic, moderated by a champion in that field, called the Discovery Cafe. Topics ranged from psychiatric care to information systems and how they all can contribute to innovation in the neurosciences. Rich, interdisciplinary discussion flowed among clinicians, industry experts, policymakers, and researchers. The Discovery Cafe provided a platform to transform mingling and networking into purposeful interaction between fellow attendees.</p>
<p><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6396.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1488" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6396-300x200.jpg" alt="Welcome - 1" width="300" height="200" /></a></p>
<p>Attendees were officially ushered into their upcoming three days of neurological innovation by CEO of Partners HealthCare, David Torchiana, M.D., and Chief Academic Officer of Partners HealthCare, Anne Klibanski, M.D., as well as by Boston Mayor Marty Walsh. A significant fraction of Partners HealthCare’s $1.5 billion enterprise is work in the neurosciences. The audience was called to action to push the frontiers of medicine against the backdrop of world-renowned facilities, scientists, and clinicians that is Boston.</p>
<p><strong>Neurocare, Neuromarkets, and Neuro Challenges </strong><br />
The day’s first panel, “Neurocare, Neuromarkets, and Neuro Challenges,” cited early detection and prophylactic care as key needs across Alzheimer’s and psychiatric care. Scott Rauch, President and Psychiatrist in Chief at McLean Hospital, stated it’s the rule rather than the exception that patients are suffering from psychiatric diseases for years before they are detected. These observations, however, were tempered amidst real-world reservations from patients, who may not want to know about genetic predispositions or had privacy concerns amidst proposals for earlier screening and detection.</p>
<p>Clinical neuroscience leaders across Partners HealthCare were called to dive into the past, present, and future of diseases such as Alzheimer’s disease (AD) to share how far we have come in the field and how very much there is still left to discover. A common thread throughout was that stigma is stalling. The medicalization of psychiatric illnesses has been a remarkable jump forward &#8211; clinicians are now viewing bipolar disorder, schizophrenia, etc., as diseases with an originating pathology like how we view hypertension or diabetes. We are now seeing the beginning of stigma erosion in public figures and celebrities stepping forward to advocate for these illnesses.</p>
<p>With this new clinical perspective comes the challenge of screening. When will AD be uniformly screened, like colon cancer? To reach patients at the primary care level is key to early intervention. It is widely understood now that changes in the brain due to AD occur decades before symptoms first appear. Engaging at-risk patients earlier and understanding how inflammation in the immune system contributes to its spread will be of note in the future of AD care.</p>
<p>In neurosurgery, advances are more technical but no less exciting. There is more precision than ever before in imaging and in the miniaturization of instruments. Gels and focused ultrasounds are able to cross the blood-brain barrier and deliver the appropriate amount of drugs to a specific location in the brain. These advances contribute to the minimization of collateral brain damage during surgery. As neurosurgery becomes safer and more seamless, we will see patients with better outcomes.</p>
<p>Not only are we able to enter the brain with newfound surgical specificity, but we are also now at the advent of specificity in neurogenetics. The future of neurocare will be linking outcomes and treatments to the genotypes of patients. Researchers are beginning to acknowledge the overlap that many of these neurodegenerative diseases share in similar genetic predispositions. This can be translated into clinical trial design by finding out how successful patients are different genetically and then designing the next trial based on that data. Lowering the burden of becoming involved in clinical trials is key to the advancement of research. Another challenge to neurocare is how to expand access to treatment. Telemedicine plays a big role with programs such as cognitive behavioral therapy being available online. Our personal devices like phones and tablets hold the answer to remote monitoring. It is how we contextualize this deluge of “big data” that will shape the trajectory of the neuromarket in upcoming years.</p>
<p><strong>“Over the Horizon: Witnessing Disruption of Neurocare”</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6594.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1489" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6594-300x200.jpg" alt="Over the Horizon - 1" width="300" height="200" /></a><br />
The day’s second panel, “Over the Horizon: Witnessing the Disruption of Neurocare,” generated bold predictions across industry and public research organizations, proposing an array of traditional therapeutics, electroceutical, brain-machine interface approaches to treat human disease and augment lifestyles, even repositioning the nervous system as the vehicle to deliver and refine treatment for patients. As Geoffrey Ling, Director of Biological Technologies Office at DARPA pointed out, experiments highlighting cognitive control of prosthetic limbs point to a potential applications that could surpass the limits of our sensory organs and other exogenous tools to improve patient cognition and lifestyles, especially in states of frailty observed later in life.</p>
<p>This provocative panel leapt into novel ideas that the panelists believe are just at the cusp of neurological innovation. These neuro-forecasters pooled their collective knowledge from biotechnology and big pharma to present the most cutting-edge and controversial of work. The audience was advised to abandon any preconceived notions on how innovation works, citing that humans did not know that cell phones would be so ingrained into our lifestyle a decade ago. Panelists pushed that in the future of the patient-empowered age, everyone will be sequencing their genome, even from birth. The best drugs will then be gene-modifiers, and the concept of a “drug” could completely vanish as combined strategies make their way into therapeutics and care plans. Clinicians will soon be prescribing drugs with apps or drugs with software. The concept of a “dose” will change as we add different interfaces into neurocare.</p>
<p>One of these novel “neural interfaces” is the concept of “electroceuticals,” or devices that deliver electrical stimulation at the level of peripheral nerves. These exquisitely specific devices will be smaller than a grain of rice and allow us to control our neurocircuitry. It is up to investigators of the future to map the neurocircuitry of diseases. The concept that the central nervous system is synergistic with pathology throughout the body is one that may be difficult for clinicians to adapt to. For example, it is clear that diabetes is a metabolic disorder but how clear is it that it is a neurological one? Imagine the possibility of treating an illness with “information” in addition to drugs.</p>
<p>Artificial intelligence (AI) may be characteristic of science fiction movies, but is nothing to fear, but rather embrace. The Stone Age and Iron Age were eras of tool adaptation, and so the expected path is that the Digital Age will move onto AI as we “adapt” to the synergy of brain and machine. By doing this, we are “liberating our bodies” and allowing our cognitive capacity to accomplish more. Our future lies in the “Internet of things,” or rather than having exogenous control in the form of cellphones, tablets, etc., we will have internal cognitive control over our environment. This is not a new concept; brain-controlled prosthetics are allowing amputees to control limbs. Phones and computers may be a thing of the past one day, and “smart” environments will take their place.</p>
<p>Along with enhancing our environments, enhancing the normal human condition is pushing the frontiers of medicine. Becoming bionic may mean unprecedented longevity for today’s youth. To achieve this. we must understand what is the “average” condition and why is it that we age and become ill. Have our genes not adapted to today’s environment and lifestyle? If so, perhaps we can identify those genes that cause disease and aging and “turn them off.” Ethical issues will be an obstacle to many of these radical ideas and must be addressed before becoming mainstream.</p>
<p>So, what must happen in order for these concepts to be implemented in the clinical setting? Building the technological platforms and understanding the revolutionary biology must happen simultaneously. Industry stakeholders have to own this work in order for it to make it into practice. As the population grows older, public pressure mounts with the heavy societal burdens of neurological disease.</p>
<p>For both the research and innovation communities, key challenges and questions arise: Why is therapeutic development usually a second career? Why is it not viewed more urgently in the minds of clinicians? What barriers are holding them back from tapping into this rich field? For innovators trying to propel disruptive interventions like electroceuticals into the care space, what will it take for consumers and patients to choose devices over drugs? IUDs and implants prove to be the most effective contraceptive method, yet pills are the most widely preferred method today. Will the idea of “invasiveness” change over time as the body interacts more with technology?</p>
<p>Only time can answer these pressing questions on the minds of today’s innovators and researchers. Biology is becoming more of a quantitative science. “Coding” our nerves and gene editing has the potential to become a universal standard of treatment. “Cognitive resilience,” or the fielding of symptoms of AD, for example, can become a reality and greatly impact the quality of life of patients. At the intersection of therapeutics and technology lie a wealth of knowledge that we do not yet know how to harvest.</p>
<p><strong>Transformation and Innovation: Conflict? Collision? Opportunity?</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6603.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1490" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6603-300x200.jpg" alt="Transformation and Innovation - 1" width="300" height="200" /></a><br />
Chief Executives from provider, pharmaceutical, and medical device stakeholders took the floor to highlight stakeholder considerations, opportunities, and needs in the face of a decrease in inflation adjusted NIH funding and population health burdens. As Jeff Leiden, M.D., Ph.D., CEO of Vertex, noted, the irony is that the science has never been better, but the funding has never been worse.</p>
<p>While undertones in funding and an increasingly difficult operating environment where apparent throughout the day, the panelists shared a universal optimism for the current state of medicine and an excitement in the potential advances to come, often pointing to current market forces as motivators for improvements in treatment and care. As Leiden noted, the health care community has a great story to tell when it comes to the value and impact that the system brings to society; we just need to focus on communicating that story to the public.</p>
<p>Posted by Angelica Recierdo, Thomas Martz, and Alessandra Maahs</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/world-forum-day-1-recap/">World Forum &#8211; Day 1 Recap</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reflections on Day 1 of the World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/reflections-on-day-1-of-the-world-medical-innovation-forum/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2015 12:39:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1482</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The almost $700 billion annual spend in neurodegenerative diseases tells a story of a global community struck by an array of stubborn neurological conditions and challenged by drug discovery, delivery, care, regulatory protocols, and economic and organizational practices serving at cross-purposes. Yet, there was something inspirational and I dare say hopeful about the presenters’ opinions ... <a title="Reflections on Day 1 of the World Medical Innovation Forum" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/reflections-on-day-1-of-the-world-medical-innovation-forum/" aria-label="More on Reflections on Day 1 of the World Medical Innovation Forum">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/reflections-on-day-1-of-the-world-medical-innovation-forum/">Reflections on Day 1 of the World Medical Innovation Forum</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6515.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-1491 size-medium" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6515-300x200.jpg" alt="Neurocare - 1" width="300" height="200" /></a></p>
<p>The almost $700 billion annual spend in neurodegenerative diseases tells a story of a global community struck by an array of stubborn neurological conditions and challenged by drug discovery, delivery, care, regulatory protocols, and economic and organizational practices serving at cross-purposes. Yet, there was something inspirational and I dare say hopeful about the presenters’ opinions of what’s to come.</p>
<p>Technology, transparency, and passion appeared central to the secret sauce. Much was stated about the power of smart devices allowing the organic evolution of large data sets to evolve and yield insight and action in a scalable fashion not seen till now.</p>
<p>Second, transparency, or specifically data and process transparency, appeared thematic as another dimension supporting progress. That is, having enhanced access and data deployment through analytics, machine interfaces, and control mechanisms further influenced interventions. This may, in cases, lead to more precise mapping, stimulating, manipulating, and modulating of circuits, genes, and varied organs in a more predictive, synergistic fashion &#8212; yielding greater value and utility.</p>
<p>Additionally, the collective process and arrangement of organized inquiry, aggregation, experimentation, and delivery may interestingly be compared to a very different but similarly transparent process.</p>
<p>In the food and beverage industry, the fast-casual restaurant segment is very popular. Chipotle Restaurant, the leader in this segment, allows diners to self-select and view the assembling of an array of diverse ingredients for a given order. The interaction effects of the employee and customer publicly engaging in the co-design and build effort yields more satisfaction, efficiency, and taste with both creator and consumer, as noted in the restaurant surveys. Similarly, in health care research, such increased process transparency is no less immaterial in the discovery-delivery value chain.</p>
<p>Third, it seems the very human quality of passion and / or emotion, can also play an out-sized role in the direction and dynamics of next gen neuroscience. Many stories about the fear surrounding Alzheimer’s is self-evident here. As described, we have all heard of some version of the hapless wonderer in the parking lot seeking their car, keys or both, much to one’s frustration. This example, perhaps associated with Alzheimer’s, can easily and obviously be substituted with other neurodegenerative diseases, as well.</p>
<p>On the hopeful side, passion was referenced as a motivator that has led to an activist public seeking answers. Their intent has further engaged some to experiment in varied ways that on occasion has yielded surprising, timely, and consequential data.</p>
<p>While there is much to hope for, there are equally many daunting challenges requiring attention. Certainly, as always, understanding the fundamental root causes, relationships, pathways, and protocols of the disease state is central. However, just as daunting on a more macro-level is the institutional – organizational arrangement in moving beyond silos to varied operating forms of collaboration, coordination, “co-opitition,” and disruption.</p>
<p>The clarion call for innovation at a cellular or genomic level can also be matched with one for social innovation. That is the experimentation for team and organizational architectures to have more appropriately employed decision rights, accountability mechanisms, resource management, and role agility &#8212; all in the service of empowering knowledge creation and application in a more expedient, practical and generative fashion when called for.</p>
<p>Finally, economic innovation is perhaps recognized as an equally stubborn yet central player in creating an optimal future for balancing the incentives for payers, payees, and providers. Agile business and operating models, governance mechanisms, and investment models will need to be created and adjusted as the field continues to mature at different stages of capability and practice.</p>
<p>Posted By Mark Sullivan, PhD</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/reflections-on-day-1-of-the-world-medical-innovation-forum/">Reflections on Day 1 of the World Medical Innovation Forum</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Hopes for Alzheimer’s disease featured at World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/new-hopes-for-alzheimers-disease-featured-at-world-medical-innovation-forum/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 16:41:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1478</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>New Hopes for Alzheimer’s disease featured at World Medical Innovation Forum Six Reasons why the Anti-Amyloid Treatment in Asymptomatic Alzheimer’s study (the &#8220;A4 study&#8221;) with Reisa Sperling, MD, BWH, Director of Clinical Research, Memory Disorders Unit, Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital is making Strides 1. The novel concept of treating patients before they are symptomatic Instead ... <a title="New Hopes for Alzheimer’s disease featured at World Medical Innovation Forum" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/new-hopes-for-alzheimers-disease-featured-at-world-medical-innovation-forum/" aria-label="More on New Hopes for Alzheimer’s disease featured at World Medical Innovation Forum">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/new-hopes-for-alzheimers-disease-featured-at-world-medical-innovation-forum/">New Hopes for Alzheimer’s disease featured at World Medical Innovation Forum</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>New Hopes for Alzheimer’s disease featured at World Medical Innovation Forum</strong></p>
<p>Six Reasons why the Anti-Amyloid Treatment in Asymptomatic Alzheimer’s study (the &#8220;A4 study&#8221;) with Reisa Sperling, MD, BWH, Director of Clinical Research, Memory Disorders Unit,<br />
Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital is making Strides</p>
<p><strong>1. The novel concept of treating patients before they are symptomatic</strong></p>
<p>Instead of waiting until patients develop full blown Alzheimer’s disease, the A4 study has been proactive. The A4 study targets older individuals with evidence of early Alzheimer’s changes in their brain but who do not yet have symptoms of Alzheimer’s disease, in hopes of preventing memory decline. This is the first time in history of AD research that a prevention trial has been undertaken in asymptomatic individuals identified with biomarker evidence of Alzheimer’s disease.</p>
<p><strong>2. The use of an anti-amyloid antibody</strong></p>
<p>The humanized monoclonal antibody, solanezumab, which has already be testing in two Phase 3 trials at the stage of Alzheimers’ dementia, binds to soluble forms of amyloid and can help its clearance of it from the brain. The previous trials in dementia patients showed some modest evidence of slowing of decline in the mildest subgroup. The hope is treating 5-10 years earlier with this antibody can bend the curve of decline.</p>
<p><strong>3. It’s empowering patients to manage their health and potential risk for developing AD</strong></p>
<p>The A4 study has made people more aware of options for treatment and potential cures in the works. Alzheimer&#8217;s disease is not a death sentence and clinicians and researchers are working hard through this trial and other to get closer to finding a cure.</p>
<p><strong>4.It’s getting people talking about Alzheimer’s disease (more people learning about what Alzheimer’s actually is, informing families at risk, communities, etc.)</strong></p>
<p>Almost everyone knows someone, or has a friend who has known someone affected by Alzheimer’s disease. More and more people are hearing the words “Alzheimer’s disease” in conversation but do not exactly know what it means. These trials are giving the disease much more press, and increasing awareness. This is beneficial in many aspects such as fundraising for research and recruiting people for this study.</p>
<p><strong>5. It involves collaborations</strong></p>
<p>The A4 trial is sponsored by a public-private partnership involving the National Institutes of Health, Eli Lilly, and several philanthropic organizations. The A4 study is also working with other prevention trial efforts in genetic at-risk populations around the world to ensure they can learn as much as possible from these trials.</p>
<p><strong>6. It emphasizes its urgency</strong></p>
<p>Most people are not aware of the urgency of action for Alzheimer’s disease. One of nine people over the age of 65 has the disease, and as our population ages, Alzheimer’s disease is becoming a public health epidemic. If we do not do something about it, this disease has the potential to bankrupt our healthcare system. It is critical to increase awareness and send the message something that can be done to cure Alzheimer’s if we act now. Attend this year’s World Medical Innovation Forum on April 27-29, 2015. Click here (medforum17.wpengine.com) to learn more.</p>
<p>Piece by Alessandra Maahs, BWH iHub</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/new-hopes-for-alzheimers-disease-featured-at-world-medical-innovation-forum/">New Hopes for Alzheimer’s disease featured at World Medical Innovation Forum</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Spotlighting Innovation at Our Inaugural Forum</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/spotlighting-innovation-at-our-inaugural-forum/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 16:00:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1441</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the United States, every phase of healthcare is being fundamentally restructured. As these changes take place, the need for disruptive research and applied innovation will remain an enduring priority. Partners HealthCare, as the largest single academic research entity, is convening leaders from around the globe to consider the future of collaborative innovation as part ... <a title="Spotlighting Innovation at Our Inaugural Forum" class="read-more" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/spotlighting-innovation-at-our-inaugural-forum/" aria-label="More on Spotlighting Innovation at Our Inaugural Forum">Read more</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/spotlighting-innovation-at-our-inaugural-forum/">Spotlighting Innovation at Our Inaugural Forum</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Partners_FORUM_2015_LOGO_550x321.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1442" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Partners_FORUM_2015_LOGO_550x321.jpg" alt="Spotlighting Innovation" width="550" height="321" /></a></p>
<p>Throughout the United States, every phase of healthcare is being fundamentally restructured. As these changes take place, the need for disruptive research and applied innovation will remain an enduring priority. Partners HealthCare, as the largest single academic research entity, is convening leaders from around the globe to consider the future of collaborative innovation as part of the inaugural World Medical Innovation Forum.</p>
<p>The event, an international gathering of more than 1,000 senior decision-makers from the life sciences, investment, clinical, entrepreneurial and academic communities, will be taking place in Boston from April 27-29, 2015. The Forum is rooted in the belief that no matter how greatly the health care industry transforms, health care providers remain committed to working together to improve patient lives through innovation.</p>
<p>The focus for this first World Forum will be the neurosciences. The Forum will present an unprecedented opportunity for senior executives, investors, entrepreneurs, physicians and scientists on the forefront of medical advancement to discuss the most compelling advances in neuroscience technology, care and research, as well as the importance of innovation throughout health care.</p>
<p>Keynote speakers will include CEOs from some of the most important companies in the neurosciences and healthcare in general, such as General Electric, Aetna, Amgen, Biogen Idec, Boston Scientific, Genzyme, Vertex Pharmaceuticals and many more. Also keynoting the Forum are dozens of internationally recognized Partners’ leaders and Harvard Medical School Faculty such as Atul Gawande, M.D., and Rudy Tanzi, Ph.D.</p>
<p>More than 100 expert speakers will discuss advances and unmet needs in areas such as multiple sclerosis, Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s diseases, depression, schizophrenia, autism, stroke and sleep disorders. The Forum will also highlight new tools and interventions in genome editing, gene therapy, neurostimulation, neurodegeneration, population management, neuroimaging and neurological biomarkers.</p>
<p>In addition to examining the cutting-edge issues in the field, the Forum will feature the “Disruptive Dozen” – 12 emerging technologies with the potential to revolutionize the neurosciences over the next decade.</p>
<p>Through its unprecedented roster of presenters and top attendees, the hope is that meaningful engagement throughout the World Forum will spark the new partnerships needed to address longstanding unmet needs and lay the groundwork for future collaborations.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/spotlighting-innovation-at-our-inaugural-forum/">Spotlighting Innovation at Our Inaugural Forum</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-agenda-21/">2021 World Medical Innovation Forum</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
